<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation]]></title><description><![CDATA[Supporting, Advancing, and Developing the PHP Language]]></description><updated>2025-08-18T07:57:31+00:00</updated><entry><author><name>James Titcumb</name><uri>https://phpc.social/@asgrim</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing the Pre-Release of the PHP Installer for Extensions (PIE)]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're thrilled to introduce the pre-release of the PHP Installer for Extensions (PIE) – <a href="https://github.com/php/pie"><strong>github.com/php/pie</strong></a>!</p>

<p>PIE aims to simplify managing PHP extensions by providing a modern, flexible alternative to PECL and treating extensions as first-class citizens in the PHP ecosystem.</p>

<blockquote>
PIE development is commissioned by the <a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/tech/php"><strong>Sovereign Tech Agency</strong></a>.
</blockquote>

<p>This initial pre-release is available as a <a href="https://github.com/php/pie/releases/tag/0.2.0">PHAR download</a>, and we invite you to take it for a spin and share your feedback. While this release is an exciting milestone, we know there's a lot more work ahead to make PIE ready for widespread use, so your feedback is invaluable. If you encounter any issues, or have any questions, feel free to open an <a href="https://github.com/php/pie/issues">issue on GitHub</a>, and help us shape the future of PIE.</p>

<h2 id="why-pie%3F">Why PIE?</h2>

<p>With PIE, the process of managing PHP extensions becomes more streamlined. Extensions are distributed via <a href="https://packagist.org/extensions">Packagist</a> just like regular PHP packages! It makes the installation and update process quite familiar if you already use Composer.</p>

<p>We’re working to make PIE stronger and easier to use. We’re improving how PHP extensions are managed and using ideas from Composer to make the process smoother.</p>

<h2 id="are-you-an-extension-author%3F">Are you an extension author?</h2>

<p>Extensions do need to be made compatible with PIE by adding a <code>composer.json</code> (more instructions <a href="https://github.com/php/pie/blob/main/docs/extension-maintainers.md">here</a>), and submitting it to <a href="https://packagist.org/packages/submit">Packagist</a>. Once a package has added support for PIE, it will appear on the Packagist <a href="https://packagist.org/extensions">Extensions list</a> page.</p>

<p>💜️🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/19/pie-pre-release/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/19/pie-pre-release/</id><updated>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry></feed>
