<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation]]></title><description><![CDATA[Supporting, Advancing, and Developing the PHP Language]]></description><updated>2025-12-02T13:45:56+00:00</updated><entry><author><name>Nils Adermann</name><uri>https://x.com/naderman</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation is Seeking a New Executive Director]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're opening the search for our next Executive Director, marking an important milestone in the continued growth and evolution of the PHP Foundation.</p>

<p>After four years at the helm of the PHP Foundation, <a href="https://x.com/pronskiy">Roman Pronskiy</a> will conclude his tenure as Executive Director in early 2026. Roman founded and helped build the Foundation from the ground up into a stable, well-run organization, expanded our team of core developers, and deepened collaboration across the PHP ecosystem. As his role at JetBrains grows, Roman has decided to focus his efforts there while continuing to support the PHP Foundation’s next chapter.</p>

<p>We’re immensely grateful for Roman’s vision and leadership, which shaped the foundation’s first years and set a strong course for the future. He will continue serving on the Board of Directors as JetBrains’ representative, providing continuity as JetBrains remains a platinum sponsor and steadfast supporter of PHP. Roman will work closely with the incoming Executive Director to make the transition smooth and complete.</p>

<p>The Board has formed a search committee consisting of two board members Sebastian Bergmann and Nils Adermann as well as two community representatives Lorna Jane Mitchell and Ben Ramsey. The search committee will manage the selection process and find a leader who can build on the Foundation's momentum and guide us through our next phase of growth.</p>

<p><strong>What we're looking for:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Strong leadership experience in open source communities</li>
<li>Deep knowledge of the PHP ecosystem</li>
<li>Excellent project management and communication skills</li>
<li>Strategic thinking and a vision for the foundation's future</li>
<li>Experience working with diverse stakeholders and sponsors</li>
</ul>

<p>This is an opportunity to shape the future of one of the world's most widely-used programming languages and support the vibrant community that sustains it.</p>

<p><strong>How you can help:</strong></p>

<p>We need the PHP community's help in finding the right person for this role. If you know someone who would be an excellent Executive Director for the PHP Foundation, please encourage them to apply or reach out to us directly.</p>

<p>The full job description and application details can be found below.</p>

<p>For questions about the search process, please contact <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x65;&#x64;&#x2d;&#x73;&#x65;&#x61;&#x72;&#99;&#104;&#64;&#116;&#104;&#101;&#112;&#104;&#112;&#46;&#102;&#111;&#117;&#110;&#100;&#97;tio&#x6e;">ed-search@thephp.foundation</a>.</p>

<p>🐘💜</p>

<h1 id="executive-director-%E2%80%93-the-php-foundation">Executive Director – The PHP Foundation</h1>

<p><strong>Position Type:</strong> Full-time or Part-time (if part-time, responsibility includes hiring necessary staff to fulfill the complete role)<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Remote, no visa opportunity<br />
<strong>Reports To:</strong> Board of Directors<br />
<strong>Term:</strong> 1 year, renewable subject to annual performance evaluation<br />
<strong>Compensation:</strong> Total Compensation $90,000-$160,000 (Base: $90,000 - $105,000 USD / year, Performance based bonus up to $65,000 USD)</p>

<h2 id="about-the-php-foundation">About The PHP Foundation</h2>

<p>PHP is one of the world's most widely-used programming languages, powering millions of websites and applications. The PHP Foundation is a collective of people and organizations relying on the PHP language. Its mission is to ensure the long-term prosperity of the PHP language.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation focuses on providing financial support and guidance to PHP language developers to support its goals of improving the language for its users, providing high-quality maintenance, and improving the PHP language project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation aims to promote the public image of the PHP language in the interest of retaining existing and gaining new users and contributors.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation operates as a collective under the Open Source Collective, a 501(c)(6) non-profit organization based in the United States. The Executive Director role will be structured as a contractor position with this entity.</p>

<h2 id="the-role">The Role</h2>

<p>The Executive Director serves as the operational leader of the PHP Foundation, defining its strategic vision and translating it into reality while managing day-to-day operations and serving as the primary bridge between the Board, staff, community, and sponsors.</p>

<p>While the programming language PHP is over 30 years old, the PHP Foundation was only created in 2021. The Executive Director will be responsible for maturing the foundation’s internal structure and will play a crucial role in ensuring the foundation can effectively support this vital ecosystem.</p>

<h2 id="key-responsibilities">Key Responsibilities</h2>

<h3 id="strategic-leadership">Strategic Leadership</h3>

<ul>
<li>Develop strategic initiatives for the PHP Foundation and the PHP language in alignment with the foundation's mission and goals</li>
<li>Annual presentation of new strategy and evaluation of previous year’s performance to the Board for approval</li>
<li>Develop and implement marketing strategies to fulfill the foundation’s mission to promote the public image of the PHP language</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="fundraising-%26-financial-oversight">Fundraising &amp; Financial Oversight</h3>

<ul>
<li>Responsible for fundraising to provide the budget for implementing proposed strategy</li>
<li>Manage finances, budgets and fundraising</li>
<li>Prepare quarterly operations summaries and financial statements</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="operational-management">Operational Management</h3>

<ul>
<li>Manage day-to-day operations, staff, including contracted PHP core developers</li>
<li>Oversee hiring, performance management, and development of Foundation staff</li>
<li>Ensure efficient execution of foundation programs and initiatives</li>
<li>Provide regular updates at board meetings</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="stakeholder-relations">Stakeholder Relations</h3>

<ul>
<li>Represent the foundation externally and maintain relationships with sponsors, partners, and community stakeholders</li>
<li>Serve as the public face of the foundation at conferences and community events</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="required-qualifications">Required Qualifications</h2>

<ul>
<li>Demonstrated leadership experience in relevant organizations or communities</li>
<li>Strong project management and organizational skills</li>
<li>Excellent written and verbal communication skills</li>
<li>Financial management and budgeting experience</li>
<li>Proven ability to work with diverse stakeholders and build consensus</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="additional-experience-we-value">Additional Experience We Value</h2>

<ul>
<li>Experience in free and open source software communities</li>
<li>Knowledge of the PHP ecosystem and its community dynamics</li>
<li>Experience in fundraising or sponsor relations</li>
<li>Network within the PHP community</li>
<li>Experience managing remote teams</li>
<li>Public speaking and presentation skills</li>
<li>Previous experience in open source foundation governance</li>
<li>Experience in or working with public relations or marketing</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="compensation-and-terms">Compensation and Terms</h2>

<ul>
<li>Contracting position with Open Source Collective 501(c)(6)</li>
<li>Fully remote, no visa opportunities</li>
<li>At full-time, base pay of $90,000 - $105,000 / year, invoiced monthly</li>
<li>Annual performance based bonus up to $65,000 tied especially to fundraising goals</li>
<li>Travel to a few community events per year required with expenses covered, additional travel encouraged if event organizers cover expenses</li>
<li>Renewable annually based on performance and mutual agreement with Board of Directors</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="selection-process">Selection Process</h2>

<p>A search committee of Board members and community representatives is managing the candidate search and evaluation process. The process includes:</p>

<ol>
<li>Application review and initial screening by the search committee</li>
<li>Interviews with the search committee</li>
<li>Committee presents top candidates to the full Board of Directors</li>
<li>Presentation of vision and strategy to the full Board</li>
<li>Final selection by full Board vote (2/3 majority required)</li>
</ol>

<p>Applications will be accepted on a rolling basis until 2025-12-15.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-apply">How to Apply</h2>

<p>Please fill in our <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1V-OHLizny6ob8BivWJv7KneHToPyRKE6Whdmnn_hl3M/edit"><strong>Google form</strong></a> including:</p>

<ul>
<li>Cover letter describing your interest and relevant experience</li>
<li>Resume/CV</li>
<li>Brief vision statement (500-1000 words) addressing: your understanding of the foundation's current position, key opportunities and challenges you see for the foundation, and your approach to the role</li>
<li>During the interview process we will ask you to provide at least 3 references who we can contact</li>
</ul>

<p>Questions about the position or application process? Contact: <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x65;&#x64;&#x2d;&#x73;&#x65;&#x61;&#x72;&#99;&#104;&#64;&#116;&#104;&#101;&#112;&#104;&#112;&#46;&#102;&#111;&#117;&#110;&#100;&#97;tio&#x6e;">ed-search@thephp.foundation</a>.</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/11/10/seeking-new-executive-director/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/11/10/seeking-new-executive-director/</id><updated>Mon, 10 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><author><name>Nils Adermann</name><uri>https://twitter.com/naderman</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation application form for 2025 is now open]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The PHP Foundation is a non-profit organization, started in 2021 by Acquia, Automattic, Craft CMS, JetBrains, Laravel, PrestaShop, Private Packagist, Symfony, Tideways, and Zend by Perforce with a mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>

<p>The foundation pays <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/#core_developers">10 developers</a> to work on the language. See what the foundation achieved in 2023 in the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/02/26/transparency-and-impact-report-2023/">Impact and transparency report</a>.</p>

<p>We’re opening a new round of applications for developer positions. We intend to decide on who we will hire by the end of October. If selected, you would start your work January 1st, 2025&#46;</p>

<p>The application form will be <strong>open until October 10, 2024</strong>.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Apply</a>
</p>

<div class="alert">
    <span class="inline-block font-bold">Note: This is not a job for PHP developers or aspiring PHP developers.</span><br> 
The development of PHP is done in the С programming language, and requires proficiency in system programming.
</div>

<h2 id="note%3A-team-size-is-unlikely-to-grow">Note: Team size is unlikely to grow</h2>

<p>While we won’t rule out the possibility of expanding our team, it’s likely we won’t pay more than the current number of 10 developers. Mindful of our budget limitations, we may rather consider restructuring or adjusting our team to make space for any outstanding applications that better help us meet our goals.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-the-requirements%3F">What are the requirements?</h2>

<p>As before, we require previous experience in PHP core development. Ideally you should have all, but at least some of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pull-requests / commits to <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/">php/php-src</a></li>
<li>Experience in writing PHP extensions</li>
<li>Participation in PHP mailing lists</li>
<li>Contributions to other open-source projects</li>
</ul>

<p>This time, however, we have a clearer idea of the tasks that can be engaged in and so the pool of considered candidates will be wider.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-you-going-to-work-on%3F">What are you going to work on?</h2>

<p>Strategic areas we’d like you to work on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Security</li>
<li>Performance</li>
<li>Infrastructure</li>
<li>Web APIs (json, PDO, streams, etc.)</li>
</ul>

<p>This is not an exhaustive list. We encourage you to <strong>provide as detailed a description of what you want to work on as possible</strong>.</p>

<p>Our primary selection criterion is <strong>pragmatism</strong>. We place greater emphasis on solutions that improve the developer experience and benefit businesses that rely on PHP, rather than new syntax features.</p>

<p>Out of scope:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pure documentation work</li>
<li>PHP packages</li>
<li>Websites</li>
<li>Translations</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-does-working-for-the-php-foundation-look-like%3F">What does working for the PHP Foundation look like?</h2>

<p>Working for the PHP Foundation offers a lot of freedom, but it also requires discipline. Your work will roughly consist of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>40% Triaging issues and fixing bugs</li>
<li>30% Working on strategic areas</li>
<li>20% Code reviews</li>
<li>&#62;10% Preparing RFCs and developing new language features</li>
</ul>

<p>As you can see, developing new RFCs is a fairly small part of the job. Most of the work is typical maintenance of an open source project.</p>

<p>We are a fully distributed team. You can work from any place<strong>&#42;</strong> and at any time. All communication is asynchronous via Slack, GitHub, and Email. We meet for synchronous calls 1-2 times a month.</p>

<p>Your work should be in line with the foundation’s mission statement, and we expect you to follow <a href="https://thephp.foundation/code-of-conduct/">the code of conduct</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>PHP Foundation Mission Statement</strong></p>
  
  <p>The PHP Foundation is a collective of people and organizations relying on the PHP language. Its mission is to ensure the long-term prosperity of the PHP language. The PHP Foundation focuses on providing financial support and guidance to PHP language developers to support its goals of improving the language for its users, providing high-quality maintenance, and improving the PHP language project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors. The PHP Foundation aims to promote the public image of the PHP language in the interest of retaining existing and gaining new users and contributors.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em><strong>&#42;</strong> We do not consider applications from persons residing in sanctioned territories.</em></p>

<h2 id="how-to-apply%3F">How to apply?</h2>

<p>Submit your application now and we will get back to you shortly. If you have any questions or suggestions, reach out to contact@thephp.foundation.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" target="_blank" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Open submission form</a>
</p>

<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeYNVQoK2r9c6EtoMnDaIpLzDc95egt1a1mcfiHTovqMDhFuw/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1693" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/17/application-form-2025/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/17/application-form-2025/</id><updated>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><author><name>Nils Adermann</name><uri>https://twitter.com/naderman</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[We Are Looking for Developers to Join the PHP Foundation]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Working on an open-source project which is used by millions of developers and which is trusted by hundreds of thousands of businesses around the world. Getting paid for this work and not having a burnout. Sounds like a dream, doesn't it? But this is exactly the opportunity that the PHP Foundation provides to those who would like to develop and maintain the PHP language.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation is a non-profit organization, started in 2021 by Acquia, Automattic, Craft CMS, JetBrains, Laravel, PrestaShop, Private Packagist, Symfony, Tideways, and Zend by Perforce with a mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>

<p>Since April 2022, the foundation pays <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/#core_developers">six developers</a> to work on the language. See what the foundation accomplished in 2022 in the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/11/22/transparency-and-impact-report-2022/">Impact and transparency report</a>.</p>

<h2 id="we-are-opening-applications-for-new-positions-at%26nbsp%3Bthe%26nbsp%3Bphp%26nbsp%3Bfoundation">We are opening applications for new positions at&nbsp;the&nbsp;PHP&nbsp;Foundation</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation is almost two years old, and we are gradually introducing structure into our activities and organizing processes. We’re opening a new round of applications for developer positions. We plan to open applications every September from now on, so if you are unable to apply now, you will have another chance next year. We intend to decide on who we will hire by the end of October. If selected, you would start your work January 1st, 2024.</p>

<p>The application form will be <strong>open until September 30, 2023</strong>.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Apply</a>
</p>

<div class="alert">
    <span class="inline-block font-bold">Note: This is not a job for PHP developers or aspiring PHP developers.</span><br> 
The development of PHP is done in the С programming language, and requires proficiency in system programming.
</div>

<h2 id="what-are-the-requirements%3F">What are the requirements?</h2>

<p>As before, we require previous experience in PHP core development. Ideally you should have all, but at least some of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pull-requests / commits to <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/">php/php-src</a></li>
<li>Experience in writing PHP extensions</li>
<li>Participation in PHP mailing lists</li>
<li>Contributions to other open-source projects</li>
</ul>

<p>This time, however, we have a clearer idea of the tasks that can be engaged in and so the pool of considered candidates will be wider.</p>

<h2 id="what-am-i-going-to-work-on%3F">What am I going to work on?</h2>

<p>Strategic areas we’d like you to work on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Security</li>
<li>Performance</li>
<li>Infrastructure</li>
<li>Web APIs (json, PDO, streams, etc.)</li>
<li>Documentation</li>
</ul>

<p>This is not an exhaustive list, and if you would like to do something else, make sure to mention it in the form. The main criteria is a pragmatic approach. In this sense, we adhere to the position that Rasmus&nbsp;Lerdorf, the author of PHP, voiced back in 2014:</p>

<pre><code class="Text">And rather than piling on language features with the main justification
being that other languages have them, I would love to see more focus on
practical solutions to real problems. The password_hash() addition in
5.5 is a good example of addressing a real Web problem.
…
I know these are much harder and less sexy than adding a couple
of tokens to the yacc grammar, but when we start looking at a new major
release this is what I hear from people who are running PHP in
production environments are looking for. Language features are nice, if
they are well thought out, but significant infrastructure improvements
are nicer.
</code></pre>

<p><em><a href="https://news-web.php.net/php.internals/71525">https://news-web.php.net/php.internals/71525</a></em></p>

<h2 id="what-does-working-for-the-php-foundation-look-like%3F">What does working for the PHP foundation look like?</h2>

<p>Working for the PHP Foundation offers a lot of freedom, but it also requires discipline. Your work will roughly consist of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>40% Triaging issues and fixing bugs</li>
<li>30% Working on strategic areas</li>
<li>20% Code reviews</li>
<li>10% Preparing RFCs and developing new language features</li>
</ul>

<p>As you can see, developing new RFCs is a fairly small part of the job. Most of the work is a typical maintenance of an open source project.</p>

<p>We are a fully distributed team. You can work from any place* and at any time. All communication is asynchronous via GitHub, Slack, and Email. We meet for synchronous calls 1-2 times a month.</p>

<p><em><strong>&#42;</strong> We do not consider applications from persons residing in sanctioned territories.</em></p>

<p>Your work should be in line with the foundation’s mission statement, and we expect you to follow <a href="https://thephp.foundation/code-of-conduct/">the code of conduct</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>PHP Foundation Mission Statement</strong></p>
  
  <p>The PHP Foundation is a collective of people and organizations relying on the PHP language. Its mission is to ensure the long-term prosperity of the PHP language. The PHP Foundation focuses on providing financial support and guidance to PHP language developers to support its goals of improving the language for its users, providing high-quality maintenance, and improving the PHP language project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors. The PHP Foundation aims to promote the public image of the PHP language in the interest of retaining existing and gaining new users and contributors.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="how-to-apply%3F">How to apply?</h2>

<p>Submit your application now and we will get back to you shortly. If you have any questions or suggestions, reach out to contact@thephp.foundation.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" target="_blank" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Open submission form</a>
</p>

<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeYNVQoK2r9c6EtoMnDaIpLzDc95egt1a1mcfiHTovqMDhFuw/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1693" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/09/06/application-form-2023/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/09/06/application-form-2023/</id><updated>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry></feed>
