<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation]]></title><description><![CDATA[Supporting, Advancing, and Developing the PHP Language]]></description><updated>2026-02-18T16:03:43+00:00</updated><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Core Security Audit Results]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The PHP Foundation is pleased to announce the completion of a comprehensive security audit of the PHP source code (<a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a>), <strong>commissioned by the <a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/">Sovereign Tech Agency</a></strong>.</p>

<p>This initiative was organized in partnership with the <a href="https://ostif.org/">Open Source Technology Improvement Fund</a> (OSTIF) and executed by the esteemed security group <a href="https://www.quarkslab.com/">Quarkslab</a>.</p>

<h2 id="audit-overview">Audit Overview</h2>

<p>Conducted over a two-month period in 2024, the audit encompassed:</p>

<ul>
<li>Development of a threat model tailored to php-src</li>
<li>Manual code reviews</li>
<li>Dynamic testing procedures</li>
<li>Cryptographic assessments</li>
</ul>

<p>The collaboration between Quarkslab’s auditors and PHP maintainers ensured a thorough examination of the codebase.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>⚠️</em><br />
  Due to budget constraints, the recent security audit focused on the most critical components of the PHP source code rather than the entire codebase. Organizations interested in sponsoring a comprehensive audit or additional assessments are encouraged to <a href="&#109;&#x61;i&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x63;&#111;&#x6e;&#x74;&#97;&#x63;t&#64;&#x74;&#104;&#101;&#x70;&#104;&#x70;&#x2e;&#102;&#x6f;&#x75;&#110;&#x64;a&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#110;">contact us</a>!<br />
  <em>⚠️</em></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="key-findings">Key Findings</h2>

<p>The audit identified 27 issues, with 17 having security implications:</p>

<ul>
<li>3 High-severity</li>
<li>5 Medium-severity</li>
<li>9 Low-severity</li>
</ul>

<p>Additionally, 10 informational findings were reported.</p>

<p>Notably, four vulnerabilities received CVE identifiers:</p>

<ul>
<li>CVE-2024-9026: Log tampering vulnerability in PHP-FPM, allowing potential manipulation or removal of characters from log messages.</li>
<li>CVE-2024-8925: Flaw in PHP’s multipart form data parsing, potentially leading to data misinterpretation.</li>
<li>CVE-2024-8929: Issue where a malicious MySQL server could cause the client to disclose heap content from other SQL requests.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="recommendations-and-resolutions">Recommendations and Resolutions</h2>

<p>Quarkslab’s report commended the overall high quality and specification adherence of the php/php-src project.</p>

<p>The PHP development team has addressed all identified issues. Users are strongly encouraged to upgrade to the latest PHP versions to benefit from these security enhancements.</p>

<h2 id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments</h2>

<p>We extend our gratitude to the individuals and organizations that made this audit possible:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>The PHP Foundation Team and PHP maintainers:</strong><br />
Jakub Zelenka, Arnaud Le Blanc, Niels Dossche, Ilija Tovilo, Stas Malyshev, Dmitry Stogov, Derick&nbsp;Rethans, and Roman Pronskiy.</li>
<li><strong>Quarkslab Team:</strong><br />
Angèle Bossuat, Julio Loayza Meneses, Mihail Kirov, Sebastien Rolland, Ramtine Tofighi Shirazi.</li>
<li><strong>Sovereign Tech Agency:</strong><br />
Abigail Garner and the team – for commissioning the audit and all the help.</li>
<li><strong>OSTIF:</strong><br />
Amir Montazery, Derek Zimmer, Helen Woeste – for organizing the collaboration.</li>
</ul>

<p>This audit underscores our commitment to enhancing PHP’s security and reliability. We remain dedicated to ongoing improvements and collaborations to ensure PHP’s robustness for the global development community.</p>

<h2 id="further-reading">Further Reading</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="/assets/files/24-07-1730-REP-V1.4_temp.pdf">Audit Report</a></li>
<li><a href="https://ostif.org/php-audit-complete/">OSTIF Blog</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog.quarkslab.com/security-audit-of-php-src.html">Quarkslab Blog</a></li>
</ul>

<p>If your company is interested in commissioning another round of security audit, please contact The PHP Foundation team: <a href="&#109;&#x61;i&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x63;&#111;&#x6e;&#x74;&#97;&#x63;t&#64;&#x74;&#104;&#101;&#x70;&#104;&#x70;&#x2e;&#102;&#x6f;&#x75;&#110;&#x64;a&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#110;">contact@thephp.foundation</a>.</p>

<p>🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/04/10/php-core-security-audit-results/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/04/10/php-core-security-audit-results/</id><updated>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><author><name>Nils Adermann</name><uri>https://twitter.com/naderman</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[We Are Looking for Developers to Join the PHP Foundation]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Working on an open-source project which is used by millions of developers and which is trusted by hundreds of thousands of businesses around the world. Getting paid for this work and not having a burnout. Sounds like a dream, doesn't it? But this is exactly the opportunity that the PHP Foundation provides to those who would like to develop and maintain the PHP language.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation is a non-profit organization, started in 2021 by Acquia, Automattic, Craft CMS, JetBrains, Laravel, PrestaShop, Private Packagist, Symfony, Tideways, and Zend by Perforce with a mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>

<p>Since April 2022, the foundation pays <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/#core_developers">six developers</a> to work on the language. See what the foundation accomplished in 2022 in the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/11/22/transparency-and-impact-report-2022/">Impact and transparency report</a>.</p>

<h2 id="we-are-opening-applications-for-new-positions-at%26nbsp%3Bthe%26nbsp%3Bphp%26nbsp%3Bfoundation">We are opening applications for new positions at&nbsp;the&nbsp;PHP&nbsp;Foundation</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation is almost two years old, and we are gradually introducing structure into our activities and organizing processes. We’re opening a new round of applications for developer positions. We plan to open applications every September from now on, so if you are unable to apply now, you will have another chance next year. We intend to decide on who we will hire by the end of October. If selected, you would start your work January 1st, 2024.</p>

<p>The application form will be <strong>open until September 30, 2023</strong>.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Apply</a>
</p>

<div class="alert">
    <span class="inline-block font-bold">Note: This is not a job for PHP developers or aspiring PHP developers.</span><br> 
The development of PHP is done in the С programming language, and requires proficiency in system programming.
</div>

<h2 id="what-are-the-requirements%3F">What are the requirements?</h2>

<p>As before, we require previous experience in PHP core development. Ideally you should have all, but at least some of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pull-requests / commits to <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/">php/php-src</a></li>
<li>Experience in writing PHP extensions</li>
<li>Participation in PHP mailing lists</li>
<li>Contributions to other open-source projects</li>
</ul>

<p>This time, however, we have a clearer idea of the tasks that can be engaged in and so the pool of considered candidates will be wider.</p>

<h2 id="what-am-i-going-to-work-on%3F">What am I going to work on?</h2>

<p>Strategic areas we’d like you to work on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Security</li>
<li>Performance</li>
<li>Infrastructure</li>
<li>Web APIs (json, PDO, streams, etc.)</li>
<li>Documentation</li>
</ul>

<p>This is not an exhaustive list, and if you would like to do something else, make sure to mention it in the form. The main criteria is a pragmatic approach. In this sense, we adhere to the position that Rasmus&nbsp;Lerdorf, the author of PHP, voiced back in 2014:</p>

<pre><code class="Text">And rather than piling on language features with the main justification
being that other languages have them, I would love to see more focus on
practical solutions to real problems. The password_hash() addition in
5.5 is a good example of addressing a real Web problem.
…
I know these are much harder and less sexy than adding a couple
of tokens to the yacc grammar, but when we start looking at a new major
release this is what I hear from people who are running PHP in
production environments are looking for. Language features are nice, if
they are well thought out, but significant infrastructure improvements
are nicer.
</code></pre>

<p><em><a href="https://news-web.php.net/php.internals/71525">https://news-web.php.net/php.internals/71525</a></em></p>

<h2 id="what-does-working-for-the-php-foundation-look-like%3F">What does working for the PHP foundation look like?</h2>

<p>Working for the PHP Foundation offers a lot of freedom, but it also requires discipline. Your work will roughly consist of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>40% Triaging issues and fixing bugs</li>
<li>30% Working on strategic areas</li>
<li>20% Code reviews</li>
<li>10% Preparing RFCs and developing new language features</li>
</ul>

<p>As you can see, developing new RFCs is a fairly small part of the job. Most of the work is a typical maintenance of an open source project.</p>

<p>We are a fully distributed team. You can work from any place* and at any time. All communication is asynchronous via GitHub, Slack, and Email. We meet for synchronous calls 1-2 times a month.</p>

<p><em><strong>&#42;</strong> We do not consider applications from persons residing in sanctioned territories.</em></p>

<p>Your work should be in line with the foundation’s mission statement, and we expect you to follow <a href="https://thephp.foundation/code-of-conduct/">the code of conduct</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>PHP Foundation Mission Statement</strong></p>
  
  <p>The PHP Foundation is a collective of people and organizations relying on the PHP language. Its mission is to ensure the long-term prosperity of the PHP language. The PHP Foundation focuses on providing financial support and guidance to PHP language developers to support its goals of improving the language for its users, providing high-quality maintenance, and improving the PHP language project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors. The PHP Foundation aims to promote the public image of the PHP language in the interest of retaining existing and gaining new users and contributors.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="how-to-apply%3F">How to apply?</h2>

<p>Submit your application now and we will get back to you shortly. If you have any questions or suggestions, reach out to contact@thephp.foundation.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" target="_blank" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Open submission form</a>
</p>

<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeYNVQoK2r9c6EtoMnDaIpLzDc95egt1a1mcfiHTovqMDhFuw/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1693" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/09/06/application-form-2023/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/09/06/application-form-2023/</id><updated>Wed, 06 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Happy Holidays from&nbsp;The&nbsp;PHP&nbsp;Foundation!]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As 2024 comes to a close, we at the PHP Foundation want to take a moment to thank everyone who has supported us this year. It’s been an incredible journey, and we couldn’t have done it without the amazing PHP community and our generous sponsors.</p>

<h2 id="a-year-of-milestones">A Year of Milestones</h2>

<p>In <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/22/php-foundation-turns-three">its third year</a>, the PHP Foundation has achieved several milestones that have further strengthened the PHP ecosystem: first in a decade <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/22/php-foundation-turns-three/#feature-development-is-only-about-20%25-of-what-the-foundation-team-does">security audit</a>, <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/19/pie-pre-release/">pie</a>, numerous features and improvements for <a href="https://www.php.net/releases/8.4/en.php">PHP 8.4</a>, and much more to come next year!</p>

<h2 id="celebrating-our-sponsors">Celebrating Our Sponsors</h2>

<p>We owe a special thanks to our major sponsors who make our work possible:</p>

<h3 id="platinum">Platinum</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/"><strong>Sovereign Tech Agency</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/"><strong>JetBrains</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://automattic.com/"><strong>Automattic</strong></a></p>

<h3 id="gold">Gold</h3>

<p><a href="https://laravel.com/"><strong>Laravel</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.godaddy.com/"><strong>GoDaddy</strong></a> <strong>&#91;new! ✨&#93;</strong></p>

<h3 id="silver">Silver</h3>

<p><a href="https://packagist.com/"><strong>Private Packagist</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://craftcms.com/"><strong>Craft CMS</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://cybozu.co.jp/en/company/"><strong>Cybozu</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://tideways.com/"><strong>Tideways</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.zend.com/"><strong>Zend by Perforce</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://symfony.com/"><strong>Symfony Corp</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://sentry.io/welcome/"><strong>Sentry</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://manychat.com/"><strong>Manychat</strong></a> <strong>&#91;new! ✨&#93;</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.mercari.com/"><strong>Mercari Inc.</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="http://Les-Tilleuls.coop"><strong>Les-Tilleuls.coop</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://www.pixiv.net/en/"><strong>pixiv Inc.</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://aternos.gmbh/en/"><strong>Aternos GmbH</strong></a></p>

<p><a href="https://chstudio.fr/en/homepage/"><strong>CH Studio</strong></a></p>

<p>Big thanks to newly joined major sponsors: <a href="https://www.godaddy.com/"><strong>GoDaddy</strong></a> and <a href="https://manychat.com/"><strong>Manychat</strong></a>!</p>

<p>Your contributions enable us to support developers, fund crucial projects, and ensure PHP is a modern and reliable choice for web development.</p>

<p>If you are yet to decide on sponsoring the foundation, <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/30/call-fo-sponsors/">here</a> you can find information on how to join us and why it matters.</p>

<h2 id="wishing-you-joyful-holidays-%E2%9C%A8">Wishing You Joyful Holidays ✨</h2>

<p>To everyone in the PHP community, we wish you a joyful holiday season filled with warmth, happiness, and a well-deserved break. Thank you for your support, passion, and commitment to PHP.</p>

<p>Here’s to a wonderful 2025! 🥂</p>

<p>Warm wishes,<br />
The PHP Foundation<br />
🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/12/23/happy-holidays-from-the-php-foundation/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/12/23/happy-holidays-from-the-php-foundation/</id><updated>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Proud to Be Community Sponsors of Laracon EU and Laracon India]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The PHP Foundation is thrilled to announce our community sponsorship of both Laracon EU and Laracon India! We believe in the power of in-person connections and are excited to support these conferences as they bring together PHP enthusiasts from around the world.</p>

<h2 id="laracon-eu"><a href="https://laracon.eu/">Laracon EU</a></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Location:</strong> Amsterdam, Netherlands</li>
<li><strong>Date:</strong> February 3–4</li>
<li><strong>Meet us:</strong> This year at Laracon EU you can meet <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pronskiy">Roman Pronskiy</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sebastian-bergmann-phpunit">Sebastian Bergmann</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nilsadermann/">Nils Adermann</a> from the PHP Foundation board. Can you spot our first ever conference banner?</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="laracon-india"><a href="https://laracon.in/">Laracon India</a></h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>Location:</strong> Ahmedabad, India</li>
<li><strong>Date:</strong> March 8–9</li>
<li><strong>Sponsorship:</strong> Laracon India <a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLScQTQJA9tnpwnED3Af61EyewEr7T2bybBR5GJ3MUd3x52FhrA/viewform">welcomes sponsors</a> who are eager to support the Laravel community and connect with talented developers in India.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="let%27s-collaborate%21">Let's Collaborate!</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation is committed to fostering the growth and development of the PHP ecosystem. We’re excited to collaborate with and support (non-financially) PHP conferences and meetups worldwide!</p>

<p>📩 Get in touch: contact@thephp.foundation.</p>

<p>Here are a few upcoming events to watch for:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.phpconference.co.uk/">PHP UK Conference 2025</a> – London, UK, February 19.</li>
<li><a href="https://phpconference.nl/">Dutch PHP Conference</a> – Amsterdam, March 18–21.</li>
<li><a href="https://phpcon-odawara.jp/2025/">PHP Conference Odawara 2025</a> – Japan, April 12.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.phpday.it/">PHPDay</a> – Verona, May 16-17.</li>
<li><a href="https://phptek.io/">php&#91;tek&#93; 2025</a> – Chicago, IL, USA, May 20-22.</li>
<li><a href="https://summit.phpers.pl/en/">PHPers Summit 2025</a> – Poznań, Poland, 24-25 May.</li>
<li><a href="https://phpconference.com/berlin-en/">International PHP Conference</a> – Berlin, June, 3–5.</li>
</ul>

<p>🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/01/31/laracons/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/01/31/laracons/</id><updated>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation Supports The Open Source Pledge]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The PHP Foundation is proud to announce our support for the Open Source Pledge initiative, launched by Sentry and its partners. This step addresses the sustainability challenges within the Open Source Software (OSS) community, particularly affecting PHP and its ecosystem.</p>

<h2 id="the-open-source-pledge%3A-a-commitment-to-sustainability">The Open Source Pledge: A Commitment to Sustainability</h2>

<p>The Open Source Pledge represents a commitment from member companies to provide meaningful financial support to Open Source maintainers. This initiative aims to prevent maintainer burnout and reduce the risk of high-profile security incidents that can impact the broader tech ecosystem.</p>

<p>The OSS community, including PHP, faces significant challenges:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Security risks:</strong> High-profile incidents like Log4shell, XZ, and Heartbleed have highlighted the potential consequences of under-resourced projects.</li>
<li><strong>Developer burnout:</strong> Many maintainers, often volunteers, are feeling exhausted and leaving the very projects you might be using.</li>
<li><strong>Losing maintainers:</strong> The demanding nature of maintaining open-source software means we’re seeing fewer contributors over time.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation%27s-role">The PHP Foundation's Role</h2>

<p>As the main funder and steward of the PHP language, we’ve seen firsthand how a lack of funding impacts crucial projects. For example:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Core language development:</strong> Keeping PHP up to date and improving it takes a lot of time and expertise.</li>
<li><strong>Security support:</strong> Without enough funding, PHP can’t address vulnerabilities quickly.</li>
<li><strong>Extension maintenance:</strong> Many essential PHP extensions are struggling to find people to maintain them.</li>
<li><strong>Documentation efforts:</strong> Keeping PHP’s extensive documentation current is always a big challenge.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="how-to-join-the-pledge">How to Join the Pledge</h1>

<p>The Open Source Pledge offers a structured approach to supporting OSS with the following requirements:</p>

<ul>
<li>Minimum contribution: $2,000 per year, per developer on staff.</li>
<li>Transparency: Companies should publish annual reports detailing their payments.</li>
<li>Direct impact: Funds go directly to maintainers, supporting their crucial work.</li>
</ul>

<p>Thanks to supporting the PHP Foundation, our major sponsors <a href="https://packagist.com/">Private Packagist</a> and <a href="https://tideways.com/">Tideways</a> are already part of the <a href="https://opensourcepledge.com/">Open Source Pledge</a>.</p>

<h1 id="%5Caction-required%5C-join-the-pledge%5C%21">&#91;Action Required&#93; Join the Pledge&#33;</h1>

<p>We urge PHP-based companies, developers, and organizations to join the Open Source Pledge and <strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">sponsor The PHP Foundation</a></strong>.</p>

<p>To learn more about the Open Source Pledge and how you can participate, visit&nbsp;<a href="https://opensourcepledge.com/">https://opensourcepledge.com/</a>.</p>

<p>Help us spread the word by sharing this post.</p>

<p>💜️ 🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/10/08/open-source-pledge/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/10/08/open-source-pledge/</id><updated>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Foundation Update, June 2022]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>This month PHP foundation staff continues to work on the PHP core and the development of the initiative as a whole. Read on to learn more about what developers have accomplished, new sponsors, and other than financial ways to contribute to the foundation.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We've created an official LinkedIn page: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation/">linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation</a>.
  Subscribe to it and follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thePHPF">@ThePHPF</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="php-core-roundup">PHP Core Roundup</h2>

<p>Here's a summary of what the foundation's developers have been working on lately:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/arnaud-lb">Arnaud Le Blanc</a> revised the RFC and implementation of multi-statement short closures. The proposal is now on vote. Arnaud has also finished the improvements to ini quantity parsing.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/derickr">Derick Rethans</a> continues to fix bugs in DateTime to make working with dates in PHP as reliable as possible.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/Girgias">Gina P. Banyard</a> has made several improvements to the type system: true, null, and false standalaone types have been added, and Disjunctive Normal Form Types put on vote. Gina also made a few fixes in SPL.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/iluuu1994">Ilija Tovilo</a> implemented multiple improvements for enums and put a couple on vote. He also made many fixes, like for instance fixed line numbers in backtrace of multi-line (fluent) function calls.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/bukka">Jakub Zelenka</a> made various fixes and improvements to PHP-FPM and OpenSSL extension.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/kocsismate">Máté Kocsis</a> makes improvements to stubs and other fixes.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>All developers devote significant time to maintenance, including fixing bugs, reducing technical debt, and making life easier for everyone working on PHP.</p>

<p>In the <strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/06/30/php-core-roundup-3/">PHP Roundup #3</a></strong> post by Ayesh, you can find a detailed log of what's been done and discussed regarding the PHP engine during the past month.</p>

<p>This time the list of changes is very long! Applause to all the PHP contributors and release managers.</p>

<p>Tweet at us: <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Ayeshlive">@Ayeshlive</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/pronskiy">@pronskiy</a>.</p>

<h2 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h2>

<p>This month we are glad to welcome a new major sponsor who joined the PHP Foundation’s sponsors herd: <strong><a href="https://www.mollie.com/en">Mollie</a></strong>.  Thank you, folks!</p>

<p>By the way, we have updated the <strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/#sponsors">Sponsors section</a></strong> on our <a href="https://thephp.foundation/">website</a>. It now shows all major contributors sorted by the amount of donation. Kudos to <a href="https://twitter.com/s_panteleev">Sergei Panteleev</a> for this tweak.</p>

<p>Shout-out to everyone for your continued support – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<h2 id="other-ways-to-contribute">Other ways to contribute</h2>

<p>We are receiving many offers of help from every corner of the community. We are grateful for the offers. There are essentially two kinds of offers being made:</p>

<ol>
<li>An offer of development time</li>
<li>An offer of expertise</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="how-to-contribute-development-time%3F">How to contribute development time?</h3>

<p>The Foundation has limited resources to manage the developers we contract to work on PHP. For this reason, it is not sensible to assume the management of external developers.</p>

<p>Any external developer who is compensated for their time spent on PHP is, of course, welcome to make use of our public communication channels:</p>

<ol>
<li>Email as: <a href="&#109;&#x61;i&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x63;&#111;&#x6e;&#x74;&#97;&#x63;t&#64;&#x74;&#104;&#101;&#x70;&#104;&#x70;&#x2e;&#102;&#x6f;&#x75;&#110;&#x64;a&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#110;">contact@thephp.foundation</a></li>
<li>Communicate via issues on GitHub repos: <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">github.com/php/php-src</a>, <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php">github.com/php/web-php</a>, etc.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="how-to-contribute-expertise%3F">How to contribute expertise?</h3>

<p>As the foundation begins to mature, a couple of currently unfulfilled roles have emerged.</p>

<p>We will soon communicate the details of these roles.</p>

<p>We intend to compile a list of all expertise on offer; If you haven't done so already, please tell what expertise you would like to make available using public communication channels.</p>

<hr />

<p><br></p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💜🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/07/04/php-foundation-update-june-2022/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/07/04/php-foundation-update-june-2022/</id><updated>Mon, 04 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[FrankenPHP Is Now Officially Supported by&nbsp;The&nbsp;PHP&nbsp;Foundation]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://frankenphp.dev">FrankenPHP</a>, a modern high-performance PHP application server created by <a href="https://dunglas.dev">Kévin Dunglas</a> and sponsored by <a href="http://Les-Tilleuls.coop">Les-Tilleuls.coop</a>, is now officially supported by the PHP Foundation. FrankenPHP integrates PHP directly into Go and Caddy, simplifying deployment, improving performance, and reducing costs. It powers real-time features, supports advanced hosting scenarios, and offers a performance-boosting “worker mode” already integrated by Laravel, Symfony, and Yii. The PHP Foundation will actively contribute to FrankenPHP’s development and host its code on the official PHP GitHub, marking a major step toward modernizing the PHP ecosystem while keeping governance with the original maintainers.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/2025-05-15-frankenphp.png" alt="FrankenPHP-PHP-Foundation" /></p>

<p>PHP is a programming language used by around 70% of websites and applications, and by key software and frameworks such as <a href="https://wordpress.org">WordPress</a>, <a href="https://laravel.com">Laravel</a>, and <a href="https://symfony.com">Symfony</a>.</p>

<p>FrankenPHP offers a host of new features that allow to:</p>

<ul>
<li>simplify the development of applications written in PHP;</li>
<li>drastically improve performance, while considerably reducing hosting costs (FinOps) and energy consumption (GreenOps);</li>
<li>facilitate deployment in production, whether on bare-metal servers or in cloud-native environments;</li>
<li>easily develop real-time features thanks to native <a href="https://mercure.rocks">Mercure</a> protocol support;</li>
<li>extend PHP apps with Go, C, and C++ programming languages;</li>
<li>support the PHP programming language in any application written in Go (server, proxy, in-house development...).</li>
</ul>

<p>Specifically, FrankenPHP integrates the official PHP interpreter as a module for Go and <a href="https://caddyserver.com">Caddy</a>, the popular next-generation web server that supports the latest web platform innovations in terms of performance, security, and DevOps: HTTP/3, compression with Zstandard, 103 Early Hints, automatic generation and renewal of HTTPS certificates, Encrypted Client Hello, structured logs, OpenMetrics/Prometheus metrics… Caddy is also co-maintained by Kévin and sponsored by Les-Tilleuls.coop.</p>

<p>Thanks to its innovative architecture, FrankenPHP lets you install a complete PHP environment (interpreter, web server, extensions, etc.) optimized for performance and security, by downloading a standalone statically compiled executable or a Docker image.</p>

<p>FrankenPHP also offers a performance-optimized mode called “worker mode”, which takes advantage of the capabilities of the Go programming language. When this optional mode is used, the PHP application will be able to retain in memory those elements that can be reused to process other HTTP requests instead of being completely reset to process each incoming HTTP request (“share nothing” model). Worker mode is especially useful for frameworks such as Symfony and Laravel that can prevent rebuilding their kernels and services again and again for nothing.</p>

<p>Using this mode requires minimal adaptations to the code of modern PHP applications in line with good programming practice. The Laravel, Symfony and Yii frameworks already offer official integrations of FrankenPHP's worker mode, enabling worker mode to be activated without modifying the application code.</p>

<p>According to <a href="https://sylius.com/blog/ecosystem/month-of-sylius-august-2024/#frankenphp">an analysis carried out this summer by Sylius</a>, the publisher of the eponymous e-commerce platform, the use of FrankenPHP's worker mode reduces the software's response times by 80%, while reducing by more than 6 the number of machines required to serve the same number of users.</p>

<p>FrankenPHP is now a reliable, mature solution used in production for an ever-increasing number of projects. The project now has <a href="https://github.com/dunglas/frankenphp">almost 8,000 stars on GitHub</a>, has passed the symbolic 100-contributor mark, and is officially supported by numerous hosting providers, including Upsun, Laravel Cloud, and Clever Cloud.</p>

<p>To get to this point, it was necessary to initiate close collaboration between the development teams of FrankenPHP, the PHP interpreter itself, the Caddy web server, and even the Go programming language.</p>

<p>Today, we're proud to announce that, with the aim of intensifying this collaboration, enabling the project to gain momentum, and modernizing the entire PHP ecosystem, <strong>the FrankenPHP project is now officially supported by the PHP Foundation</strong>.</p>

<p>In concrete terms, FrankenPHP's source code will be transferred to the PHP project's GitHub organization, and the PHP Foundation team will contribute to the maintenance and development of FrankenPHP to ensure its reliability, durability, and compatibility with the latest language innovations.</p>

<p>Part of the FrankenPHP documentation will also be transferred to the PHP website.</p>

<p>The governance of the project remains unchanged, and the current team of maintainers (Kévin Dunglas, Robert Landers, Alexander Stecher) will continue to be in charge of releases, as well as code reviews. They will be actively collaborating with the PHP Foundation team in charge of the language development.</p>

<p>In addition to the support provided by the foundation, Les-Tilleuls.coop will continue to sponsor FrankenPHP (as well as PHP and Caddy) by providing developers and contributing financially.</p>

<p>FrankenPHP is already <a href="https://caddyserver.com/#:~:text=4x%20faster%20PHP%20apps">promoted by Caddy</a> as the official, modern solution for using PHP with this server.<br />
In the future, to simplify the PHP development experience (one-line installation of a complete development environment) and to promote a solution that, for projects requiring it, considerably improves the performance and efficiency of PHP applications, FrankenPHP may be highlighted on the PHP website as one of the ways to use the language (other SAPIs such as PHP-FPM will continue to be fully supported solutions).</p>

<p>To find out more about FrankenPHP and the many new possibilities it offers, take a look at <a href="https://frankenphp.dev">its documentation</a>. To meet the software's authors and find out how it is used in production, don't miss <a href="https://api-platform.com/con/">the API Platform conference</a> (by the same authors as FrankenPHP) taking place on September 18 and 19 in France (Lille).</p>

<p>Also, join us online for <a href="https://lp.jetbrains.com/phpverse-2025/"><strong>PHPverse on June 17</strong></a> — a special event celebrating PHP’s 30th anniversary.</p>

<p>Finally, to help keep the PHP ecosystem innovating, <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">support the foundation</a>!</p>

<p><a href="https://thephp.foundation/">The PHP Foundation</a><br />
<a href="http://Les-Tilleuls.coop">Les-Tilleuls.coop</a><br />
<a href="https://caddyserver.com">The Caddy team</a></p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/05/15/frankenphp/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/05/15/frankenphp/</id><updated>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Announcing the Official PHP SDK for MCP]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>The PHP Foundation</strong>, <strong>Anthropic’s MCP team, and Symfony</strong> are collaborating on the <strong>official PHP SDK for the Model Context Protocol (MCP)</strong>. Our goal is a <strong>framework-agnostic, production-ready</strong> reference implementation the PHP ecosystem can rely on.</p>

<p>The Symfony team will lead maintenance, with contributions from the broader community, including <a href="https://github.com/CodeWithKyrian">Kyrian Obikwelu</a> (<a href="https://github.com/php-mcp">PHP-MCP</a>).</p>

<p>This initiative consolidates earlier work into a single, trusted implementation – <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/php-sdk"><strong>modelcontextprotocol/php-sdk</strong></a> – starting with the server and expanding to client capabilities.</p>

<p>⭐ Star the repo, try it, open issues/PRs, and join discussions.</p>

<!--
- [Symfony announcement](https://symfony.com/blog/symfony-to-provide-the-official-mcp-sdk)  
- [MCP blog announcement]()
-->

<h2 id="%2A%2Awhat-is-mcp-and-why-is-it-important%2A%2A"><strong>What is MCP and why is it important</strong></h2>

<p>The <a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/">Model Context Protocol</a> (MCP) is an open protocol introduced by <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/">Anthropic</a> to enable AI applications to connect with and utilize external tools and data sources, akin to a standardized "USB-C port" for AI systems.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>💡 Fun fact: MCP co-creator <a href="https://x.com/dsp_"><strong>David Soria Parra</strong></a> was release manager for <a href="https://wiki.php.net/todo/php54">PHP 5.4</a> and <a href="https://wiki.php.net/todo/php55">5.5</a>, and a long-time PHP core contributor. His PHP code still runs inside <a href="https://github.com/symfony/http-foundation/blob/6.1/IpUtils.php#L105">every Symfony and Laravel project</a> today. Cheers, David! 💜</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To make it easier to build MCP servers, the community provides SDKs – lightweight frameworks that handle the protocol details so developers can focus on their applications.</p>

<p>There were several official SDKs for different programming languages. However, there was no official PHP SDK, even though a few community implementations existed.</p>

<p>That’s why <strong>the PHP Foundation stepped up to coordinate</strong> the development and maintenance of the official PHP SDK for MCP.</p>

<p>This brings two important benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>A <strong>trusted reference implementation</strong> developers can rely on.</li>
<li>Visibility of <strong>PHP’s readiness for AI development</strong> outside its own ecosystem.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="%2A%2Awhat%E2%80%99s-happening%2A%2A"><strong>What’s happening</strong></h2>

<p><strong>The PHP Foundation</strong> has partnered with the MCP team at <strong>Anthropic</strong> and the <strong>Symfony</strong> team to develop the <strong>official MCP SDK for PHP.</strong></p>

<p>The Symfony team will be lead maintainers of the SDK as they have a proven track record of building high-quality framework-agnostic components that much of the PHP ecosystem relies on.</p>

<p>Additionally, <a href="https://github.com/CodeWithKyrian">Kyrian Obikwelu</a> joined the maintainer team and brings his previous experience and work on MCP libraries. Other PHP MCP SDK authors are welcome to participate as well.</p>

<p><strong>Roadmap (high level):</strong></p>

<ol>
<li>Server-side building blocks (initial release)</li>
<li>Client capabilities and additional transports as the spec evolves</li>
<li>Docs, examples, and stability hardening driven by real-world use</li>
</ol>

<p>We’ll keep this implementation framework-agnostic so it works well in any platform, legacy apps, and custom stacks. Community adapters and examples will live alongside the core packages.</p>

<h2 id="%2A%2Aget-involved%2A%2A"><strong>Get involved</strong></h2>

<p><strong>Try it:</strong> install the SDK, scaffold a small MCP server, and expose one or two safe tools.</p>

<p><strong>Contribute:</strong> issues, docs, and PRs are very welcome – especially around testing, and real-world examples.</p>

<p><strong>Bring your framework:</strong> we’re keen on first‑class integrations for Laravel, WordPress, Drupal, Laminas, and more. We keep a list of integrations in the repo as well.</p>

<p><strong>Start here:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>SDK repo: <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/php-sdk"><strong>modelcontextprotocol/php-sdk</strong></a></li>
<li>Composer package: <a href="https://packagist.org/packages/mcp/sdk"><strong>https://packagist.org/packages/mcp/sdk</strong></a></li>
<li>MCP spec &amp; ecosystem: <a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-06-18"><strong>https://modelcontextprotocol.io/</strong></a></li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://symfony.com/blog/let-s-build-the-symfony-ai-ecosystem-together"><strong>Join the Symfony AI Hackathon</strong></a><br />
  The in-person event will be <a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/ML4e5SqtcwGRYJH8A">hosted at Quentic in Berlin</a>, and requires a <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/symfony-ai-hackathon-tickets-1591414586869">free registration via Eventbrite</a> upfront. For online participation, please make sure to join our <a href="https://symfony.com/slack">Slack Workspace</a> and the &#35;ai channel to follow along and raise your topics or questions.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This SDK helps ensure PHP is visible as a great language choice to a wider audience when working in the AI ecosystem.
Let’s build it together!<br />
💜🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/09/05/php-mcp-sdk/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/09/05/php-mcp-sdk/</id><updated>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Foundation Update, May 2022]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>This time our regular update is short. Check the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/05/30/php-core-roundup-2/">PHP Core Roundup</a> series for a detailed development log.</p>

<h2 id="interview-with-core-developers">Interview with core developers</h2>

<p>After the <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/updates/php-foundation-update-april-2022">April update</a>, Sebastian Bergmann published an <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/05/06/interview-with-core-developers/">interview with our sponsored core developers</a>: Derick Rethans, Gina Peter Banyard, Jakub Zelenka, Máté Kocsis, and Ilija Tovilo. The other day we updated it and added answers from Arnaud Le Blanc. Check <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/05/06/interview-with-core-developers/">the interview</a> to get a high-level picture of what guys are working on.</p>

<h2 id="php-core-roundup">PHP Core Roundup</h2>

<p>In the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/05/30/php-core-roundup-2/">PHP Roundup #2</a> post by Ayesh, you can find a detailed log of what's been done and discussed regarding the PHP engine this month.</p>

<p>We decided to rename the series from <em>PHP Roundup</em> to <em>PHP Core Roundup</em> to reflect the content better and emphasize that the roundup is only about the core of the language.</p>

<p>Send your questions about the roundup directly to roundup@thephp.foundation or simply tweet at us: <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Ayeshlive">@Ayeshlive</a>.</p>

<h2 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h2>

<p>This month we are glad to welcome new major sponsors who generously support the PHP Foundation:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://moodle.org/">Moodle</a></strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://spysystem.dk/">SPY</a></strong></li>
<li><strong><a href="https://symfony.com/">Symfony</a></strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Thank you, folks!</p>

<p>We’d like to give a shout-out to everyone for your continued support.</p>

<p>We truly appreciate it – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💜🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/06/01/php-foundation-update-may-2022/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/06/01/php-foundation-update-may-2022/</id><updated>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation: Impact and Transparency Report 2024]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="executive-summary">Executive Summary</h2>

<p>As of early 2025, The PHP Foundation comprises <strong>8 volunteer board members</strong>, <strong>an Executive Director</strong> sponsored by JetBrains, and <strong>10 developers</strong> paid part-time/full-time who contribute significantly to the PHP language and its extensions.</p>

<p>In 2024, The PHP Foundation received <strong>$683,550 in donations and investments</strong> from organizations and individuals.</p>

<p>The foundation’s primary focus in 2024 remained strengthening the maintenance of PHP core, housed in the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> GitHub repository. This project is the home of the PHP language, where PHP’s interpreter is developed. Everyone who uses PHP benefits in one way or another from the work that is done in this repository.</p>

<p>The 10 part-time and full-time developers contracted by The PHP Foundation were responsible for a substantial portion of the commits and reviews made to the PHP language.</p>

<p><strong>Key achievements in 2024 included:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Completion of projects funded by the Sovereign Tech Fund</li>
<li>Expansion of the development team</li>
<li>Increased contributions to PHP core</li>
<li>Enhanced community engagement and sponsor relations</li>
</ul>

<p>The foundation <strong>plans to spend up to $900,000 in 2025</strong>, including compensation and fees. We continue to seek additional sponsor contributions to sustain and expand these efforts in the coming years.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-mission">The PHP Foundation Mission</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation’s mission remains focused on ensuring the long-term prosperity of the PHP language. Our priorities continue to be:</p>

<ul>
<li>Improving the language for users</li>
<li>Providing high-quality maintenance</li>
<li>Improving the project to retain current contributors and integrate new ones</li>
<li>Promoting the public image of PHP</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-sponsors">The PHP Foundation Sponsors</h2>

<p>In 2024, the following companies made major financial contributions (donating $12,000 or more):</p>

<p><strong>Sovereign Tech Agency, JetBrains, Automattic, Laravel, GoDaddy.com, Craft CMS, Private Packagist, Cybozu, Tideways, Mercari Inc., pixiv Inc., Sentry, Manychat, Zend by Perforce, Les-Tilleuls.coop, CH Studio, Aternos GmbH.</strong></p>

<p>Overall, 658 organizations and individuals sponsored the foundation in 2024 through <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation">on Open Collective</a> and <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/ThePHPF">GitHub Sponsors</a>.</p>

<p>Here is what some of the prominent folks say.</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-taylor-otwell">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“The PHP Foundation plays a vital role in ensuring the long-term sustainability and health of PHP. By supporting core development and fostering collaboration across the community, the Foundation helps keep PHP modern, stable, and thriving for years to come.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/taylor.png" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Taylor Otwell, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Founder &amp; CEO, Laravel</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-artemy-pestretsov">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“At JetBrains, we’re proud to support the PHP Foundation and its commitment to strengthening PHP. It’s great to see how the Foundation’s achievements directly benefit the developer community we deeply care about, and we’re excited to be part of PHP’s ongoing success.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/artemy.png" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Artemy Pestretsov, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Product Leader, PhpStorm at JetBrains</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-courtney-robertson">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“At GoDaddy, we recognize that PHP is the backbone of the open web and the engine powering many of the sites we host. Our contribution to The PHP Foundation is a strategic investment in maintaining the secure, reliable, and innovative technology that drives our digital ecosystem.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/courtney.jpeg" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Courtney Robertson, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Open Source Developer Relations, GoDaddy</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-nils-adermann">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“PHP is absolutely vital to global business, enabling digital public spaces, human interaction, and commerce around the world. We’re proud to do our part by contributing to PHP’s continuous improvements through the PHP Foundation, and call on all other companies relying on PHP to join us.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/nils.png" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Nils Adermann, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Co-Founder, Composer, Private Packagist</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-chad-whitacre">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“PHP is my favorite foundation. There I said it. Why? Their primary objective is to pay developers. You'd think that is obvious but most foundations do everything but that.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/chad.jpeg" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Chad Whitacre, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Head of Open Source, Sentry</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<h2 id="projects-for-the-sovereign-tech-agency-delivered-successfully">Projects for The Sovereign Tech Agency Delivered Successfully</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/">Sovereign Tech Agency</a> (STA) supports the development, improvement, and maintenance of open digital infrastructure in the public interest. Its goal is to strengthen the open-source ecosystem sustainably, focusing on security, resilience, technological diversity, and the people behind the code. STF is funded by the German Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs and Climate Action (BMWK) and supported by the German Federal Agency for Disruptive Innovation GmbH (SPRIND).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/sta.png" width="597" alt="STA"></p>

<p>The Sovereign Tech Agency commissioned work on four major projects, all of which we successfully delivered. Here’s a brief overview of the results.</p>

<h3 id="pecl-overhaul">PECL Overhaul</h3>

<p>The previous system for distributing PHP extensions, PECL/PEAR, is outdated, clumsy for users, and prone to supply-chain attacks, making it unreliable for average developers. This as a result leads to the creation of redundant tools and multiple security issues.</p>

<p>We proposed to rewrite the PECL installer, replacing the messy code and the inefficient website.</p>

<p>The result is <a href="https://github.com/php/pie"><strong>🥧PIE</strong></a> <strong>(PHP Installer for Extensions)</strong>, a new tool that replaces PECL with a PHP-native toolchain that is easier to maintain and more secure. It relies on the packagist.org infrastructure which is also a native PHP ecosystem.</p>

<p>Follow the progress of <strong>PIE</strong> here: <a href="https://github.com/php/pie">https://github.com/php/pie</a>.</p>

<p>The tool has already gathered a group of <a href="https://github.com/php/pie/graphs/contributors">contributors</a> and was well received in the community:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.codito.dev/2024/11/pie-new-extension-installer-for-php/">Pie: new extension installer for PHP</a></li>
<li><a href="https://phpconference.nl/session/pie-the-phps-next-big-thing/">PIE: The PHP’s Next Big Thing</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sensiolabs.com/blog/2024/introducing-pie-php-extension-installer">Introducing PIE: The Modern PHP Extension Installer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://laravel-news.com/pie">PIE (PHP Installer for Extensions)</a></li>
</ul>

<p>We continue investing in PIE in 2025.</p>

<h3 id="web-services-tool-for-php-fpm">Web Services Tool for PHP-FPM</h3>

<p>The Web Services Tool (WST) is a command-line application designed to test PHP-FPM integration across different web servers, environments, and configurations.</p>

<p>Currently, the tool is hosted under a separate GitHub organization (wstool/wst), with plans to move it to the official PHP GitHub organization in the future.</p>

<p>WST has already proven valuable for PHP-FPM development and testing, helping to identify and address complex issues that were previously untested in an automated way.</p>

<p>Learn more in the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/10/21/web-services-tool-for-php-fpm/">introductory blog post</a>.</p>

<h3 id="security-audit">Security Audit</h3>

<p>We conducted the first external security audit of the PHP core source code in over a decade. The audit is organized in partnership with <a href="https://ostif.org/"><strong>OSTIF</strong></a> and performed by <a href="https://www.quarkslab.com/"><strong>Quarkslab</strong></a>.</p>

<p>The public report is currently pending and will be published on <a href="https://thephp.foundation/">The PHP Foundation website</a> once available.</p>

<h3 id="documentation-improvements">Documentation Improvements</h3>

<p>We made multiple incremental improvements to the PHP documentation and also conducted a security review of the docs. Like the source code audit, this review was organized in partnership with <a href="https://ostif.org/"><strong>OSTIF</strong></a> and performed by <a href="https://www.quarkslab.com/"><strong>Quarkslab</strong></a>. As the scope here was too huge, we had to be smart and limit the review to certain most impactful pages.</p>

<p>Additionally, a new Wasm-based PHP runner has been included allowing all code example blocks to be executed directly on the page thanks to <a href="https://les-tilleuls.coop/en">Les-Tilleuls.coop</a>. Further improvements have been made since then, by fixing more examples and including resources to make the XML extensions' examples work..</p>

<p>An auto-cleaner script has also been added that removes comments older than 1 year with a score of &#45;5 or lower.  This has removed around 2000 low-quality notes from the site.</p>

<h3 id="infrastructure-update">Infrastructure Update</h3>

<p>As part of <a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/programs/bug-resilience">The Sovereign Tech Bug Resilience Program</a>, we partnered with <a href="https://neighbourhood.ie/">Neighbourhoodie Software</a> to overhaul the scripts powering parts of PHP’s web infrastructure, and also set up more appropriate back-ups.
Previously scattered scripts have been consolidated into robust Ansible playbooks. The rollout is currently being planned, and will result in a much easier to maintain and restore the PHP project's infrastructure. In the future, all infrastructure will likely be managed through this.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-staff">The PHP Foundation Staff</h2>

<h3 id="renewing-contracts">Renewing contracts</h3>

<p>In 2023, we had a team of 6 developers. All of them demonstrated a high quality of work, and dedication to the mission of the foundation. We were happy to renew the contracts for 2024 as well as extend the total number of hours for developers requesting it.</p>

<p>We aim to review the rates every year based on the available funding and priorities.</p>

<h3 id="growing-the-team">Growing the Team</h3>

<p>As was mentioned in the previous transparency report, we aimed to extend the team. It did not happen in 2023 because one of the prospective developers could not join the team for personal reasons, and had to step down from PHP core development entirely. Again, this is <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/2021/11/the-php-foundation/#the_bus_factor">the Bus Factor at its worst</a>. However, we were able to extend the team starting with 2024&#46;</p>

<p>Initially, we offered the new developers 6-month trial contracts so that the developers and the Governing Board can evaluate the results and then decide whether to continue the engagements. The results were far beyond our expectations. All new developers David Carlier, James Titcumb, Saki Takamachi, and Shivam Mathur demonstrated dedication and brought high value results, and demonstrated value.</p>

<h3 id="why-didn%E2%80%99t-we-add-more-developers%3F">Why didn’t we add more developers?</h3>

<p>In October 2024, following our usual process, we <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/17/application-form-2025/">opened applications</a> to expand or update our development team. We received many applications, including some from highly qualified candidates. However, we ultimately decided not to expand the team this time.</p>

<p><strong>The main reason is simple: budget constraints.</strong></p>

<p>Our funding from sponsorships determines how much we can afford, and we prioritize long-term stability over short-term expansion. Retaining the current team ensures we maintain the compound benefits of accumulated knowledge and experience. Growing the team temporarily, only to downsize later, would be counterproductive.</p>

<p>If we secure additional funding throughout the year, we may revisit the decision to expand the team.</p>

<h3 id="the-team-as-of-2025">The team as of 2025</h3>

<p>Starting from January, we continue contracting 10 developers to work on PHP:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Arnaud Le Blanc</strong> <a href="https://github.com/arnaud-lb">@arnaud-lb</a></li>
<li><strong>David Carlier</strong> <a href="https://github.com/devnexen">@devnexen</a></li>
<li><strong>Derick Rethans</strong> <a href="https://github.com/derickr">@derickr</a></li>
<li><strong>Gina Peter Banyard</strong> <a href="https://github.com/Girgias">@Girgias</a></li>
<li><strong>Ilija Tovilo</strong> <a href="https://github.com/iluuu1994">@iluuu1994</a></li>
<li><strong>Jakub Zelenka</strong> <a href="https://github.com/bukka">@bukka</a></li>
<li><strong>James Titcumb</strong> <a href="https://github.com/asgrim">@asgrim</a></li>
<li><strong>Máté Kocsis</strong> <a href="https://github.com/kocsismate">@kocsismate</a></li>
<li><strong>Saki Takamachi</strong> <a href="https://github.com/SakiTakamachi">@SakiTakamachi</a></li>
<li><strong>Shivam Mathur</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shivammathur">@shivammathur</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="retrospective%3A-goals-of-2024">Retrospective: Goals of 2024</h2>

<p>In the previous report, we outlined a few organizational and technical goals. Let’s look back and evaluate the results.</p>

<h3 id="organization-goals">Organization goals</h3>

<p><strong>Onboard new major sponsors ❌✅</strong><br />
We did have a few new and returning major sponsors, including Laravel, GoDaddy, Manychat. And of course we are happy about ongoing sponsorship from our founding members, and <a href="https://x.com/ThePHPF/status/1853390265429508427">increased commitment from Automattic</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Explore strategic partnerships and marketing opportunities ✅</strong><br />
We did collaborate with the Sentry team on Open Source Pledge initiative</p>

<p><strong>Further develop the Advisory Board initiative ❌</strong><br />
The Advisory Board played a big role in <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/01/how-hooks-happened/">shaping the Hooks RFC</a>. However, we have much more potential. In 2025, we’d like to revamp the AB to make it more useful and collaborative.</p>

<p><strong>Grow the foundation's community ✅</strong><br />
The PHP Foundation Slack is an invite-only community, and its closed nature has helped keep it very productive. We gradually add more community leaders and developers, along with one-channel guests for specific tasks. We also maintain a public channel, <strong>&#35;php-internals</strong>, which is mirrored on the <a href="https://phpc.chat/">PHP Community Discord server</a>.</p>

<h3 id="technical-goals">Technical goals</h3>

<p><strong>Ongoing maintenance and development of the PHP core ✅</strong></p>

<p><strong>Deliver the STF projects ✅</strong></p>

<p><strong>Improve the quality of the ideas and RFCs coming from the foundation ✅</strong><br />
All of the RFCs from The PHP Foundation — even major ones like Hooks — passed the vote. We see that as a clear sign of the proposals’ quality.</p>

<p><strong>Conduct research and surveys to define priorities ❌✅</strong><br />
We conducted <a href="https://youtu.be/XE4g1Tl6RQw?si=6zlWRFlyaKnv9cji&amp;t=843">quantitative research</a> in collaboration with the <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">PhpStorm</a> team and<br />
JetBrains. However, we were unable to conduct a PHP community survey. Nevertheless, we supported <a href="https://www.zend.com/blog/2025-php-survey-launch">Zend by Perforce PHP Landscape Survey</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Develop a high-level roadmap for PHP changes sponsored by the foundation ❌</strong>
The roadmap and vision need further development and discussion. We plan to announce a few strategic moves in the upcoming months.</p>

<h2 id="php-language-impact">PHP Language Impact</h2>

<p>Every day, the PHP Foundation staff team contributes to the open-source repositories of the <a href="https://github.com/php">PHP GitHub organization</a>. The foundation team contributes in many forms: filing issues, reviewing pull requests, participating in discussions on mailing lists, triaging issues, submitting RFC proposals.</p>

<p>In this document, four categories of contributions are presented in more detail: commits to php-src, reviews of pull requests on php-src, submitted RFC documents, and documentation work.</p>

<h3 id="commits-to-php">Commits to PHP</h3>

<p>The following chart summarizes the number of commits made to the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> repository in 2024&#46;</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th align="left"></th>
  <th align="center">2022</th>
  <th align="center">2023</th>
  <th align="center">2024</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Total by The PHP Foundation</td>
  <td align="center">683</td>
  <td align="center">784</td>
  <td align="center">1976</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Total other</td>
  <td align="center">885</td>
  <td align="center">1588</td>
  <td align="center">3378</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/commits.svg" alt="Commits" /></p>

<p>We’re happy to see not only an <strong>increase in commits from PHP Foundation</strong> developers but also a significant <strong>boost in contributions from other developers</strong> and the wider community. We consider this one of our biggest achievements and a strong sign of a thriving, <strong>healthy ecosystem</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note that the number of commits does not fairly represent the level of effort or the scope of the work. However, it can demonstrate the foundation's relative level of contribution to the PHP core through an objective metric.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="reviews">Reviews</h3>

<p>The diagram summarizes the number of pull request reviews made in the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> repository from January 1 to December 31, 2024&#46;</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th align="left"></th>
  <th align="center">2022</th>
  <th align="center">2023</th>
  <th align="center">2024</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Total by The PHP Foundation</td>
  <td align="center">283</td>
  <td align="center">702</td>
  <td align="center">1278</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Total other</td>
  <td align="center">551</td>
  <td align="center">416</td>
  <td align="center">866</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/reviews.svg" alt="Reviews" /></p>

<h3 id="rfcs">RFCs</h3>

<p>Below are the RFC proposals authored or co-authored by The PHP Foundation developers in 2024 (date order).</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th align="left">RFC</th>
  <th align="left">Proposed</th>
  <th align="left">Status</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/property-hooks">Property hooks</a></td>
  <td align="left">2023-01-03</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/release_cycle_update">Release cycle update</a></td>
  <td align="left">2023-11-05</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/13111">Dedicated StreamBucket class</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-01-19</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/support_object_type_in_bcmath">Support object type in BCMath</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-03-24</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/correctly_name_the_rounding_mode_and_make_it_an_Enum">Correctly name the rounding mode and make it an Enum</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-04-21</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="http://wiki.php.net/rfc/asymmetric-visibility-v2">Asymmetric Visibility v2</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-05-09</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/lazy-objects">Lazy Objects</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-06-03</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="http://wiki.php.net/rfc/hook_improvements">Property hook improvements</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-06-28</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/gmp-final">Make the GMP class final</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-06-29</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/add_bcdivmod_to_bcmath">Add bcdivmod to BCMath</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-06-30</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/fix_up_bcmath_number_class">Fix up BCMath Number Class / Change GMP bool cast behavior</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-06-30</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/directory-opaque-object">Change Directory class to behave like a resource object</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-09-14</td>
  <td align="left">Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left"><a href="http://wiki.php.net/rfc/phpnet-analytics">PHP.net Analytics Collection</a></td>
  <td align="left">2024-10-28</td>
  <td align="left">Approved</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="generics">Generics</h3>

<p>Generics are one of the most requested PHP features, but also the hardest. In 2024, the Foundation funded exploratory research into how generics might be implemented.  The <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/08/19/state-of-generics-and-collections/">result of that research</a> is available in its own blog post. In short, there is potential to make it happen but still some significant performance-related issues to resolve.</p>

<h3 id="release-maintenance">Release Maintenance</h3>

<p>Saki Takamachi, one of the Foundation developers, volunteered to be a release manager for PHP 8.4. The PHP Foundation supported such an initiative.</p>

<p>Jakub Zelenka, another foundation developer, continued duty as a release manager for PHP 8.3. Also supported by the foundation.</p>

<h3 id="security">Security</h3>

<p>The PHP Foundation contributed significantly to the 4 security releases. As per <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/blob/php-8.1.31/NEWS">PHP 8.1 changelog</a>, most security issues were addressed by Niels Dossche (11), followed by the foundation developers Jakub Zelenka (6) and Arnaud Le Blanc (1). There has been additional work done in terms of reviews and release preparations.</p>

<p>In addition, various documentation security issues were fixed by the foundation developers as result of the security audit.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-and-the-eu-cyber-resilience-act">The PHP Foundation and the EU Cyber Resilience Act</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation is now a founding member of the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/04/02/open-source-community-cra-compliance-initiative/">Cyber Resilience Act Working Group</a>, giving us a key role in monitoring developments, representing PHP’s interests, and ensuring compliance with the regulation.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/eu_cra_wg.png" alt="EU Cyber Resilience Act Working Group" /></p>

<p>Late last year, the group evolved into the <a href="https://orcwg.org/">Open Regulatory Compliance Working Group</a> (ORCWG). Jakub Zelenka, the Foundation developer, is part of the FAQ task force. That allows us to play an advisory role and help prepare the PHP ecosystem for the regulations.</p>

<p>For more details, see:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/04/02/open-source-foundations-unite-on-common-standards-for-eus-cybersecurity-resilience-act/">TechCrunch: Open Source Foundations Unite on Common Standards</a></li>
<li><a href="https://newsroom.eclipse.org/news/announcements/eclipse-foundation-launches-open-regulatory-compliance-working-group-help-open">Eclipse Foundation Announcement</a></li>
<li>ORCWG website: <a href="https://orcwg.org">orcwg.org</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="open-source-pledge-collaboration-with-sentry">Open Source Pledge Collaboration with Sentry</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/open-source-pledge-logo-sticker.svg" width="400" alt="Open Source Pledge"/></p>

<p>In 2024, Sentry launched the <a href="https://opensourcepledge.com/">Open Source Pledge</a>, with the aim of encouraging companies that rely on Open Source systems to help directly fund Open Source development.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation is also <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/10/08/open-source-pledge/">a supporter of this effort</a>; contributing to Open Source is its entire purpose.  The Foundation also <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">welcomes sponsorships</a> from companies and organizations that wish to support Open Source as part of their Pledge.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-brand-%26-public-channels">The PHP Foundation brand &amp; public channels</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation represents a community of core PHP developers and advocates for the PHP programming language. The PHP Foundation used the channels listed below for public communication:</p>

<ul>
<li>12,546 Twitter followers <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">https://twitter.com/thephpf</a></li>
<li>18,337 LinkedIn page followers <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation">https://www.linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation</a></li>
<li>1,060 Mastodon followers <a href="https://phpc.social/@thephpf">https://phpc.social/@thephpf</a></li>
<li>1,029 Bluesky followers <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/thephpf.bsky.social">https://bsky.app/profile/thephpf.bsky.social</a></li>
</ul>

<p>PHP Foundation developers and board members gave talks at multiple conferences throughout the year:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XE4g1Tl6RQw">Laracon EU</a> – Roman Pronskiy</li>
<li><a href="https://www.phpconference.co.uk/">PHP UK Conference</a> – Derick Rethans, Gina Banyard</li>
<li><a href="https://phpconference.com/">International PHP Conference</a> – Derick Rethans, Nils Adermann</li>
<li><a href="https://froscon.org/en/">FrOSCon</a> – Sebastian Bergmann</li>
<li><a href="https://tek.phparch.com/">php&#91;tek&#93;</a> – Derick Rethans, Nils Adermann</li>
<li><a href="https://events.drupal.org/barcelona2024">DrupalCon Barcelona</a>&#45; Nils Adermann</li>
<li><a href="https://php.bettercode.eu/">betterCode(PHP)</a> – Saki Takamachi, Sebastian Bergmann, Nils Adermann</li>
<li><a href="https://event.afup.org/">ForumPHP</a> – Gina P. Banyard, Derick Rethans, Nicolas Grekas</li>
<li><a href="https://live.symfony.com/2023-brussels-con/">SymfonyCon</a> – Nicolas Grekas, Nils Adermann</li>
<li>Various Symfony meetups in France and Germany &#45; Nicolas Grekas</li>
<li><a href="https://confoo.ca">ConFoo</a> — Derick Rethans, Nicolas Grekas</li>
<li><a href="https://phpconference.nl">Dutch PHP Conference</a> — Derick Rethans</li>
<li><a href="https://2024.phpday.it/">phpDay</a> — Derick Rethans, Gina Banyard</li>
<li><a href="https://event.afup.org/afup-day-2024/afup-day-2024-lille/">AFUP Days 2024 Lille</a>  — Gina Banyard</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="gina-made-it-to-openuk%E2%80%99s-%E2%80%98new-year-honours-list%E2%80%99">Gina made it to OpenUK’s ‘New Year Honours List’</h3>

<p>Gina Banyard, one of the Foundation's developers, was awarded an <a href="https://openuk.uk/honours/">Honour by OpenUK</a>, an Open Technology organization that recognizes "above and beyond" contributions to Open Source.  Congratulations, Gina&#33;</p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/report-2024/gina_openuk.png" width="492" alt="Gina OpenUK"/></p>

<h2 id="financial-report">Financial report</h2>

<p>In 2024, The PHP Foundation was financially backed by organizations and individuals with the goal of paying a competitive salary to as many core developers as possible.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th align="left"></th>
  <th align="left">2021-2022</th>
  <th align="left">2023</th>
  <th align="left">2024</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Total donated</td>
  <td align="left">$ 712,484</td>
  <td align="left">$ 478,767</td>
  <td align="left">$ 683,550</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Fees &#42;</td>
  <td align="left">$ 90,273</td>
  <td align="left">$ 60,098</td>
  <td align="left">$ 83,110</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Total received</td>
  <td align="left">$ 622,211</td>
  <td align="left">$ 418,669</td>
  <td align="left">$ 600,440</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td align="left">Paid to developers</td>
  <td align="left">$ 133,285</td>
  <td align="left">$ 275,181</td>
  <td align="left">$ 635,487</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><br></p>

<p><em>&#42; Fees include a 10%  Open Source Collective fiscal host fee (dealing with contracts, expense reviews and payments, bank account management, official registrations and dealing with government requirements, open collective platform development etc), and 1-5% percent of payment processing fees, depending on the payment method used.</em></p>

<p>All incoming and outgoing transactions of The PHP Foundation are publicly available to view for anyone: <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation#category-BUDGET">https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation&#35;category-BUDGET</a></p>

<h2 id="goals-for-2025">Goals for 2025</h2>

<p>Our foremost mission remains the same: <strong>maintain and develop the PHP language</strong>. We’d like PHP to be the best platform for users and for businesses creating web applications and APIs.</p>

<p>The main challenge for continuing the work of The PHP Foundation is to ensure sustainable sponsorship.</p>

<p>From a technical standpoint, the goal is to ensure that foundation developers work on valuable tasks.</p>

<h3 id="organization-goals">Organization Goals</h3>

<ul>
<li>Secure funding to support core development and marketing initiatives.</li>
<li>Launch the "PHP 30" anniversary campaign in collaboration with JetBrains.</li>
<li>Consolidate and grow social media presence across multiple platforms.</li>
<li>Increase website traffic through improved documentation and resources.</li>
<li>Develop an Ambassador Program.</li>
<li>Begin preparation for the "PHP Next" marketing campaign to highlight PHP's modernization.</li>
<li>Modernize PHP's website with updated downloads page, documentation, and homepage.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="technical-goals">Technical Goals</h3>

<ul>
<li>Continue on-going maintenance and development of the PHP core.</li>
<li>Establish a working group for integrating modern HTTP server capabilities into PHP core.</li>
<li>Address key developer experience pain points, particularly for first-time users.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="budget-plan-for-2025">Budget plan for 2025</h2>

<p>In 2025, we adjusted the developers’ hours according to their availability, requests, and our budget restrictions.</p>

<p>With this plan, we estimate our annual spending cap at approximately <strong>$900,000</strong> for developer compensation.</p>

<p>Our collaboration with the OpenCollective platform has been positive, and we plan to continue operating under the umbrella of the Open Source Collective in 2025&#46; This means that sponsorships we receive are reduced by 10% for Open Source Collective fees and 0-5% for payment processing fees.</p>

<h2 id="outro">Outro</h2>

<p>The PHP language is a living entity and, as such, requires continuous support to address developer issues, resolve security vulnerabilities, and has to evolve to meet the needs of the future.</p>

<p>Based on the strong third year of the foundation, we are excited to continue and multiply the efforts in the next years.</p>

<p>With <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/"><strong>your help</strong></a>, we continue the mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>

<section class="text-center mt-6">
    <div class="mb-14">
        <a href="/sponsor/" target="_blank" class="inline-block text-xl py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">
            Join The PHP Foundation
        </a>
    </div>
</section>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/03/31/transparency-and-impact-report-2024/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/03/31/transparency-and-impact-report-2024/</id><updated>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Call for Designs: Refresh the PHP 8.5 Release Page]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<div class="flex justify-center mb-4">
    <a href="https://x.com/pronskiy/status/1877672616355340392" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/website_redesign.png" width="500" alt="Website Redesign Twitter" class="shadow-md rounded-lg"/></a>
</div>

<p>Redesign <a href="https://www.php.net/">php.net</a>? We hear you. Let’s start small and ship something great: a refreshed PHP 8.5 release page. The <a href="https://externals.io/message/112026#112026">8.0-era page</a> built with community contributors and <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/?utm_source=thephp.foundation&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=phpstorm&amp;utm_content=refreshing-php-release-webpage">JetBrains</a> set the tone for 8.x. It’s held up, but 8.5 is a good moment to modernize: modern, clean, fast, inspiring.</p>

<p>We’re opening a design contest and you, the community, will help choose the winner. Read on for how to enter.</p>

<h2 id="prizes">Prizes</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>🥇 Grand prize: USD $1,000 sponsored by JetBrains</strong></li>
<li>Honorable mentions (credit in the footer of the page)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-we%E2%80%99re-looking-for">What we’re looking for</h2>

<p>A modern, lightweight design for the PHP 8.5 release page that:</p>

<ul>
<li>Keeps things simple: vanilla HTML/CSS, minimal/no JS, <strong>no new build tools or frameworks</strong>.</li>
<li>Mobile-first &amp; fast: responsive layouts, small assets, system fonts.</li>
<li>Localizable: works with multiple languages, avoids text baked into images.</li>
<li>Content-first: use existing <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/pull/1454">8.5 content</a> as data.</li>
<li>On-brand: feels at home on php.net; tasteful, unobtrusive visuals.</li>
<li>Maintainable: straightforward markup that future contributors can edit.</li>
</ul>

<p>Nice-to-have: a visual approach that can evolve for future releases (e.g., PHP 9.x).</p>

<h2 id="what-to-submit">What to submit</h2>

<p>Please submit designs first (we’re not judging big code drops):</p>

<ul>
<li>Mockups or prototype (Issue to <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/new?template=design-contest.yml">php/web-php</a>).</li>
<li>A short rationale (why this layout, how it meets the criteria).</li>
<li>You can also link to PR with the implementation.<br />
Keep the code small and clean. We won’t review large generated codebases.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="how-to-submit">How to submit</h2>

<p>Create a GitHub Issue in the <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php">php/web-php</a> repository using <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/new?template=design-contest.yml">Design Contest template</a>:</p>

<div class="flex justify-center mb-4">
    <img width="600" src="/assets/post-images/2025/contest_issue.png" class="shadow-md rounded-lg"/>
</div>

<p>Include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Link(s) to mockups/prototype</li>
<li>3–5 screenshots (desktop/mobile)</li>
<li>Rationale (300–600 words)</li>
<li>Your name (and teammates, if any)</li>
</ul>

<p>See a pinned <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/1472">contest tracking issue</a> with all entries for easy browsing.</p>

<h2 id="timeline-utc">Timeline (UTC)</h2>

<ul>
<li>Submissions open: Oct 1, 2025</li>
<li>Deadline: Oct 22, 2025, 23:59</li>
<li>Shortlist announced: Oct 23, 2025</li>
<li>Community vote: Oct 23–Oct 30, 2025</li>
<li>Winner announced: Nov 1, 2025</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="how-we%E2%80%99ll-pick-the-winner">How we’ll pick the winner</h2>

<ul>
<li>Jury (40%): php.net maintainers Sergey, Luffy, Derick, Sara + design advisor <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sergei-ellin/">Sergei Elin</a> (JetBrains) evaluate against the criteria below.</li>
<li>Community vote (60%): single-vote mechanism.</li>
<li>Tie-breaker: jury decision.</li>
</ul>

<p>Scoring criteria:</p>

<ol>
<li>Clarity of content hierarchy</li>
<li>Responsiveness &amp; mobile UX</li>
<li>Performance &amp; simplicity (no deps, readable markup)</li>
<li>Fit with php.net look and tone</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="rules-%26-licensing">Rules &amp; licensing</h2>

<ul>
<li>Your submission must be your original work and free of restrictive third-party licenses.</li>
<li>By entering, you agree your design (and any code you provide) will be licensed under the <a href="https://php.net/copyright.php">same terms as the php.net</a> website (web-php repository) and may be adapted as needed.</li>
<li>Team entries are allowed (max 1 entry per person/team).</li>
<li>Judges and organizers cannot participate.</li>
<li>We may decline to award if no entry meets the bar.</li>
<li>Participants must be 18 years or older.</li>
<li>Submissions from participants in restricted or sanctioned territories will not be considered.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="questions">Questions</h2>

<p>Please ask in the pinned <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/1472">Contest issue</a> in <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php">php/web-php</a>. We’ll keep answers centralized and public.</p>

<p>Let’s make the PHP 8.5 release page a joy to browse – clear, fast, and friendly for everyone!</p>

<p>🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/10/01/design-contest/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/10/01/design-contest/</id><updated>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Core Roundup #13]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The PHP Core team has been as productive as ever this past month, bringing forth a robust collection of updates that promise to shape the future of PHP. From RFCs that are sure to stir up lively debate, to ones that bring small, yet impactful changes, it has been a month filled with interesting developments. Here's what you need to know.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The PHP Foundation is a collective of PHP contributors, veterans, and companies that collaborate to ensure the long-term sustainability of the PHP programming language. The foundation currently supports six contributors focused on PHP's maintenance, debt reduction, and feature development. These contributors work closely with others on coding, documentation, and discussions.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Started over a year ago, the PHP Core Roundup series offers a summary of the latest developments, discussions, and news about PHP Core, contributed by both PHP Foundation members and other participants. This post is the thirteenth in the PHP Core Roundup series.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><div class="px-4 pt-3 border-b border-t -mx-4 border-gray-200">
    <div class="bg-white py-8">
        <div class="mx-auto grid max-w-7xl grid-cols-1 gap-10 lg:grid-cols-12 lg:gap-8">
            <div class="max-w-xl text-4xl font-medium tracking-tight text-gray-900 lg:col-span-6">
                Subscribe to The PHP Foundation newsletter
            </div>
            <form method="POST"
                  action="https://php-foundation.mailcoach.app/subscribe/9be4e2bd-f9d8-475c-b00e-2dcc4cf90056"
                  class="w-full max-w-md lg:col-span-6">
                <div class="flex gap-x-4">
                    <label for="email-address" class="sr-only">Email address</label>
                    <input id="email-address" name="email" type="email" autocomplete="email" required
                           class="min-w-0 flex-auto rounded-md border-0 px-3.5 py-2 text-gray-900 shadow-sm ring-1 ring-inset ring-gray-300 placeholder:text-gray-400 focus:ring-2 focus:ring-inset focus:ring-indigo-600 sm:text-sm sm:leading-6"
                           placeholder="Enter your email">
                    <button type="submit"
                            class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">
                        Subscribe
                    </button>
                </div>
                <div class="mt-4 text-sm leading-6 text-gray-900">
                    No spam. We only send 1–2 emails per month.
                </div>
            </form>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
</p>

<h2 id="releases">Releases</h2>

<p>The PHP development team released two new versions in May 2023: .</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.php.net/archive/2023.php#2023-05-11-1">PHP 8.2.6</a></strong></p>

<p>This release includes several bug fixes and improvements, notably in areas such as Core, Date, DOM, Exif, Intl, PCRE, Reflection, SPL, Standard, and Streams.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://www.php.net/archive/2023.php#2023-05-11-2">PHP 8.1.19</a></strong></p>

<p>This release includes bug fixes across various components such as Core, DOM, Exif, Intl, PCRE, and Standard.</p>

<h2 id="recent-rfcs-and-mailing-list-discussions">Recent RFCs and Mailing List Discussions</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Changes and improvements to PHP are discussed, reported, and voted on by the PHP Foundation Team, the PHP development team, and contributors. Bug reports are made to the PHP <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues">issue tracker</a>, changes are discussed in <a href="https://www.php.net/mailing-lists.php">mailing lists</a>, minor code changes are proposed as <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues">pull requests</a>, and major changes are discussed in detail and voted on as <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc">PHP RFCs</a>. <a href="https://github.com/php/doc-en/">Documentation</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php">php.net website</a> changes are also discussed and improved at their relevant Git repositories on GitHub.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br>
Hundreds of awesome PHP contributors put their efforts into improvements to the PHP code base, documentation, and the php.net website. Here is a summary of some changes made by the people behind PHP. Things marked with 💜 are done by the PHP Foundation team.</p>

<h2 id="rfc-updates">RFC Updates</h2>

<p>Following are the RFCs and major pull-requests discussed, voted on, and implemented since our last update.</p>

<h3 id="in-voting%3A-define-proper-semantics-for-range-function-by-gina-peter-banyard-%F0%9F%92%9C">In Voting: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/proper-range-semantics">Define proper semantics for range() function</a> by Gina Peter Banyard 💜</h3>

<p>This RFC proposes to adjust the semantics of the <code>range()</code> function in PHP to throw exceptions or at least warn when passing unusable arguments to <code>range()</code>.</p>

<p>The <code>range()</code> function in PHP generates an array of values going from a start value to an end value. However, the current behavior of the function is complex and can lead to unexpected results. For example, if one of the boundary inputs is a string digit (e.g. "1"), both inputs will be interpreted as numbers. This RFC aims to address these issues and make the behavior of the <code>range()</code> function more predictable and consistent.</p>

<h3 id="in-voting%3A-mb_str_pad-by-niels-dossche">In Voting: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/mb_str_pad">mb_str_pad()</a> by Niels Dossche</h3>

<p>This RFC proposes the addition of a multibyte string pad function to the mbstring extension. This function would work similarly to the existing <code>str_pad()</code> function, but with support for multibyte strings. This is a welcome addition for developers working with multibyte strings, as it will make it easier to manipulate and format these strings in PHP.</p>

<h3 id="under-discussion%3A-nameof-operator-by-robert-landers">Under Discussion: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/nameof">Nameof Operator</a> by Robert Landers</h3>

<p>This RFC proposes to add a global <code>nameof()</code> function, which would return the name of a variable, class, function, or method as a string. This could be useful in a variety of scenarios, such as debugging, logging, or creating more informative error messages.</p>

<h3 id="under-discussion%3A-marking-overridden-methods-by-tim-d%C3%BCsterhus">Under Discussion: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/marking_overriden_methods">Marking Overridden Methods</a> by Tim Düsterhus</h3>

<p>This RFC proposes a way to explicitly mark methods that are intended to override methods from a parent class with a new <code>#[\Override]</code> attribute. If this attribute is added to a method, the engine shall validate that a method with the same name exists in a parent class or any of the implemented interfaces. If no such method exists a compile time error shall be emitted.</p>

<p>The similar concepts exist in Java, TypeScript, C++, C#, Swift, Kotlin, and other languages.</p>

<h3 id="under-discussion%3A-deprecate-functions-with-overloaded-signatures-by-m%C3%A1t%C3%A9-kocsis-%F0%9F%92%9C">Under Discussion: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/deprecate_functions_with_overloaded_signatures">Deprecate Functions with Overloaded Signatures</a> by Máté Kocsis 💜</h3>

<p>This RFC proposes to deprecate a number of functions that have overloaded signatures, meaning they behave differently based on the number or type of arguments passed to them. The goal is to make PHP's function signatures more consistent and predictable.</p>

<h3 id="under-discussion%3A-deprecations-for-php-8.3-by-gina-peter-banyard-%F0%9F%92%9C%2C-christoph-m.-becker%2C-m%C3%A1t%C3%A9-kocsis-%F0%9F%92%9C%2C-tim-d%C3%BCsterhus%2C-go-kudo%2C-andreas-heigl">Under Discussion: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/deprecations_php_8_3">Deprecations for PHP 8.3</a> by Gina Peter Banyard 💜, Christoph M. Becker, Máté Kocsis 💜, Tim Düsterhus, Go Kudo, Andreas Heigl</h3>

<p>The aim is to clean up some of the older, less consistent parts of PHP to make the language more reliable and predictable. The following list provides a short overview of the functionality targeted for deprecation:</p>

<ul>
<li>Passing negative <code>$widths</code> to <code>mb_strimwidth()</code></li>
<li>The <code>NumberFormatter::TYPE_CURRENCY</code> constant</li>
<li>Unnecessary <code>crypt()</code> related constants</li>
<li><code>MT_RAND_PHP</code></li>
<li>Global Mersenne Twister</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="declined%3A-php-technical-committee-by-jakub-zelenka-%F0%9F%92%9C-and-larry-garfield">Declined: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/php_technical_committee">PHP Technical Committee</a> by Jakub Zelenka 💜 and Larry Garfield</h3>

<p>This RFC proposed the creation of a PHP Technical Committee (TC) that would make decisions about technical aspects of the PHP language and its reference implementation. The TC would have been responsible for resolving technical conflicts between core developers. Despite the potential benefits, the community decided not to move forward with this proposal.</p>

<h2 id="notable-mailing-list-discussions">Notable Mailing List Discussions</h2>

<h3 id="callable-types-via-interfaces"><a href="https://externals.io/message/120083">Callable types via Interfaces</a></h3>

<p>The proposal suggests that callable types should be allowed to be represented as interfaces, which would allow for more precise type hinting and better static analysis. The sentiment in the thread is generally positive, with many participants expressing support for the idea. However, some concerns were raised about potential complexity and the need for careful implementation to avoid breaking existing code.</p>

<h3 id="interface-properties"><a href="https://externals.io/message/120403">Interface Properties</a></h3>

<p>The discussion starter suggests making it possible to define properties in interfaces and argues that this feature would align well with the deprecation of dynamic properties and could replace the current practice of specifying these properties in doc blocks.</p>

<p>Larry Garfield pointed out that interface properties are already included in the <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/property-hooks">Property Hooks RFC</a>, which is expected to go to a vote soon.</p>

<p>David Gebler expressed his disagreement with the proposal, stating that interfaces in most languages don't support defining properties because they are generally seen as an implementation detail rather than a promise about supported behavior. He also mentioned that interfaces are essentially an alternative to multiple inheritance, and mandating fields as well as method signatures brings them very close to abstract classes. He also expressed concerns about multiple interfaces defining the same property, which could lead to conceptual confusion.</p>

<p>Some participants expressed support, noting that it could improve code clarity and reduce the need for doc blocks.</p>

<h2 id="merged-prs-and-commits">Merged PRs and Commits</h2>

<p>This month, the PHP core team has been hard at work improving the PHP language. Here's a list of the commits made by the team, grouped by author:</p>

<details>

<summary>Click here to expand</summary>

<ul>
<li><strong>Tim Düsterhus</strong>

<ul>
<li>RFC: Make unserialize() emit a warning for trailing bytes in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/9630">GH-9630</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Dmitry Stogov</strong>

<ul>
<li>JIT: Fixed inaccurate range inference usage for UNDEF/NULL/FALSE in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/25ad171f63">25ad171f63</a></li>
<li>Fixed <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11127">GH-11127</a> (JIT fault) in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/ed0b593c11">ed0b593c11</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>yang yuhan</strong>

<ul>
<li>JIT: Align JIT stubs in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11149">GH-11149</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>ColinHDev</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix negative indices on empty array not affecting next chosen index in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11157">GH-11157</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Sara</strong>

<ul>
<li>Add configuration opcache.jit_max_trace_length in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11173">GH-11173</a></li>
<li>Cacheline demote to improve performance in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11101">GH-11101</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Niels Dossche</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix too wide OR and AND range inference in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11170">GH-11170</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/9068">GH-9068</a>: Conditional jump or move depends on uninitialised value(s) in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10221">GH-10221</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11175">GH-11175</a> and <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11177">GH-11177</a>: Stream socket timeout undefined behaviour in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11183">GH-11183</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11178">GH-11178</a>: Segmentation fault in spl_array_it_get_current_data (PHP 8.1.18) in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11182">GH-11182</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11104">GH-11104</a>: STDIN/STDOUT/STDERR is not available for CLI without a script in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/f6c0c60ef6">f6c0c60ef6</a></li>
<li>Implement NEON-accelerated version of BLOCKCONV for lowercasing and uppercasing strings in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11161">GH-11161</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/10031">GH-10031</a>: [Stream] STREAM_NOTIFY_PROGRESS over HTTP emitted irregularly for last chunk of data in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10492">GH-10492</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11141">GH-11141</a>: Could not open input file: should be sent to stderr in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11163">GH-11163</a></li>
<li>Fix maximum argument count of pcntl_forkx() in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11199">GH-11199</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11160">GH-11160</a>: Few tests failed building with new libxml 2.11.0 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11162">GH-11162</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11180">GH-11180</a>: hash_file() appears to be restricted to 3 arguments in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11198">GH-11198</a></li>
<li>Remove unnecessary NULL assignments after ecalloc in streams in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11209">GH-11209</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/8426">GH-8426</a>: make test fail while soap extension build in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11211">GH-11211</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/10834">GH-10834</a>: exif_read_data() cannot read smaller stream wrapper chunk sizes in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10924">GH-10924</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://bugs.php.net/bug.php?id=97836">#97836</a> and <a href="https://bugs.php.net/bug.php?id=81705">#81705</a>: Segfault / type confusion in concat_function in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10049">GH-10049</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11274">GH-11274</a>: POST/PATCH request via file_get_contents + stream_context_create switches to GET after a HTTP 308 redirect in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11275">GH-11275</a></li>
<li>Fix -Wstrict-prototypes warnings in fuzzer SAPI in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11277">GH-11277</a></li>
<li>Remove unused variable err in mb_send_mail() in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11285">GH-11285</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11245">GH-11245</a> (In some specific cases SWITCH with one default statement will cause segfault) in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11251">GH-11251</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11281">GH-11281</a>: DateTimeZone::getName() does not include seconds in offset in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11282">GH-11282</a></li>
<li>Fix allocation loop in <code>zend_shared_alloc_startup()</code> in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11306">GH-11306</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11288">GH-11288</a> and <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11289">GH-11289</a> and <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11290">GH-11290</a> and <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/9142">GH-9142</a>: DOMExceptions and segfaults with replaceWith in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11299">GH-11299</a></li>
<li>Shrink libxml_doc_props struct in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11326">GH-11326</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/10234">GH-10234</a>: Setting DOMAttr::textContent results in an empty attribute value in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10245">GH-10245</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11338">GH-11338</a>: SplFileInfo empty getBasename with more than one slash in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11340">GH-11340</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11336">GH-11336</a>: php still tries to unlock the shared memory ZendSem with opcache.file_cache_only=1 but it was never locked in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11341">GH-11341</a></li>
<li>Fix spec compliance error for DOMDocument::getElementsByTagNameNS in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11343">GH-11343</a></li>
<li>Fix DOMElement::append() and DOMElement::prepend() hierarchy checks in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11344">GH-11344</a></li>
<li>Remove unnecessary tree setting in dom_zvals_to_fragment() in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11345">GH-11345</a></li>
<li>Implement dom_get_doc_props_read_only() in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11345">GH-11345</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11347">GH-11347</a>: Memory leak when calling a static method inside an xpath query in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11350">GH-11350</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Ilija Tovilo 💜</strong>

<ul>
<li>Add retry mechanism in <code>run-tests.php</code> in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10892">GH-10892</a></li>
<li>Downgrade to Ubuntu 20.04 for ASAN nightly for now in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/ef6bbaa1ec">ef6bbaa1ec</a></li>
<li>Correctly copy lineno for zval asts in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11203">GH-11203</a></li>
<li>Fix use-of-uninitialized value in <code>phar_object.c</code> in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11202">GH-11202</a></li>
<li>Fix use-of-undefined in zend_fiber_object_gc of ex->call in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11208">GH-11208</a></li>
<li>Fix compilation for PHP 8.1 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/8f66b67ccf">8f66b67ccf</a></li>
<li>Fix potential NULL pointer access in zend_fiber_object_gc in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/0a04c008d0">0a04c008d0</a></li>
<li>Fix delayed early binding class redeclaration error in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11226">GH-11226</a></li>
<li>Fix -Wenum-int-mismatch warning in ext/json/php_json_encoder.h in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/ac41608797">ac41608797</a></li>
<li>Implement delayed early binding for classes without parents in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/0600f513b3">0600f513b3</a></li>
<li>Fix segfault in mb_strrpos/mb_strripos with ASCII encoding and negative offset in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11220">GH-11220</a></li>
<li>Fix string coercion for $a .= $a in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11296">GH-11296</a></li>
<li>Fix concat_function use-after-free on out-of-memory error in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11297">GH-11297</a></li>
<li>Fix access on NULL pointer in array_merge_recursive() in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11303">GH-11303</a></li>
<li>Fix preg_replace_callback_array() pattern validation in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11301">GH-11301</a></li>
<li>Fix exception handling in array_multisort() in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11302">GH-11302</a></li>
<li>Use zend_ast_apply in zend_eval_const_expr in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11261">GH-11261</a></li>
<li>Allow arbitrary expressions in static variable initializer in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/9301">GH-9301</a></li>
<li>Use single allocation for indirect values in array_multisort in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11309">GH-11309</a></li>
<li>Fix <code>zend_jit_stop_counter_handlers()</code> performance issues with protect_memory=1 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11323">GH-11323</a></li>
<li>Add tests for list() in assignment in array literals in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/8ed66b4347">8ed66b4347</a></li>
<li>Revert "Use zend_ast_apply in zend_eval_const_expr (#11261)" in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/fbe6696d49">fbe6696d49</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Nils</strong>

<ul>
<li>Remove unused macro PHP_FNV1_32A_INIT and PHP_FNV1A_64_INIT in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11114">GH-11114</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>David CARLIER</strong>

<ul>
<li><code>ext/pgsql</code>: pg_cancel_query internal update in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/84c185c8ba">84c185c8ba</a></li>
<li><code>ext/pgsql</code>: pg_trace allow to refine its trace mode via 2 new constants in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/7ec8ae12c4">7ec8ae12c4</a></li>
<li><code>ext/pgsql</code>: pg_lo_read addressing the todo. in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11159">GH-11159</a></li>
<li><code>ext/pgsql</code> adding PGSQL_ERRORS_SQLSTATE constant support in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/f31d253849">f31d253849</a></li>
<li><code>ext/pgsql</code>: fix pg_trace test when trace mode is supported. in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11191">GH-11191</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Bob Weinand</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11189">GH-11189</a>: Exceeding memory limit in zend_hash_do_resize leaves the array in an invalid state in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/05bd1423ee">05bd1423ee</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11222">GH-11222</a>: foreach by-ref may jump over keys during a rehash in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/975d28e278">975d28e278</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Julien Quiaios</strong>

<ul>
<li>Add new test for array_fill() to cover the case when the parameter count is too large in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11184">GH-11184</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Cédric Anne</strong>

<ul>
<li>Make SERVER_SOFTWARE compliant with RFC3875 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11093">GH-11093</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Calvin Buckley</strong>

<ul>
<li><code>http_response_code</code> should warn if headers were already sent in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10744">GH-10744</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Daniel Kesselberg</strong>

<ul>
<li>Add PKCS7_NOOLDMIMETYPE and OPENSSL_CMS_OLDMIMETYPE in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/fa10dfcc81">fa10dfcc81</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Jakub Zelenka 💜</strong>

<ul>
<li>Add myself as a standard CODEOWNER to not miss some changes in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/5690e8baea">5690e8baea</a></li>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/10461">GH-10461</a>: Postpone FPM child freeing in event loop in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/102953735c">102953735c</a></li>
<li>Expose JSON internal function to escape string in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/e8a836eb39">e8a836eb39</a></li>
<li>Fix bug <a href="https://bugs.php.net/bug.php?id=64539">#64539</a>: FPM status - query_string not properly JSON encoded in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11050">GH-11050</a></li>
<li>FPM: Fix memory leak for invalid primary script file handle in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11088">GH-11088</a></li>
<li>Fix FPM status json encoded value test in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11276">GH-11276</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Florian Moser</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11054">GH-11054</a>: Reset OpenSSL errors when using a PEM public key in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11055">GH-11055</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Gina Peter Banyard 💜</strong>

<ul>
<li>Prevent unnecessary string duplication in assert() in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11031">GH-11031</a></li>
<li>ext/standard/array.c: use uint32_t instead of incorrect int type in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/646f54b594">646f54b594</a></li>
<li>Fix assertion warning message when no description is provided in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/e35cd34bcd">e35cd34bcd</a></li>
<li>Use uint32_t for variable storing <code>ZEND_NUM_ARGS()</code> in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/80c8ca9c8f">80c8ca9c8f</a></li>
<li>FPM: refactor fpm_php_get_string_from_table() to better match usage in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11051">GH-11051</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Máté Kocsis 💜</strong>

<ul>
<li>Narrow bool return types to true when possible in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/85338569de">85338569de</a></li>
<li>Add support for true standalone type when generating methodsynopsis in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/281669aeb4">281669aeb4</a></li>
<li>Narrow some more return types to true in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/09dd3e3daf">09dd3e3daf</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Michael Voříšek</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix gmp_long/gmp_ulong typedef warning on Windows x86 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11112">GH-11112</a></li>
<li>Allow CTE on more CTE safe functions in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/10771">GH-10771</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Amedeo Baragiola</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix compilation error on old GCC versions in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11212">GH-11212</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Luc Vieillescazes</strong>

<ul>
<li>Keep the orig_path for xport stream in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11113">GH-11113</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Randy Geraads</strong>

<ul>
<li>Added negative offset test for mb_strrpos in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/c5a623ba5e">c5a623ba5e</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Peter Kokot</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix #9483: Fix autoconf warnings due to old libtool in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11207">GH-11207</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Alex Dowad</strong>

<ul>
<li>Use shared, immutable array for return value of mb_list_encodings in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/97e29bed9e">97e29bed9e</a></li>
<li>Take order of candidate encodings into account when guessing text encoding in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/3ab10da758">3ab10da758</a></li>
<li>Use pakutoma's encoding check functions for mb_detect_encoding even in non-strict mode in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/7914b8cefd">7914b8cefd</a></li>
<li>Combine CJK encoding conversion code in a single source file in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/c717c79a09">c717c79a09</a></li>
<li>Optimize conversion of SJIS-2004 text to Unicode in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/73633bf1c3">73633bf1c3</a></li>
<li>Optimize conversion of CP932 text to Unicode in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/175154dbcc">175154dbcc</a></li>
<li>Move kana translation tables to <code>mbfilter_cjk.c</code> in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/245daedb41">245daedb41</a></li>
<li>Test mb_strlen for all text encodings supported by mbstring in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/f337c92050">f337c92050</a></li>
<li>Fix problem with CP949 conversion when 0xC9 precedes byte lower than 0xA1 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/8e6be14372">8e6be14372</a></li>
<li>Convert mbfilter_conv{,_r}_map_tbl to return bool in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/18ca489347">18ca489347</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Peter Chun-Sheng, Li</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11099">GH-11099</a>: Generating <code>phar.php</code> during cross-compile can't be done in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11243">GH-11243</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Nikita Popov</strong>

<ul>
<li>Correctly handle multiple constants in typed declaration in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/c230aa9be3">c230aa9be3</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>LoongT4o</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix the JIT buffer relocation failure at the corner case in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11266">GH-11266</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Pierrick Charron</strong>

<ul>
<li>PHP-8.2 is now for PHP 8.2.8-dev in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/d5f68b50fc">d5f68b50fc</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Ben Ramsey</strong>

<ul>
<li>PHP-8.1 is now for PHP 8.1.21-dev in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/2f2fd06be0">2f2fd06be0</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Mikhail Galanin</strong>

<ul>
<li><code>ext/session</code>: pass ini options to extra processes in tests in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11294">GH-11294</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>KoudelkaB</strong>

<ul>
<li>Access violation when ALLOC_FALLBACK fixed in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/8946b7b141">8946b7b141</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Daniil Gentili</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix GCC 12 compilation on riscv64 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/1dfa277a96">1dfa277a96</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Kirill Nesmeyanov</strong>

<ul>
<li>Add string output escaping into zend dump (phpdbg + opcache debug) in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11337">GH-11337</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>divinity76</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix return value in stub file for DOMNodeList::item in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11342">GH-11342</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Yuya Hamada</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix mb_strlen is wrong length for CP932 when 0x80 in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commit/c50172e812">c50172e812</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>James Lucas</strong>

<ul>
<li>Fix bug <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/issues/11246">GH-11246</a> cli/get_set_process_title in <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/pull/11247">GH-11247</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

</details>

<p><br>
This concludes the list of commits made by the PHP core team in the past month. We're grateful for their hard work and dedication to improving PHP.</p>

<p><br></p>

<hr />

<h2 id="support-php-foundation">Support PHP Foundation</h2>

<p>At PHP Foundation, we support, promote, and advance the PHP language. We financially support six part-time PHP core developers to contribute to the PHP project. You can help support PHP Foundation at <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation">OpenCollective</a> or via <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/ThePHPF">GitHub Sponsors</a>.</p>

<p>A big thanks to all our sponsors — PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💜️ 🐘</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>PHP Roundup is (except for this particular one) prepared by Ayesh Karunaratne from <strong><a href="https://php.watch">PHP.Watch</a></strong>, a source for PHP News, Articles, Upcoming Changes, and more.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/06/06/php-core-roundup-13/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/06/06/php-core-roundup-13/</id><updated>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Design Contest Results and Lessons Learned]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last few weeks we ran a focused community contest to refresh the <strong>PHP 8.5 release page</strong>. Thank you to everyone who submitted, reviewed, voted, and discussed.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Note about future redesigns</strong><br />
  This contest was an experiment for a single release page. We might <strong>not</strong> use the same approach for a broader homepage redesign. If we did run a contest again, we would separate tracks (on-brand update vs blue-sky concept), use a dedicated voting tool or randomized ordering, keep log-damped voting, and set a 50/50 jury/community split with clearer criteria and a small shortlist honorarium.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="%2A%2Aresults%2A%2A"><strong>Results</strong></h2>

<h3 id="%2A%2Awinner%3A%2A%2A-%2A%2Anuno-guerra-%40nunowar%2A%2A-%E2%80%93-%2Aphp-is-awesome-%F0%9F%94%A5%2A"><strong>Winner:</strong> <strong>Nuno Guerra <a href="https://github.com/nunowar">@nunowar</a></strong> – <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/1539"><em>PHP is Awesome 🔥</em></a></h3>

<p><a href="https://nunoguerra.com/dev/php/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/design-contest/nunowar.png" class="shadow-md rounded-lg"/></a></p>

<p><strong>Prizes:</strong> <strong>$1,000  + AI Ultimate License from <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">JetBrains</a></strong>·+ <strong>$1,000 from <a href="https://getrector.com/">Rector</a></strong></p>

<p>At JetBrains, we decided to support other contestants with gifts as well.</p>

<h3 id="%2A%2Arunner-up%3A-hanna-stelmakh-%40hastelmakh%2A%2A-%E2%80%93-%2Aphp-8.5-release-page-design-contest-submission%2A"><strong>Runner-up: Hanna Stelmakh <a href="https://github.com/hastelmakh">@hastelmakh</a></strong> – <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/1534"><em>PHP 8.5 Release Page Design Contest Submission</em></a></h3>

<p><a href="https://www.figma.com/proto/82kDxx1bh6ngC8Pv2Z2jUW/PHP-Release-8.5?page-id=0%3A1\&node-id=449-2387\&viewport=-7617%2C246%2C0.13\&t=f2P7pJOdSAEOKLDY-1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/design-contest/hastelmakh.png" class="shadow-md rounded-lg"/></a></p>

<p><strong>Prize:</strong> <strong>$500 + AI Ultimate License from <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/">JetBrains</a></strong></p>

<h3 id="%2A%2Ashortlist%3A%2A%2A"><strong>Shortlist:</strong></h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/ben-joostens">@ben-joostens</a><strong>,</strong> <a href="https://github.com/tao">@tao</a>, <a href="https://github.com/lumnn">@lumnn</a>, <a href="https://github.com/thiagoolivier">@thiagoolivier</a>, <a href="https://github.com/mcpad2025-crypto">@mcpad2025-crypto</a>, <a href="https://github.com/minlivalievs-eng">@minlivalievs-eng</a>, <a href="https://github.com/giodi">@giodi</a>, <a href="https://github.com/everlastedSE">@everlastedSE</a>, <a href="https://github.com/asterd">@asterd</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ad-1984">@ad-1984</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Ayesh">@Ayesh</a>, <a href="https://github.com/StillMoe">@StillMoe</a>, <a href="https://github.com/KarinCheng">@KarinCheng</a>, <a href="https://github.com/christian-acceseo">@christian-acceseo</a></p>

<p><strong>Shortlist thank-you:</strong> <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/"><strong>PhpStorm</strong></a> <strong>/ <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/ai-ides/buy/">AI Ultimate License</a> from JetBrains</strong> for all shortlisted participants.</p>

<h2 id="%2A%2Aa-little-fun-along-the-way%2A%2A-"><strong>A little fun along the way</strong> <img style="display:inline;" width="40" src="https://ftp.ntu.edu.tw/php/images/ele-running.gif"/></h2>

<p>Of course, no PHP contest would be complete without a bit of humor. Among all the serious submissions, one playful entry <a href="https://x.com/jon_bossenger/status/1983140310826795201">from X/Twitter</a> stood out:</p>

<p><a href="https://php-85-hyperactive.vercel.app/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/design-contest/php-85-hyperactive.png" class="shadow-md rounded-lg"/></a></p>

<p>It didn’t quite meet the “accessible and lightweight” brief, but it earned an honorary mention for spirit and commitment to vintage web aesthetics.</p>

<h2 id="%2A%2Anext-steps%2A%2A"><strong>Next steps</strong></h2>

<p>We will collaborate with Nuno Guerra to polish the winning design and may incorporate ideas from other entries where they improve clarity or accessibility. And finally we’ll adapt it to <a href="https://php.net">php.net</a>’s stack.</p>

<p>In the spirit of PHP, contributions are welcome! We encourage all participants to join the <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/1592"><strong>implementation thread</strong></a> and help refine the final page.</p>

<h2 id="%2A%2Ahow-the-scoring-worked%2A%2A"><strong>How the scoring worked</strong></h2>

<p>We combined a jury score with a community vote and <strong>used a logarithmic transform</strong> to reduce social-media spikes. We counted <strong>👍 during the voting window</strong> for each shortlisted entry and <strong>ignored 👎</strong> and other reactions.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Jury (40%)</strong><br />
Judges scored four criteria from 0 to 5. For each entry we averaged judges into <code>J</code> in the range 0–25.<br />
Normalization: <code>J_norm = J / 25</code>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Community vote (60%), log-damped</strong><br />
For entry <em>i</em> with <code>V_i</code> upvotes and <code>T = Σ V_i</code> across the shortlist:<br />
<code>V′_i = log(1 + V_i)</code> and <code>V_logshare = V′_i / Σ V′_k</code>.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Final score</strong><br />
Final <code>= 0.4 × J_norm + 0.6 × V_logshare</code></p></li>
</ul>

<p>We will publish the full table with anonymized jury subtotals and final scores.</p>

<h2 id="%2A%2Alessons-learned%2A%2A"><strong>Lessons learned</strong></h2>

<p>We might not run this contest format again. <strong>But if we did, here’s what we would fix:</strong></p>

<h3 id="%2A%2A1-scope-%26-brief%3A-on-brand-update-vs-full-rework%2A%2A"><strong>1) Scope &amp; brief: on-brand update vs full rework</strong></h3>

<p>The scope was the <strong>PHP 8.5 release page</strong> with an <strong>on-brand</strong> constraint. Some entries explored broader rebrands.</p>

<p><strong>Next time we would</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Be more explicit on on-brand requirement.</li>
<li><p>Potentially Split into <strong>two tracks</strong> judged and presented <strong>separately</strong>:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Track A:</strong> on-brand update of the specific page.<br />
<strong>Track B:</strong> blue-sky concept for future reference.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="%2A%2A2-%E2%80%9Cspec-work%E2%80%9D-concerns%2A%2A"><strong>2) “Spec work” concerns</strong></h3>

<p>We kept scope small, didn’t require code, and recognized more than one entry (runner-up and shortlist thanks).</p>

<p><strong>Next time we would:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Prepare a more detailed brief with the community.</li>
<li>Offer a <strong>paid shortlist honorarium</strong>.</li>
<li>Cap deliverables (mock-ups plus optional tiny HTML/CSS), no heavy code.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="%2A%2A3-voting-%26-balance-order-bias%2C-social-reach%2C-weights%2A%2A"><strong>3) Voting &amp; balance (order bias, social reach, weights)</strong></h3>

<p>Order bias and social amplification are real. In this contest we <strong>ignored downvotes</strong> and <strong>used log damping</strong> on upvotes.</p>

<p><strong>Next time we would also:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Use a dedicated voting tool that shuffles candidates.</li>
<li>Optionally hide aggregate reaction counts until voting closes.</li>
<li>Set a 50/50 split between jury and community.</li>
<li>Publish the full calculation sheet upfront for auditability.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="%2A%2Athank-you%2A%2A"><strong>Thank you</strong></h2>

<p>Thanks to all participants, voters, reviewers, and to the jury and design advisors for careful evaluations. Special thanks to <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/"><strong>JetBrains</strong></a> and <a href="https://getrector.com/"><strong>Rector</strong></a> for supporting the community with prizes and encouragement.</p>

<p>If you want to follow implementation, join the thread here: <a href="https://github.com/php/web-php/issues/1592"><strong>php/web-php/issues/1592</strong></a>.</p>

<p>🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/11/05/design-contest-results/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/11/05/design-contest-results/</id><updated>Wed, 05 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Foundation Update, November 2023]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>This post provides insights into The PHP Foundation's recent activities.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>My name is Roman Pronskiy. I’m employed by <a href="https://jetbrains.com/">JetBrains</a> to manage operations at the PHP Foundation. Reach out to me at pronskiy@thephp.foundation.</p>
  
  <p>You can find the full foundation structure <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/">here</a>, including all board members, developers, and the community.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="team-growth">Team Growth</h2>

<p>In September, we initiated an open call for new developers to join the PHP Foundation by launching an <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/09/06/application-form-2023/">application form</a>.</p>

<p>We received a total of 207 applications. From this pool, we selected a shortlist of 12 qualified candidates. Following a comprehensive review and input from existing foundation members, we further refined our selection to 4 outstanding individuals. We will soon announce the new members.</p>

<p>The primary focus for the new developers will be on the maintenance and modernization of PHP’s infrastructure — a critical step towards ensuring PHP being a robust and forward-looking language.</p>

<p>The public work undertaken by our developers can be followed in our monthly <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/roundup/">"PHP Core Roundup"</a> series, which highlights the ongoing progress and developments within PHP core.</p>

<h2 id="advisory-board">Advisory Board</h2>

<p>For our major sponsors, we offer exclusive insights through occasional digests that provide a deeper dive into discussions, debates, and early-stage developments. This not only keeps our sponsors abreast of the latest happenings but also allows them to see the direct impact of their support. This is one of the benefits of being an Advisory Board member.</p>

<p>We announced the advisory board initiative <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/03/31/php-foundation-update-march-2023/#a-new-benefit-for-major-sponsors-%E2%80%93-advisory-board-membership">in March</a>. Since then, 9 companies have joined the initiative with their representatives.</p>

<p>In addition to the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/">Governing Board</a> that includes Automattic, JetBrains, Private Packagist, Symfony, Tideways, Zend by Perforce, and PHP fellows, we now welcome the Advisory Board members: Moodle, Shopware, Laravel, Ardennes-étape, Les-Tilleuls.coop / API Platform, Aternos GmbH, PrestaShop, CraftCMS.</p>

<p>There were several useful discussions within the group. Specifically, we’d like to highlight the one around <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/property-hooks">Property Hooks RFC</a>. The Advisory Board feedback helped to shape the proposal design significantly.</p>

<p>By the way, you can already try property hooks on <a href="https://3v4l.org/">3v4l.org</a>, thanks to <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/SjonHortensius">Sjon Hortensius</a>.
<a href="https://3v4l.org/Y4KZn/rfc#vrfc.property-hooks"><img src="/assets/post-images/2023/3v4l-property-hooks.png"></a></p>

<h2 id="sovereign-tech-fund-invests-in-php">Sovereign Tech Fund invests in PHP</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://sovereigntechfund.de/en/">Sovereign Tech Fund</a> is an organization that supports the development, improvement, and maintenance of open digital infrastructure in the public interest. Its goal to strengthen the open-source ecosystem sustainably, focusing on security, resilience, technological diversity, and the people behind the code. STF is funded by the German Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs and Climate Action (BMWK) and supported by the German Federal Agency for Disruptive Innovation GmbH (SPRIND).</p>

<p>We have collaborated with STF to create work plans for these specific projects: PECL overhaul, Testing tool for FPM, Security Audit, and Documentation improvements.</p>

<p>We’ll share more details on each project early next year, and for now we are thrilled and grateful to the Sovereign Tech Fund for trusting us.</p>

<h2 id="security-audit-of-php-is-coming">Security audit of PHP is coming</h2>

<p>As mentioned above, STF is investing in PHP, and we are going to commission an audit of PHP's C code base. We expect security issues to be found. To mitigate possible bad perception, we aim to publish and fix the revealed security issues at the same time.</p>

<p>For this security audit, we are partnering with <a href="https://ostif.org/">The Open Source Technology Improvement Fund, Inc</a> (OSTIF), a corporate non-profit dedicated to securing critical open-source projects. They have a proven track record of audits for <a href="https://github.com/ostif-org/OSTIF/blob/main/Completed-Engagements.md">popular open-source projects</a> such as cURL, Git, Linux Kernel, OpenSSL, Node.js, and others.</p>

<h2 id="reports-schedule">Reports schedule</h2>

<p>Although we promised to prepare quarterly reports, that unfortunately did not happen to be feasible. So for 2023, we fall back to one yearly report. The 2023 transparency report will be published in December.</p>

<h2 id="meet-us-at-the-conferences">Meet us at the conferences</h2>

<p>You can meet our team at the following conferences in late 2023:</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://php.bettercode.eu/">betterCode(PHP)</a> – Nov 27</strong></p>

<p>Jakub Zalenka will give a talk: "PHP 8.3: Changes and future plans". <br> 
Besides Jakub, there will be talks from Niels Dossche and Sebastian Bergmann.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://live.symfony.com/2023-brussels-con/">SymfonyCon Brussels</a> – Dec 7–8</strong></p>

<p>You’ll be able to meet and talk to our board members: Nils Adermann, Sebastian Bergmann, Nicolas Grekas, and Roman Pronskiy.</p>

<h2 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h2>

<p>Check out the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/#sponsors">Sponsors section</a> on our <a href="https://thephp.foundation/">website</a>. It shows all major contributors sorted by donation amount.</p>

<p>Big thanks to the <strong><a href="https://sentry.io/">Sentry</a></strong> team for sponsoring the PHP foundation!</p>

<p>Sentry is a popular application performance monitoring &amp; error tracking tool, and they <a href="https://blog.sentry.io/we-just-gave-500-000-dollars-to-open-source-maintainers/?utm_source=linkedin&amp;utm_content=blog-fundfest23-learnmore">just gave $500,000 to multiple open source maintainers</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Shout-out to non-financial sponsors</strong></p>

<p><a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/">Digital Ocean</a> has been supporting the PHP project for ages – <a href="https://www.php.net/">php.net</a> servers run on DigitalOcean boxes. We would like to express our gratitude to DigitalOcean for their ongoing support.</p>

<p>Big thanks to <a href="https://thephp.foundation/#sponsors">everyone</a> for your continued support – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<hr />

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> or Mastodon <a href="https://phpc.social/@thephpf">phpc.social/@thephpf</a> to get the latest updates from the PHP Foundation.
💜🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/11/27/php-foundation-update-november-2023/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/11/27/php-foundation-update-november-2023/</id><updated>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Foundation Update, September 2024]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?= 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>Here are some updates we’d like to share with you.</p>

<h2 id="generics-research-progress">Generics Research Progress</h2>

<p>One of our most anticipated projects is the research into generics for PHP. In August, we published a <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/08/19/state-of-generics-and-collections/">comprehensive report on the state of generics and collections in PHP</a>. This research is a crucial step towards potentially implementing generics in future PHP.  The further direction has not been decided yet, so we encourage the PHP community to review the report and provide feedback.</p>

<h2 id="welcoming-ben-marks-as-official-php-foundation-ambassador">Welcoming Ben Marks as Official PHP Foundation Ambassador</h2>

<p>We are thrilled to announce that <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bhmarks/">Ben Marks</a> has stepped up as the official PHP Foundation ambassador. Ben is Director Global Market Development at Shopware, and  was a co-Founder of the Magento Association.</p>

<p>In this role, Ben will:</p>

<ul>
<li>Serve as a liaison between the Foundation and the broader PHP community.</li>
<li>Represent the Foundation at conferences and events.</li>
<li>Help communicate our initiatives and gather feedback from the community.</li>
</ul>

<p>We're confident that Ben's contributions will strengthen our connections within the PHP world and help us better serve the community's needs.</p>

<p>Please give Ben a warm welcome&#33;</p>

<h2 id="website-updates-in-progress">Website Updates in Progress</h2>

<p>We’d like to make sure our <strong><em><a href="https://thephp.foundation">thephp.foundation</a></em></strong> website provides clear information about what we do, how sponsors can support the foundation, and what are the benefits on top of supporting the PHP language maintenance and development. Please share what you think is missing on the website or is not clearly described. Roast the website so we can improve&#33;</p>

<h2 id="shout-out-to-our-sponsors">Shout-out to our Sponsors</h2>

<p>We want to extend a big thank you to all the individuals and organizations supporting The PHP Foundation. This time, we’d like to give special recognition to <a href="https://www.sovereigntechfund.de/">Sovereign Tech Fund</a> for their incredible investment this year. And a big thank you to <a href="https://cybozu.co.jp/en/">Cybozu</a>, <a href="http://Les-Tilleuls.coop">Les-Tilleuls.coop</a>, <a href="https://www.pixiv.net/en/">pixiv Inc.</a>, <a href="https://www.mercari.com/">Mercari Inc.</a>, <a href="https://aternos.gmbh/en/">Aternos GmbH</a>, <a href="https://en.ardennes-etape.be/">Ardennes-étape</a>, <a href="https://chstudio.fr/">CH Studio</a>, and <a href="https://spysystem.dk/">SPY</a>.</p>

<p>We’re also deeply grateful to our major sponsors for their continued commitment: <a href="https://automattic.com/">Automattic</a>, <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/">JetBrains</a>, <a href="https://packagist.com/">Private Packagist</a>, <a href="https://craftcms.com/">Craft CMS</a>, <a href="https://www.zend.com/">Zend by Perforce</a>, <a href="https://tideways.com/">Tideways</a>, and <a href="https://symfony.com/">Symfony</a>.</p>

<p>Thank you so much to <a href="https://thephp.foundation/#sponsors">everyone who sponsored</a> – the PHP Foundation is all of us&#33;</p>

<p><br></p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on X/Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a>, Mastodon <a href="https://phpc.social/@thephpf">phpc.social/@thephpf</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation/">LinkedIn</a> to get the latest updates from the PHP Foundation. 
💜🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/12/php-foundation-update-september-2024/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/12/php-foundation-update-september-2024/</id><updated>Thu, 12 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation Update, March 2022]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>We promised to publish monthly updates, but something everything went wrong in February.</p>

<p>Thank you all for being understanding about the lack of update in February. This post will bring you all up to date on everything that's been accomplished since our last post in January.</p>

<h3 id="php-foundation-core-developers">PHP Foundation Core Developers</h3>

<p>One of our primary goals for 2022 is to find and hire developers to work on the core.</p>

<p>We are excited to reveal our initial group of sponsored developers!</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Arnaud Le Blanc</strong> <a href="https://github.com/arnaud-lb">@arnaud-lb</a></li>
<li><strong>Derick Rethans</strong> <a href="https://github.com/derickr">@derickr</a></li>
<li><strong>Gina Peter Banyard</strong> <a href="https://github.com/Girgias">@Girgias</a></li>
<li><strong>Ilija Tovilo</strong> <a href="https://github.com/iluuu1994">@iluuu1994</a></li>
<li><strong>Jakub Zelenka</strong> <a href="https://github.com/bukka">@bukka</a></li>
<li><strong>Máté Kocsis</strong> <a href="https://github.com/kocsismate">@kocsismate</a></li>
</ul>

<p>You might be surprised to see Derick Rethans’ name in the list above. After all, he was listed as a PHP Fellow when we announced the Foundation last year. Shortly after we launched the Foundation, Derick informed us of his desire to focus his work on developing and maintaining PHP's core and that he wanted to apply for sponsorship from the Foundation to make this happen. To avoid any conflicts of interest, Derick stepped down from his administrative role before he applied for sponsorship.</p>

<p>We are incredibly happy that these core developers have agreed to join the Foundation, and we are looking forward to the great things we can do together.</p>

<h3 id="code-of-conduct">Code of Conduct</h3>

<p>All participants of the PHP Foundation including administration members and developers are expected to abide by the <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.contributor-covenant.org%2Fversion%2F2%2F1%2Fcode_of_conduct%2F">Code of Conduct</a>.</p>

<p>To ensure enforcement of the Code of Conduct we are setting up a dedicated team. Tobias Nyholm <a href="https://github.com/Nyholm">@Nyholm</a>, who leads <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fsymfony.com%2Fcare">Symfony’s CARE team</a>, will be responsible for assembling and running the Foundation’s CoC team. Welcome aboard, Tobias!</p>

<h3 id="what%E2%80%99s-next">What’s next</h3>

<p>Our main goal for the next month is to set up a proper communication and development process. We will conduct several meetings to discuss technical and organizational matters.</p>

<p>Since the purpose of the Foundation is to train the next generation of internal developers, we want to emphasize maintenance and user-focused features to maximize our impact. As such, we will review the efforts and ensure the plans fall in line with such an agenda.</p>

<p>We would also like to reduce the bus factor of PHP. So whenever possible, developers will be expected to update the <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.phpinternalsbook.com%2F">PHP Internals Book</a> to ensure that no knowledge is lost.</p>

<p>On the administration side, we plan to work on increasing the transparency of our operations: to shed some light on the governance structure, discussions, and so on.</p>

<h3 id="php-foundation-stands-with-ukraine-%F0%9F%87%BA%F0%9F%87%A6">PHP Foundation stands with Ukraine 🇺🇦</h3>

<p>On February 24th, 2022, Vladimir Putin's Regime began an illegal war of aggression in Ukraine. There are no words to truly express our outrage at such disregard for human life.</p>

<p>Many PHP developers have lived in or are living in Ukraine, and the PHP Foundation is supported by many backers from Ukraine, including sponsors <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Foroinc.com%2Flets-stop-the-war-together%2F">Oro, Inc.</a> and <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fmacpaw.com%2F">MacPaw</a>.</p>

<p>If you, like many in the PHP Foundation, are desperate to find a way to help, there are some organizations listed below that are working to provide humanitarian aid to people who are caught up in this war.</p>

<p>We are proud that many of our sponsors stand with Ukraine too. Here are just a few examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fsymfony.com%2Fblog%2Fsymfony-stands-with-ukraine">Symfony</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.acquia.com%2Fblog%2Facquia-stands-ukraine">Acquia</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fblog.jetbrains.com%2Fblog%2F2022%2F03%2F11%2Fjetbrains-statement-on-ukraine%2F">JetBrains</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwordpress.org%2Fnews%2F2022%2F03%2Fepisode-26-matt-mullenweg-on-ukraine-community-and-wordpress%2F">Automattic</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/composer/packagist/commit/86244a3695fcaaac9c5ba4257a4314eae1c6d981">Composer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/Livesport_eu/status/1496925425821491208">Livesport.eu</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.shopware.com%2Fen%2Fshopware-and-its-two-founders-support-caritas-international-aid-for-ukraine%2F">Shopware</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Please consider supporting the people of Ukraine. You can find more information on how to do so on the <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fen.isupportukraine.eu%2F">I Support Ukraine</a> website.</p>

<p>If you’d like to make a donation, consider <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.unicefusa.org%2Fwar-ukraine">UNICEF</a>, <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.peopleinneed.net%2Fdonate%2Fonce%3Famount%3D1000%26accountId%3D7">People in Need</a>, or any <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.globalcitizen.org%2Fen%2Fcontent%2Fways-to-help-ukraine-conflict%2F">other humanitarian organization</a> of your choice helping the people not only in Ukraine.</p>

<p>If you are a PHP developer in need of support, reach out to us at social@thephp.foundation and we’ll do everything we can to help you.</p>

<h3 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h3>

<p>Lots of you have kindly donated to the PHP Foundation, and we are extremely grateful!</p>

<p>We’d like to say a massive thanks to the following newly joined major sponsors for their very generous contributions:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fpaycomonline.com%2F">Paycom</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.ec-cube.net%2F">EC-CUBE</a></li>
<li><a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cambiumlearning.com%2F">Cambium Learning, Inc.</a> (<a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.learninga-z.com%2F">Learning A-Z</a>)</li>
</ul>

<p>And shout-out to everyone else who has contributed, we are truly grateful to you all – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>A special mention goes to <a href="https://opencollective.com/redirect?url=https%3A%2F%2F1password.com%2F">1password</a> for <a href="https://github.com/1Password/1password-teams-open-source#the-php-foundation">providing us</a> with a free membership to ensure all of our sensitive data is stored and shared securely.</p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💙💛 ☮️ 🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/03/31/the-php-foundation-update-march-2022/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/03/31/the-php-foundation-update-march-2022/</id><updated>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcoming Passbolt to the PHP Foundation]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We’re thrilled to announce that <strong>Passbolt has joined the PHP Foundation</strong> as a Silver sponsor! PHP powers over 77% of the web – including Passbolt’s collaborative password and secrets manager. Their support strengthens our mission to keep it thriving.</p>

<p>Check out their heartfelt announcement here: <strong><a href="https://www.passbolt.com/blog/a-love-letter-passbolt-joins-the-php-foundation-as-a-company-member">Passbolt’s Blog</a></strong>.</p>

<p>The Foundation funds developers to ensure PHP remains fast, secure, and innovative. With Passbolt and many other industry leaders by our side, we’re building a sustainable future for the language we all rely on.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This post kicks off a new blog series highlighting our amazing sponsors. Stay tuned as we spotlight the companies and individuals driving PHP forward – each one a vital part of our community’s success.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Want to join the effort? <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">Sponsor The PHP Foundation</a> and help us power the web’s backbone!</p>

<p>🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/04/03/welcoming-passbolt-to-the-php-foundation/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/04/03/welcoming-passbolt-to-the-php-foundation/</id><updated>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[30 years of PHP: FrankenPHP is now part of the PHP organisation]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>On June 8, 1995, Rasmus Lerdorf released the first version of the PHP language. Over time, PHP has become the most popular server-side programming language, now powering over 70% of websites!</p>

<p>Exactly 30 years after the first release of PHP, we are proud to announce that <a href="https://frankenphp.dev">FrankenPHP</a>, a modern and high-performance application server based on Caddy, is now part of <a href="https://github.com/php/frankenphp">the PHP organisation on GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>As a reminder, FrankenPHP offers features that are unique in the PHP ecosystem:</p>

<ul>
<li>simplify the development of applications written in PHP;</li>
<li>drastically improve performance, while considerably reducing hosting costs (FinOps) and energy consumption (GreenOps);</li>
<li>facilitate deployment in production, whether on bare-metal servers, or in cloud-native environments;</li>
<li>easily develop real-time features thanks to native <a href="https://mercure.rocks">Mercure</a> protocol support;</li>
<li>extend PHP apps with Go, C, and C++ programming languages;</li>
<li>support the PHP programming language in any application written in Go (server, proxy, in-house development…).</li>
</ul>

<p>The move of FrankenPHP into the PHP organisation follows the announcement of FrankenPHP support by the PHP Foundation, in collaboration with <a href="https://les-tilleuls.coop">Les-Tilleuls.coop</a> (the creator of FrankenPHP) and the team maintaining <a href="https://caddyserver.com">the Caddy web server</a>.</p>

<p>This is the first step towards greater integration of the tool into the language ecosystem.</p>

<p>The roadmap and new features that are likely to change the way PHP applications are developed will be announced at the <strong><a href="https://jb.gg/phpverse-phpf">JetBrains PHPverse 2025</a></strong> online conference on <strong>June 17</strong>, to celebrate PHP's 30th birthday. There is still time to register, and it's free!</p>

<p><a href="https://jb.gg/phpverse-phpf"><img src="/assets/post-images/2025/phpverse_2025.gif" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Happy 30th birthday, PHP! 🎉</p>

<p>🐘💜</p>

<p><div
    class="thread-container"
    data-reddit-thread=""
    data-reddit-search="PHP"
    data-reddit-max-depth="10"
    data-reddit-show-content="false"
    data-reddit-show-controls="true"
></div>
<script>window.REDDITIFY_PROXY_URL = 'https://redditify-proxy.root-8f3.workers.dev';</script>
<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://unpkg.com/redditify/dist/redditify.css">
<script src="https://unpkg.com/redditify/dist/redditify.min.js"></script>
</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/06/08/php-30/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/06/08/php-30/</id><updated>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Foundation Update, April 2022]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>We’re off by two but still happy to bring you an update from the foundation.</p>

<p>It's been a month since the PHP Foundation began to fully deliver on its 2022 goal of hiring developers to work on the PHP core.</p>

<p>Backed by our awesome sponsors, six talented folks have already been doing their work for a whole month. Derick Rethans, Arnaud Le Blanc, Gina Peter Banyard, Jakub Zelenka, and Máté Kocsis started on April 1, and Ilija Tovilo started even earlier than that.</p>

<p>We’ve made the first <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/expenses">payouts</a>, and we will continue making them regularly at the end of each month.</p>

<h2 id="how-were-the-devs-selected%2C-and-how-do-they-work%3F">How were the devs selected, and how do they work?</h2>

<p>We received about 70 applications in total. From them, we selected everyone who had significant experience making <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php-src</a> contributions.</p>

<p>We also now have a pool of a few other candidates, and we will consider involving them later.</p>

<p>All of the current developers are working part time, and everyone has different working hours. The developers devote 10–40% of their time exclusively to PHP core maintenance, bug fixes, code reviews, preparing proposals, and implementing new language features.</p>

<p>You can follow the Foundation team's work in real-time by looking at <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/commits/master">commits in php/php-src</a> and discussions in the <a href="https://externals.io/">Internals mailing list</a>.</p>

<p>In addition to the PHP Foundation team, even more work on the PHP core is being done by Dmitry Stogov, Christoph M. Becker, and many other contributors to core and documentation. We’d like to give a big shout-out and thank-you to them!</p>

<h2 id="php-roundup">PHP Roundup</h2>

<p>We have started a separate <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/04/28/php-roundup-1/">PHP Roundup</a> newsletter that covers the development of the PHP core in more detail. Ayesh Karunaratne, the author of the <a href="https://php.watch/">PHP.Watch</a> website, is leading this initiative.</p>

<p>Check it out and subscribe at <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/04/28/php-roundup-1/">thephp.foundation/blog/2022/04/28/php-roundup-1/</a>.</p>

<h2 id="bigger-picture-and-roadmap">Bigger picture and roadmap</h2>

<p>Some folks have asked us whether there is a roadmap for PHP. The short answer is ‘No’. But we’d be happy to grow to the point where we can have one.</p>

<p>The problem the Foundation was created to address will not be solved overnight simply because the funds become available. While PHP is in a better position than it has ever been in terms of financing, this doesn't do much to improve the bus factor. In other words, financing alone is not able to increase the availability of the expertise needed to execute the kinds of projects that would appear on a roadmap.</p>

<p>Financing allows us to cultivate expertise organically, which results in increasing the bus factor. That is precisely what we are currently doing. The only way to become an expert in PHP is by doing PHP. We are essentially paying contributors to become the kind of experts we will need in the future while at the same time compensating them for their valuable contributions in the present.</p>

<p>It has taken us six months to get this far. And there'll be a time, quite soon, when we can talk more extensively about the future.</p>

<h2 id="website-%E2%80%93-thephp.foundation">Website – <a href="https://thephp.foundation/">thephp.foundation</a></h2>

<p>Thanks to the work of Matthew Weier O'Phinney, the foundation’s official website is now up and running. On its <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/">blog</a>, you can find all the updates and the PHP Roundup series.</p>

<p>The site is open source and is hosted on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/ThePHPF/thephp.foundation">github.com/ThePHPF/thephp.foundation</a>.</p>

<p>It is made with the Sculpin static generator and uses Tailwind CSS. There are some <a href="https://github.com/ThePHPF/thephp.foundation/issues">known issues</a>, and pull requests with fixes and improvements are welcome.</p>

<p>We will add pages about the foundation's structure and team shortly.</p>

<h2 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h2>

<p>We’d like to give a shout-out to everyone for your continued support, we truly appreciate it – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💜🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/05/02/the-php-foundation-update-april-2022/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/05/02/the-php-foundation-update-april-2022/</id><updated>Mon, 02 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation application form for 2026 is now open]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>The PHP Foundation is a non-profit organization with a mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>
  
  <p>Current major sponsors include JetBrains, Automattic, Sovereign Tech Agency, Laravel, GoDaddy.com, Private Packagist, Craft CMS, Zend by Perforce, Tideways, Symfony, Mercari Inc., Les-Tilleuls.coop, pixiv Inc., Aternos GmbH, Sentry, Cybozu, Manychat, and Passbolt.</p>
  
  <p>The foundation pays <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/#core_developers">11 developers</a> to work on the language. See what the foundation achieved in 2024 in the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/03/31/transparency-and-impact-report-2024/">Impact and transparency report</a>. You can also watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2qTJgx2QF9M">Roman Pronskiy's video overview</a> of what the Foundation is working on.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We're opening a regular round of applications for developer positions. We intend to decide on whom we will hire by the end of November. If selected, you would start your work January 1st, 2026.</p>

<p>The application form will be <strong>open until October 30, 2025</strong>.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/v9iTTRFwemRkZett7" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Apply</a>
</p>

<div class="alert italic">
    <span class="inline-block font-bold">⚠️ Note: This is not a job for PHP developers or aspiring PHP developers.</span><br><br>
The development of <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">the PHP core</a> is done in the С programming language, and requires proficiency in system programming.
</div>

<h2 id="what-are-the-requirements%3F">What are the requirements?</h2>

<p>As before, we require experience in PHP core development. Ideally, you should have all, but at least some of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pull-requests / commits to <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a></li>
<li>Experience in writing PHP extensions</li>
<li>Participation in PHP mailing lists</li>
<li>Contributions to other open-source projects</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-are-you-going-to-work-on%3F">What are you going to work on?</h2>

<p>Strategic areas we'd like you to work on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Performance</li>
<li>Security</li>
<li>Infrastructure</li>
<li>Web APIs (json, PDO, streams, etc.)</li>
</ul>

<p>This is not an exhaustive list. We encourage you to <strong>provide as detailed a description of what you want to work on as possible</strong>.</p>

<p>Our primary selection criterion is <strong>pragmatism</strong>. We place greater emphasis on solutions that improve the developer experience and benefit businesses that rely on PHP, rather than new syntax features.</p>

<p>Out of scope:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pure documentation works</li>
<li>Userland PHP packages</li>
<li>Websites</li>
<li>Translations</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-does-working-with-the-php-foundation-involve%3F">What does working with the PHP Foundation involve?</h2>

<p>Working for the PHP Foundation offers a lot of freedom, but it also requires discipline. Your work will roughly consist of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>40% Triaging issues and fixing bugs</li>
<li>30% Working on strategic areas</li>
<li>20% Code reviews</li>
<li>&#62;10% Preparing RFCs and developing new language features</li>
</ul>

<p>As you can see, developing new RFCs is a fairly small part of the job. Most of the work is typical maintenance of an open-source project.</p>

<p>We are a fully distributed team. You can work from any place<strong>&#42;</strong> and at any time. All communication is asynchronous via Slack, GitHub, and Email. We meet for synchronous calls once a month.</p>

<p>Your work should be in line with the foundation's mission statement, and we expect you to follow <a href="https://thephp.foundation/code-of-conduct/">the code of conduct</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>PHP Foundation Mission Statement</strong></p>
  
  <p>The PHP Foundation is a collective of people and organizations relying on the PHP language. Its mission is to ensure the long-term prosperity of the PHP language. The PHP Foundation focuses on providing financial support and guidance to PHP language developers to support its goals of improving the language for its users, providing high-quality maintenance, and improving the PHP language project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors. The PHP Foundation aims to promote the public image of the PHP language in the interest of retaining existing and gaining new users and contributors.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em><strong>&#42;</strong> We do not consider applications from persons residing in sanctioned territories.</em></p>

<h2 id="how-to-apply%3F">How to apply?</h2>

<p>Submit your application now, and we will get back to you shortly. If you have any questions or suggestions, reach out to contact@thephp.foundation.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/v9iTTRFwemRkZett7" target="_blank" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Open submission form</a>
</p>

<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeYNVQoK2r9c6EtoMnDaIpLzDc95egt1a1mcfiHTovqMDhFuw/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1866" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/09/30/application-form-2026/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/09/30/application-form-2026/</id><updated>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Foundation Update, July 2022]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>Last month, the PHP foundation members continued the work on PHP 8.2 release and more. We are prepared to give a few talks this autumn. Also, besides core developers, we have a growing community of volunteers who help the PHP foundation. Read on to learn more.</p>

<h2 id="meet-us-at-the-conferences">Meet us at the conferences</h2>

<p>This autumn, you will be able to talk to the foundation administration members and developers at real-life events!</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://event.afup.org/afup-day-2022/">Forum PHP, Paris – October 13-14</a></strong></p>

<p><strong>Sebastian Bergmann and Roman Pronskiy</strong> will give a talk about the past, the present, and the future of PHP. They will share the status of the Foundation, what has been accomplished in the first year, share some plans, and, of course, answer questions and expect feedback.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I look forward to talk about <a href="https://twitter.com/ThePHPF?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ThePHPF</a> at <a href="https://twitter.com/afup?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@afup</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ForumPHP?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#ForumPHP</a> together with <a href="https://twitter.com/pronskiy?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@pronskiy</a>!<br><br>We’re eager to answer your questions and look forward to hearing your suggestions! <a href="https://t.co/2x8id0mDZ5">pic.twitter.com/2x8id0mDZ5</a></p>&mdash; Sebastian Bergmann (@s_bergmann) <a href="https://twitter.com/s_bergmann/status/1544184297115947010?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 5, 2022</a></blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<p><strong>Gina P. Banyard</strong>, one of the PHP Foundation’s developers, will talk about PHP’s type system internals.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="fr" dir="ltr">Nous sommes ravis d&#39;accueillir pour la première fois <a href="https://twitter.com/Girgias?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@Girgias</a>, jeune et talentueux core-contributeur à PHP, pour un talk sur les rouages du typage lors du Forum PHP 2022.<br>🎤 &quot;Typage en PHP comment ça fonctionne ?&quot; - Forum PHP 2022 - 13&amp;14/10, Disneyland Paris <a href="https://t.co/dB0pWflmKB">pic.twitter.com/dB0pWflmKB</a></p>&mdash; AFUP (@afup) <a href="https://twitter.com/afup/status/1546423801998708736?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 11, 2022</a></blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<p><strong><a href="https://live.symfony.com/2022-paris-con/">SymfonyCon, Paris – November 17-18</a></strong></p>

<p>At this conference, you’ll be able to catch up with Sebastian Bergmann, Roman Pronskiy, and Nicolas Grekas.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://phpconference.com/">International PHP Conference, Munich – October 23-24</a></strong></p>

<p>Sebastian Bergmann and Derick Rethans will each talk at the IPC this year.</p>

<p><em>Where else would you like to see us?</em></p>

<h3 id="%2A%2Aswag%21%2A%2A"><strong>Swag!</strong></h3>

<p>By the way, we’d like to have stickers and other swag for conference attendees. If you would like to help with the design or sponsor the production, please reach out to <a href="&#109;&#x61;i&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x63;&#111;&#x6e;&#x74;&#97;&#x63;t&#64;&#x74;&#104;&#101;&#x70;&#104;&#x70;&#x2e;&#102;&#x6f;&#x75;&#110;&#x64;a&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#110;">contact@thephp.foundation</a>.</p>

<h2 id="website-updates">Website updates</h2>

<p>Thanks to Sergey Panteleev, one of the PHP 8.2 release managers, we have a few nice additions to our website.</p>

<ul>
<li>A new <strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/">structure page</a></strong> where you can see all the people currently actively involved in the PHP Foundation activities.</li>
<li>Every post has a nicely generated preview image — please, share the links to the PHP Foundation to help spread the word.</li>
</ul>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/ThePHPF/thephp.foundation">website is open-source</a> and built with <a href="https://github.com/sculpin/sculpin">Sculpin</a> and <a href="https://tailwindcss.com/">Tailwind CSS</a>. So if you stumbled upon a bug, please do not hesitate to report or submit a PR.</p>

<h2 id="php-core-roundup">PHP Core Roundup</h2>

<p>In July, we marked the feature-freeze for PHP 8.2, and this next version of PHP is being shaped by PHP Foundation members and all the contributors to be an exciting release!</p>

<p>Catch up to this month's PHP Core changes on the <strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/07/28/php-core-roundup-4/">PHP Core Roundup #4</a></strong> post by Ayesh, where you can find a detailed log of what's been done and discussed regarding the PHP engine.</p>

<p><strong>What if our proposal did not make it?</strong></p>

<p>Among many fixes and improvements, some suggestions did not pass the RFC voting barrier. For instance, that happened to the <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/auto-capture-closure">Short Closures 2.0</a> proposal.</p>

<p>We consider this a good experience in any case, and developers might reconsider, improve, and suggest it in the next release cycle, i.e., PHP 8.3.</p>

<p>We also consider it to be a good thing that it's difficult to change the language, as these changes are forever.</p>

<p><strong>What about deprecations?</strong></p>

<p>PHP has a long 25-year history, and no wonder it has some old quirks. One of them relates to DateTime and DateTimeImmutable confusion.</p>

<p>Derrick Rethans, a core developer of the PHP Foundation, asks for an opinion about in which way this confusion should be resolved; if it should:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Making PHP&#39;s DateTime class mutable was one of the bigger mistakes of the Date/Time APIs. I&#39;m considering to change DateTime to be immutable by default in PHP 9, and to drop DateTimeImmutable altogether (or make it an alias). This is likely going to break some code. Opinions?</p>&mdash; Derick Rethans (@derickr) <a href="https://twitter.com/derickr/status/1551611856007069696?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 25, 2022</a></blockquote>

<p>Let Derick know what you think.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can find more insights on PHP core development process in&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/roundup/">PHP&nbsp;Roundup&nbsp;Series</a></strong>.</p>
  
  <p>Tweet at us: <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Ayeshlive">@Ayeshlive</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/pronskiy">@pronskiy</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br></p>

<h2 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h2>

<p>This month we are glad to welcome a new major sponsor who joined the PHP Foundation’s sponsors herd:</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://opencollective.com/cybozu">Cybozu, Inc</a></strong></p>

<p>Thank you for supporting PHP!</p>

<p>Shout-out to <a href="https://thephp.foundation/#sponsors">everyone</a> for your continued support – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<hr />

<p><br></p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💜🐘</p>

<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/08/04/php-foundation-update-july-2022/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/08/04/php-foundation-update-july-2022/</id><updated>Thu, 04 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[PHP Foundation Update, March 2023]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>It's been a while since our last update, so today we’d like to shed some light on what the PHP Foundation has been up to in recent months. Topics include changes to the reporting schedule, a new initiative within the Foundation called the Advisory Board, conferences with Foundation members, and other news.</p>

<h2 id="new-schedule-for-the-foundation%E2%80%99s-updates-and-reports">New schedule for the Foundation’s updates and reports</h2>

<p>Last year we started by publishing monthly updates, followed by an annual report released in October. Check out the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/11/22/transparency-and-impact-report-2022/">Impact and Transparency Report 2022</a> if you haven’t yet had a chance to do so.</p>

<p>Now that the Foundation has moved into a phase of steady growth and there are fewer administrative updates, we will publish an update and report once a quarter. The next report, the PHP Foundation 2023 Q1 Report, will come out in April.</p>

<p>As for the technical details and results of the Foundation’s developer team, nothing has changed. Every month <a href="https://aye.sh/">Ayesh</a> publishes a <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/roundup/">PHP Core Roundup</a> where he talks about what’s kept the team busy and the accomplishments of other PHP contributors.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-is-now-on-github-sponsors">The PHP Foundation is now on GitHub Sponsors</h2>

<p>From the very beginning, we used <a href="https://opencollective.com/">OpenCollective</a> as our financial platform for collecting and distributing funds. We are very happy with and grateful for their service.</p>

<p>For some companies and individuals, though, it’s a lot easier to donate via GitHub Sponsors. To make it easier for them to pitch in, we’ve opened a GitHub Sponsors page: <strong><a href="https://github.com/sponsors/ThePHPF">github.com/sponsors/ThePHPF</a></strong>.</p>

<p>We are going to use GitHub Sponsors only to <em>receive</em> financial support. The funds will then be transferred to OpenCollective on a monthly basis, and we’ll continue to pay developers via OpenCollective, as before.</p>

<h2 id="a-new-benefit-for-major-sponsors-%E2%80%93-advisory-board-membership">A new benefit for major sponsors – Advisory Board membership</h2>

<p>A major goal of the PHP Foundation is to provide a voice for PHP's users in its development, and one initiative is to create an Advisory Board to provide communication between sponsors and the foundation team.</p>

<p>The advisory board's role is to assist in setting priorities for the utilization of the developer time and resources that the foundation provides. In other words, the board helps the foundation determine how best to allocate its funds to support the most critical and beneficial initiatives for the PHP community.</p>

<p>The Advisory Board is a forum for members to discuss shared challenges and propose feedback on developer plans. It provides a platform to exchange ideas and bring forward community concerns. The Foundation will review common requests and sponsor impactful projects, but feedback is provided periodically and not all suggestions will be implemented. It is a shared communication channel for constructive dialogue and common goal-setting.</p>

<p>For the first iteration of the Advisory Board, any company that contributed $10,000 in the early stages of the PHP Foundation will be offered the status of a major sponsor and a seat on the Advisory Board through October 2023. After that, the status and membership will be based on the extent of each member’s contributions and their commitment to continued support.</p>

<p>Currently, membership on the Advisory Board has the following benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Every month we provide developer plans – a list of tasks that the PHP Foundation developers will work on in the near future. Advisory Board members can discuss these plans among their teams and provide us with feedback that they feel we should consider.</li>
<li>Advisory board members are welcome to share their pain points or ideas on behalf of their communities or organizations. Suggestions may be discussed by other members and will be considered by the foundation developers.</li>
</ul>

<p>⚠️ Note: All language decisions go through the established Request for Comments (RFC) process, which is not affiliated with the PHP Foundation. Language decisions are the purview of PHP Internals. It means that some of the PHP Foundation’s efforts may not make it into the language. But with the Advisory Board discussions, we expect increased quality and acceptance rate of the foundation’s RFCs.</p>

<p>We’re also looking into providing some exclusive benefits for individual sponsors and smaller business contributors, as well. What would sound interesting or lucrative to you? Let us know!</p>

<h2 id="meet-us-at-the-conferences">Meet us at the conferences</h2>

<p>This spring, the PHP Foundation admins and developers will attend a few conferences.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://phpconference.com/berlin-en/program-berlin-en/">International PHP Conference</a>, May 22–26, Berlin, Germany</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Sebastian Bergmann (thePHP.cc, PHPUnit), Nils Adermann (Packagist Conductors GmbH, Composer), and Gina Peter Banyard (PHP core developer) will participate in a keynote panel about the PHP Foundation and the State of PHP.</li>
<li>Benjamin Eberlei (Tideways GmbH, Doctrine) and Nils Adermann will give a presentation entitled <em>The PHP Foundation: Past, Present, and Future</em>.</li>
<li>Gina Peter Banyard will present a talk called <em>Contributing to PHP: How?</em></li>
</ul>

<p>Benjamin Eberlei, Nils Adermann, and Sebastian Bergmann are members of the PHP Foundation’s administration. Gina Peter Banyard is one of the PHP core developers paid by the PHP Foundation.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://tek.phparch.com/">php[tek] 2023</a>, May 16–18, Chicago, USA</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Sara Golemon, PHP Foundation admin, will talk about <em>Funding PHP</em>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="derick-rethans-made-it-onto-the-openuk%E2%80%99s-honours-list-for-2023">Derick Rethans made it onto the OpenUK’s Honours List for 2023</h2>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">I am happy to announce that over the holidays I was honoured as part of <a href="https://twitter.com/openuk_uk?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@openuk_uk</a>&#39;s 2023 Honours list, partly due to my work with the <a href="https://twitter.com/ThePHPF?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ThePHPF</a> <a href="https://t.co/AwZmI4iIBh">https://t.co/AwZmI4iIBh</a> <a href="https://t.co/ip01eRBGhG">pic.twitter.com/ip01eRBGhG</a></p>&mdash; Derick Rethans (@derickr) <a href="https://twitter.com/derickr/status/1611014569345912838?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">January 5, 2023</a></blockquote>

<p>Congratulations, Derick!</p>

<h2 id="thank-you-to-our-sponsors">Thank you to our sponsors</h2>

<h3 id="renewed-and-new-sponsorships">Renewed and new sponsorships</h3>

<p>We are very grateful to all the sponsors who continue to support the PHP community via the Foundation. Some of the biggest contributors include:</p>

<ul>
<li>Automattic</li>
<li>Private Packagist</li>
<li>Craft CMS</li>
<li>Tideways</li>
<li>Zend by Perforce</li>
<li>Shopware AG</li>
<li>Aternos GmbH</li>
<li>Ardennes-étape</li>
<li>Cybozu Inc.</li>
<li>Moodle</li>
<li>Rakus</li>
<li>Mercari Inc.</li>
<li>Spryker</li>
<li>Les-Tilleuls.coop</li>
</ul>

<p>Check out the <strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/#sponsors">Sponsors section</a></strong> on our <a href="https://thephp.foundation/">website</a>. It now shows all major contributors sorted by donation amount.</p>

<h3 id="shout-out-to-non-financial-sponsors">Shout-out to non-financial sponsors</h3>

<h4 id="sticker-mule">Sticker Mule</h4>

<p>We’re grateful to <a href="https://www.stickermule.com/">Sticker Mule</a> for official PHP Foundation swag, such as stickers and limited-edition T-shirts. You can find stickers at the conferences where we give talks. Logo and sticker designs are under a CC license, so feel free to use them if you’d like to produce your own merch.</p>

<h4 id="slack">Slack</h4>

<p>Big thanks to <a href="https://slack.com/">Slack</a> who kindly provided us with a pro plan for the messenger. We’d like to personally thank <a href="https://twitter.com/mattbrowndev">Matt Brown</a>, Psalm author and PHP community member, for helping arrange this.</p>

<p>Shout-out to <a href="https://thephp.foundation/#sponsors">everyone</a> for your continued support – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<hr />

<p><br></p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a> or Mastodon <a href="https://phpc.social/@thephpf">phpc.social/@thephpf</a> to get the latest updates from the Foundation.</p>

<p>💜🐘</p>

<script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/03/31/php-foundation-update-march-2023/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/03/31/php-foundation-update-march-2023/</id><updated>Fri, 31 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation Calls for Sponsors: Help&nbsp;Shape the Future of PHP]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hey there, PHP enthusiasts and tech leaders&#33; It's that time of the year again when everyone's crunching numbers and deciding on budgets. We've got an opportunity for you to make a real impact on the PHP ecosystem. Let's dive in.</p>

<p><strong>Don't need convincing? <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">Sponsor us now</a>!</strong></p>

<h2 id="join-us%5C%21-fund-the-future-of-web-development">Join us&#33; Fund the Future of Web Development</h2>

<p>We just opened applications for PHP core language contributors: <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/17/application-form-2025/">The PHP Foundation application form for 2025 is now open</a>.</p>

<p>Here's the deal: <strong>the more sponsors we get, the more ambitious we can be with our plans</strong>. At a minimum, we finance maintenance and security support, but with more funding, we can continue high-reaching projects.</p>

<p>Your sponsorship could help us:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Tackle long-standing bugs</strong> that have been bothering developers for ages.</li>
<li><strong>Implement cool new features</strong> that will make PHP even more awesome.</li>
<li><strong>Improve performance and security</strong> (because who doesn't want a faster PHP).</li>
</ul>

<p>And if we get enough sponsors, we might even venture into some experimental territory. Your support could lead to the next big breakthrough in PHP development.</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-kévin-dunglas">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“To achieve exceptional performance and simplify application deployment, FrankenPHP pushes the PHP engine to its limits and uses it in atypical ways (ZTS, musl libc, specific timeout management...).<br />
<br />
This would not be possible without the excellent work done by the&nbsp;PHP&nbsp;Foundation's team: they correct the problems we report, continuously improve performance and make the engine always more generic and modular, which not only enables us to innovate in FrankenPHP, but also benefits the entire ecosystem by making PHP faster and more reliable.<br />
<br />
By sponsoring the foundation, you're investing in the future of PHP!”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2024/report-2023/kevin_dunglas.png" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Kévin Dunglas, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">author of <a href="https://frankenphp.dev/">FrankenPHP</a></cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<h2 id="2025%3A-the-year-php-turns-30-and-it%27s-going-to-be-epic%5C%21">2025: The Year PHP Turns 30 (and It's Going to Be Epic&#33;)</h2>

<p>PHP is turning 30 in 2025, and we're planning a special celebration&#33; By sponsoring the PHP Foundation, you'll be front and center for this milestone year. Here's what we've got cooking:</p>

<ul>
<li>A massive collaboration with the marketing teams from Laravel, JetBrains, and Zend by Perforce. It's like the Avengers of the PHP world coming together.</li>
<li>A much-needed facelift for php.net. Let's make it shine for PHP’s 30th birthday&#33;</li>
</ul>

<p>Imagine your company being visible as a part of this historic moment. Pretty cool, right?</p>

<h2 id="why-sponsor-the-php-foundation%3F">Why Sponsor the PHP Foundation?</h2>

<p>You might be wondering, "Why should I sponsor the PHP Foundation?" Let us list some of the reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Visibility:</strong> Your brand will be seen by millions of developers worldwide. That's a lot of eyeballs.</li>
<li><strong>Influence:</strong> Help shape the future of one of the most widely used programming languages on the web.</li>
<li><strong>Security:</strong> Without sufficient funding, the PHP language will lack the resources to promptly address bugs your company runs into.</li>
<li><strong>Recruitment:</strong> Attract top PHP talent by showing your commitment to the language.</li>
<li><strong>Giving Back:</strong> If PHP has helped your business grow, here's your chance to return the favor.</li>
<li><strong>Tech Cred:</strong> Nothing says "we're serious about web development" like sponsoring a major programming language.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="ready-to-jump-in%3F">Ready to Jump In?</h2>

<p>Here's how you can get started:</p>

<ol>
<li>Check out our sponsorship tiers on our website: <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">thephp.foundation/sponsor</a>.</li>
<li>Reach out to us at <a href="&#109;&#x61;i&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x63;&#111;&#x6e;&#x74;&#97;&#x63;t&#64;&#x74;&#104;&#101;&#x70;&#104;&#x70;&#x2e;&#102;&#x6f;&#x75;&#110;&#x64;a&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#110;">contact@thephp.foundation</a>.</li>
<li>Let's chat about how we can make this partnership beneficial for both of us.<br />
Office hours call: <a href="http://cal.com/pronskiy/php-foundation-office-hours">cal.com/pronskiy/php-foundation-office-hours</a></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="stay-in-the-loop">Stay in the Loop</h2>

<p>Don't miss out on any PHP Foundation news. Follow us on:</p>

<ul>
<li>LinkedIn: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation">PHP Foundation</a></li>
<li>Twitter/X: <a href="https://x.com/thephpf">@ThePHPF</a></li>
<li>Mastodon: <a href="https://phpc.social/@thephpf">@thephpf@phpc.social</a></li>
</ul>

<p>And for those who prefer their news in their inbox, subscribe to our email newsletter. We send ~1–2 emails a month – just the good stuff about PHP and the Foundation.</p>

<p><div class="px-4 pt-3 border-b border-t -mx-4 border-gray-200">
    <div class="bg-white py-8">
        <div class="mx-auto grid max-w-7xl grid-cols-1 gap-10 lg:grid-cols-12 lg:gap-8">
            <div class="max-w-xl text-4xl font-medium tracking-tight text-gray-900 lg:col-span-6">
                Subscribe to The PHP Foundation newsletter
            </div>
            <form method="POST"
                  action="https://php-foundation.mailcoach.app/subscribe/9be4e2bd-f9d8-475c-b00e-2dcc4cf90056"
                  class="w-full max-w-md lg:col-span-6">
                <div class="flex gap-x-4">
                    <label for="email-address" class="sr-only">Email address</label>
                    <input id="email-address" name="email" type="email" autocomplete="email" required
                           class="min-w-0 flex-auto rounded-md border-0 px-3.5 py-2 text-gray-900 shadow-sm ring-1 ring-inset ring-gray-300 placeholder:text-gray-400 focus:ring-2 focus:ring-inset focus:ring-indigo-600 sm:text-sm sm:leading-6"
                           placeholder="Enter your email">
                    <button type="submit"
                            class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">
                        Subscribe
                    </button>
                </div>
                <div class="mt-4 text-sm leading-6 text-gray-900">
                    No spam. We only send 1–2 emails per month.
                </div>
            </form>
        </div>
    </div>
</div>
</p>

<p>P.S. If you have any questions or wild ideas about how you'd like to support PHP, don't hesitate to reach out. We're all ears.</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/30/call-fo-sponsors/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/30/call-fo-sponsors/</id><updated>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation Update, January 2022]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><code>&lt;?php echo 'Hello world!';</code></p>

<p>In November, the PHP Foundation was launched publicly and we’ve seen enormous support from the community.
Thanks to all of you who have already supported the initiative! We’re planning to update you about our workstream activities on a monthly basis, and this is our first update post.
Let’s take a look at what we’ve been working on!</p>

<h3 id="the-first-round-of-applications-is-now-closed">The first round of applications is now closed</h3>

<p>Since November, many developers have applied for sponsorship, and there were quite a few that we would be very happy to sponsor.</p>

<p>We are discussing the details with applicants and planning the budget.
In order to organize this correctly we need proper documents and agreements.
The JetBrains legal department and OpenCollective staff are helping us to prepare the required paperwork.</p>

<p>We plan to complete the preparations and sign the necessary documents in January.
After that, we will announce the list of the first batch of sponsored developers.</p>

<h3 id="how-we%E2%80%99re-making-decisions">How we’re making decisions</h3>

<p>So far, we have held three administration meetings where we discussed the pressing issues.
Each meeting and the decision-making process are documented in our organization on GitHub at <a href="https://github.com/thephpf">github.com/thephpf</a>.
For now the details are hidden, but we would like to make these meetings and notes public at some point.</p>

<p>In the next few months, we plan to hold biweekly meetings and work on the foundation’s governance, rules, and bylaws.</p>

<h3 id="shout-out-to-our-sponsors">Shout out to our sponsors</h3>

<p>Many thanks to everyone who has donated to the PHP Foundation!</p>

<p>In addition to the founding sponsors – <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com">JetBrains</a>, <a href="https://automattic.com">Automattic</a>, <a href="https://www.acquia.com">Acquia</a>, <a href="https://www.zend.com">Zend</a>, <a href="https://craftcms.com">Craft CMS</a>, <a href="https://laravel.com">Laravel</a>, <a href="https://symfony.com">Symfony</a>, <a href="https://tideways.com">Tideways</a>, <a href="https://www.prestashop.com/en">PrestaShop</a>, and <a href="https://packagist.com">Private Packagist</a> – we have a whole new group of major sponsors!</p>

<p>A big thanks goes to the following companies who donated $10,000 or more:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.rakus.co.jp/">RAKUS</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.livesport.eu/">Livesport s.r.o.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://op.gg/">OP.GG</a></li>
<li><a href="https://polcode.com">Polcode</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.shopware.com">Shopware</a></li>
<li><a href="https://binc.jp">BASE, Inc.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://aternos.org">Aternos GmbH</a></li>
<li><a href="https://digitalscholar.org">Digital Scholar</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.ardennes-etape.be">Ardennes-étape</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Thank you to everyone else who has contributed – the PHP Foundation is all of us!</p>

<p>That’s all for today. Follow us on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/ThePHPF">@ThePHPF</a> to get the latest updates from the foundation.</p>

<p>💖🐘</p>

<p>Feel free to contact us at <a href="&#109;&#x61;i&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x63;&#111;&#x6e;&#x74;&#97;&#x63;t&#64;&#x74;&#104;&#101;&#x70;&#104;&#x70;&#x2e;&#102;&#x6f;&#x75;&#110;&#x64;a&#116;&#x69;&#111;&#110;">contact@thephp.foundation</a>.</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/01/21/the-php-foundation-update-january-2022/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/01/21/the-php-foundation-update-january-2022/</id><updated>Fri, 21 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Manychat: A PHP Foundation Sponsor Sharing Their PHP Scaling Journey]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At the PHP Foundation, we’re proud to be supported by companies that build amazing products and contribute back to the PHP ecosystem. Today we’d like to highlight <a href="https://manychat.com/?utm_source=phpfoundation&amp;utm_medium=site&amp;utm_campaign=casestudy">Manychat</a> — one of our Silver sponsors.</p>

<p>Manychat is the world’s leading chat marketing platform, helping businesses connect with their customers on Instagram, WhatsApp, Facebook Messenger, and beyond. With over <strong>1 billion conversations powered every year</strong> across <strong>170+ countries</strong>, Manychat is a great example of how PHP scales and supports high-traffic applications around the world.</p>

<h2 id="why-php%3F-because-speed-wins">Why PHP? Because Speed Wins</h2>

<p>In their recently published case study — <em><a href="https://medium.com/manychat-engineering/how-manychat-scaled-to-1-billion-conversations-using-php-a-startups-guide-to-smart-tech-choices-781c74f16f23">How Manychat Scaled to 1 Billion Conversations Using PHP</a></em> — the Manychat team shares the story of how PHP helped them go from a tiny startup with just one developer to a platform supporting millions of users.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>“We could build right away — our only developer already knew PHP, so we skipped onboarding and got straight to work.”</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>By choosing PHP, Manychat was able to build their MVP in just a few days and start learning from real users immediately. As they grew, they faced the familiar scaling challenges of high traffic, heavy workloads, and resource management. Their case study provides mentions architectural decisions they made — from using asynchronous request handling with NGINX + Lua, to optimizing background task processing with PHP-CLI workers, and managing database connections efficiently with PgBouncer.</p>

<h2 id="php-at-the-heart-of-a-global-platform">PHP at the Heart of a Global Platform</h2>

<p>Today Manychat’s platform continues to run on PHP, handling millions of API calls and conversations while keeping infrastructure costs under control.</p>

<p>If you’re excited about building products that reach millions and love working with PHP at scale, check out the <a href="https://careers.manychat.com/team/engineering?utm_source=phpfoundation&amp;utm_medium=site&amp;utm_campaign=casestudy">open positions at Manychat</a>. They’re hiring PHP engineers!</p>

<h2 id="supporting-the-community">Supporting the Community</h2>

<p>Manychat isn’t just building with PHP — they’re giving back to the community. As a <strong>Silver sponsor</strong> of the PHP Foundation, they help us fund initiatives that keep PHP stable, modern, and accessible to millions of developers worldwide.</p>

<p>In addition, Manychat is active in the tech community, hosting <a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/o/manychat-46565622503">PHP meetups and events</a> in <strong>Barcelona</strong> and <strong>Amsterdam</strong>. We love seeing our sponsors not only build great products but also foster connections between developers around the world.</p>

<h2 id="read-their-story">Read Their Story</h2>

<p>We encourage you to check out their full case study on scaling with PHP:</p>

<p>👉 <em><a href="https://medium.com/manychat-engineering/how-manychat-scaled-to-1-billion-conversations-using-php-a-startups-guide-to-smart-tech-choices-781c74f16f23">How Manychat Scaled to 1 Billion Conversations Using PHP</a></em></p>

<p><strong>Thank you, Manychat, for your support!</strong></p>

<p>🐘💜</p>

<hr>

<p><br></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This post continues the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/sponsors/">blog series</a> highlighting our amazing sponsors. Stay tuned as we spotlight the companies and individuals driving PHP forward – each one a vital part of our community’s success.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Want to join the effort? <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">Sponsor The PHP Foundation</a> and help us power the web’s backbone!</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/05/09/manychat-powered-by-php/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/05/09/manychat-powered-by-php/</id><updated>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><author><name>Nils Adermann</name><uri>https://twitter.com/naderman</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation application form for 2025 is now open]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The PHP Foundation is a non-profit organization, started in 2021 by Acquia, Automattic, Craft CMS, JetBrains, Laravel, PrestaShop, Private Packagist, Symfony, Tideways, and Zend by Perforce with a mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>

<p>The foundation pays <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/#core_developers">10 developers</a> to work on the language. See what the foundation achieved in 2023 in the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/02/26/transparency-and-impact-report-2023/">Impact and transparency report</a>.</p>

<p>We’re opening a new round of applications for developer positions. We intend to decide on who we will hire by the end of October. If selected, you would start your work January 1st, 2025&#46;</p>

<p>The application form will be <strong>open until October 10, 2024</strong>.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Apply</a>
</p>

<div class="alert">
    <span class="inline-block font-bold">Note: This is not a job for PHP developers or aspiring PHP developers.</span><br> 
The development of PHP is done in the С programming language, and requires proficiency in system programming.
</div>

<h2 id="note%3A-team-size-is-unlikely-to-grow">Note: Team size is unlikely to grow</h2>

<p>While we won’t rule out the possibility of expanding our team, it’s likely we won’t pay more than the current number of 10 developers. Mindful of our budget limitations, we may rather consider restructuring or adjusting our team to make space for any outstanding applications that better help us meet our goals.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-the-requirements%3F">What are the requirements?</h2>

<p>As before, we require previous experience in PHP core development. Ideally you should have all, but at least some of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pull-requests / commits to <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src/">php/php-src</a></li>
<li>Experience in writing PHP extensions</li>
<li>Participation in PHP mailing lists</li>
<li>Contributions to other open-source projects</li>
</ul>

<p>This time, however, we have a clearer idea of the tasks that can be engaged in and so the pool of considered candidates will be wider.</p>

<h2 id="what-are-you-going-to-work-on%3F">What are you going to work on?</h2>

<p>Strategic areas we’d like you to work on:</p>

<ul>
<li>Security</li>
<li>Performance</li>
<li>Infrastructure</li>
<li>Web APIs (json, PDO, streams, etc.)</li>
</ul>

<p>This is not an exhaustive list. We encourage you to <strong>provide as detailed a description of what you want to work on as possible</strong>.</p>

<p>Our primary selection criterion is <strong>pragmatism</strong>. We place greater emphasis on solutions that improve the developer experience and benefit businesses that rely on PHP, rather than new syntax features.</p>

<p>Out of scope:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pure documentation work</li>
<li>PHP packages</li>
<li>Websites</li>
<li>Translations</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-does-working-for-the-php-foundation-look-like%3F">What does working for the PHP Foundation look like?</h2>

<p>Working for the PHP Foundation offers a lot of freedom, but it also requires discipline. Your work will roughly consist of the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>40% Triaging issues and fixing bugs</li>
<li>30% Working on strategic areas</li>
<li>20% Code reviews</li>
<li>&#62;10% Preparing RFCs and developing new language features</li>
</ul>

<p>As you can see, developing new RFCs is a fairly small part of the job. Most of the work is typical maintenance of an open source project.</p>

<p>We are a fully distributed team. You can work from any place<strong>&#42;</strong> and at any time. All communication is asynchronous via Slack, GitHub, and Email. We meet for synchronous calls 1-2 times a month.</p>

<p>Your work should be in line with the foundation’s mission statement, and we expect you to follow <a href="https://thephp.foundation/code-of-conduct/">the code of conduct</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>PHP Foundation Mission Statement</strong></p>
  
  <p>The PHP Foundation is a collective of people and organizations relying on the PHP language. Its mission is to ensure the long-term prosperity of the PHP language. The PHP Foundation focuses on providing financial support and guidance to PHP language developers to support its goals of improving the language for its users, providing high-quality maintenance, and improving the PHP language project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors. The PHP Foundation aims to promote the public image of the PHP language in the interest of retaining existing and gaining new users and contributors.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em><strong>&#42;</strong> We do not consider applications from persons residing in sanctioned territories.</em></p>

<h2 id="how-to-apply%3F">How to apply?</h2>

<p>Submit your application now and we will get back to you shortly. If you have any questions or suggestions, reach out to contact@thephp.foundation.</p>

<p style="text-align: center;">
<a href="https://forms.gle/Ji7Vvj1y2bMf9pUz7" target="_blank" class="inline-block py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">Open submission form</a>
</p>

<iframe src="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSeYNVQoK2r9c6EtoMnDaIpLzDc95egt1a1mcfiHTovqMDhFuw/viewform?embedded=true" width="100%" height="1693" frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0">Loading…</iframe>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/17/application-form-2025/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/09/17/application-form-2025/</id><updated>Tue, 17 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation Turns Three!]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wow. Can you believe it? Just three years (and one day) ago, PHP had no organization behind it. Only two people were being paid to work on the language that powers 70% of the web.</p>

<p>Here’s the very first announcement about the creation of the PHP Foundation: 
<a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/2021/11/the-php-foundation/">The New Life of PHP – The PHP Foundation</a>.</p>

<h2 id="fast-forward-to-today">Fast forward to today</h2>

<p>We now have a team of 10 talented engineers dedicated to PHP. We’re supported by major companies, governments, and an incredible community. That same community is creating amazing projects with PHP, while businesses continue to thrive thanks to a mature, secure, and performant language.</p>

<p>Since 2021, we’ve seen three PHP releases—PHP 8.2, 8.3, and the freshly released <a href="https://www.php.net/releases/8.4/en.php">PHP 8.4</a>. Here are just a few highlights from these releases, developed by the PHP Foundation team:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/property-hooks">Property hooks</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/asymmetric-visibility-v2">Asymmetric Visibility</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/lazy-objects">Lazy Objects</a></li>
<li><a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/19/pie-pre-release/">New tool for installing extensions: pie</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/support_object_type_in_bcmath">Support object type in BCMath</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/saner-inc-dec-operators">Saner Increment/Decrement operators</a></li>
<li>Multiple type system improvements: <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/null-false-standalone-types">null and false as stand-alone types</a>, <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/dnf_types">Disjunctive Normal Form Types</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/readonly_amendments">Readonly amendments</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/dynamic_class_constant_fetch">Dynamic class constant fetch</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/arbitrary_static_variable_initializers">Arbitrary static variable initializers</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="feature-development-is-only-about-20%25-of-what-the-foundation-team-does">Feature development is only about 20% of what the foundation team does</h2>

<p>Behind the scenes, there’s a lot more: triaging and fixing issues, handling security reports, reviewing code, updating documentation, and maintaining infrastructure. All of this work empowers the community and ensures PHP is stable and reliable.</p>

<p>Here are some highlights:</p>

<ul>
<li>The total contributions to the PHP repositories grew by 51+%</li>
<li>We conducted the first external security audit for PHP in 10 years</li>
<li>We extended security support for PHP versions by one year</li>
<li>We improved CI and testing infrastructure</li>
<li>We introduced automated benchmarks to track performance regressions</li>
</ul>

<p>None of this would be possible without our sponsors. Huge thanks to every company and individual who has supported us over the past three years!</p>

<p>Special shout-outs to:<br />
JetBrains, Automattic, Sovereign Tech Agency, Craft CMS, Private Packagist, Tideways, Zend by Perforce, Laravel, Symfony, Mercari Inc., Les-Tilleuls.coop, pixiv Inc., Aternos GmbH, Sentry, Ardennes-étape, Cybozu,</p>

<p>and many others — PHP is all of us!</p>

<p>If you haven’t already, please consider <a href="https://thephp.foundation/sponsor/">sponsoring the PHP Foundation</a> 🙏</p>

<p>Here’s to PHP and many more years ahead!<br />
🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/22/php-foundation-turns-three/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/11/22/php-foundation-turns-three/</id><updated>Fri, 22 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation
Team Update 2024]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Now in our third year, we're gearing up to grow our impact. This year, four more developers are joining the PHP Foundation to further advance PHP.</p>

<p>Since April 2022, the PHP Foundation has contracted six outstanding developers:</p>

<ul>
<li>Arnaud Le Blanc <a href="https://github.com/arnaud-lb">@arnaud-lb</a></li>
<li>Derick Rethans <a href="https://github.com/derickr">@derickr</a></li>
<li>Gina Peter Banyard <a href="https://github.com/Girgias">@Girgias</a></li>
<li>Ilija Tovilo <a href="https://github.com/iluuu1994">@iluuu1994</a></li>
<li>Jakub Zelenka <a href="https://github.com/bukka">@bukka</a></li>
<li>Máté Kocsis <a href="https://github.com/kocsismate">@kocsismate</a></li>
</ul>

<p>All of them started as part-time contributors, and since then have significantly grown their capacity and dedication to PHP core tasks. We consider it a big achievement that the team continues to collaborate effectively, accumulating more experience and knowledge, and expanding their PHP Core involvement.</p>

<h2 id="team-update-2024">Team Update 2024</h2>

<p>We are happy to announce a team expansion. Four talented developers are joining as part-time team members of the foundation.</p>

<ul>
<li>David Carlier <a href="https://github.com/devnexen">@devnexen</a></li>
<li>James Titcumb <a href="https://github.com/asgrim">@asgrim</a></li>
<li>Saki Takamachi <a href="https://github.com/SakiTakamachi">@SakiTakamachi</a></li>
<li>Shivam Mathur <a href="https://github.com/shivammathur">@shivammathur</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Please give them a warm welcome! We are looking forward to the great things we will accomplish together.</p>

<p>Happy New Year! 🎉🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/01/03/the-php-foundation-team-update-2024/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/01/03/the-php-foundation-team-update-2024/</id><updated>Wed, 03 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><author><name>Joe Watkins</name><uri>https://github.com/krakjoe</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcoming Joe Watkins as a PHP Foundation Developer]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We’re excited to share that Joe Watkins is joining the PHP Foundation as a contractor for the rest of 2025&#46;</p>

<p>Joe has helped <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/2021/11/the-php-foundation/">establish the PHP Foundation</a> in 2021 and is a long-time contributor to PHP core. He is known for his work on extensions like <a href="https://github.com/krakjoe/parallel">parallel</a> and <a href="https://github.com/krakjoe/pcov">PCOV</a> and most recently, he released <a href="https://krakjoe.github.io/ort/">ORT</a>, a blazing-fast ONNX runtime for PHP bringing native AI inference capabilities to PHP developers for the first time.</p>

<p>This decision comes outside our usual funding cycle, and it’s driven by two key factors:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>Joe’s renewed health and momentum.</strong> While we initially planned to bring Joe on board in August 2024, his health at the time didn’t allow it. After reviewing our budget post-H1 2025 and realizing we had extra room, we saw an opportunity to support Joe’s return and enable him to contribute once again.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The impact of his work.</strong> ORT is a concrete step toward making PHP more capable and future-proof. Beyond code, Joe has also contributed to the PHP process itself — having proposed and championed several process-related RFCs over the years that helped shape how PHP evolves.</p></li>
</ol>

<p>Joe is contracted for a limited number of hours in H2 2025&#46; For 2026, he will be welcome to apply through our regular contributor funding process later this month, alongside others.</p>

<p>Here is what Joe has to say:</p>

<figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/2236138?s=200&v=4" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Joe Watkins</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>

<blockquote>
  <p>When we established The PHP Foundation, we were focused on raising the bus factor of PHP.</p>
  
  <p>It's years later now, and the bus factor is no longer a major concern. The Foundation has contracted and trained very skilled developers, and the effort they have put in cannot be understated.<br />
  <br />
  Moreover, we have the means to train and pay new developers, should the ones we have now decide to pursue other professional opportunities.</p>
  
  <p>We also imagined that from The Foundation would emerge a vision for PHP, something loosely resembling a roadmap. This isn't because The Foundation wanted to take control of the direction of the project, but rather a more practical concern. Namely, it's difficult to get sponsorship for "maintenance and development". It's easier to convince businesses to sponsor our activities when we know our goals are aligned.</p>
  
  <p>No such road map has materialized; The Foundation has many generous businesses sponsoring the work that goes on, but the bi-directional communication between sponsors and developers is limited, and so alignment is not assured.</p>
  
  <p>I joined the foundation as a developer so that I can address this problem.</p>
  
  <p>My intention is to be the conduit between sponsors (the board members) and developers, to advocate for developers, and to communicate with them on behalf of the board.</p>
  
  <p>I will also, as a developer, be able to advance my own ideas for the future of PHP.</p>
  
  <p>PHP has been around for so long it feels like a part of the furniture of the web. It seems obvious that in ten years, PHP will still be relevant, as it was for the last ten and the ten years before that.</p>
  
  <p>This isn't really the case; PHP has thrived because the ecosystem of the web allowed it to. While internals is focused on the development of the language at a syntax and API level, there's limited discussion of PHP "the product". PHP is a product, and The Foundation has to function something like a business, although our profit is measured in progress rather than pennies. We need to ask questions about adoption rates and relevance in a changing digital landscape. We must be able to answer these questions.</p>
  
  <p>With an increase in bi-directional communication between board and developers, and the clarity this brings to our shared and declared goals, we can start to answer these questions.</p>
  
  <p>If I succeed in my goals, there will emerge a roadmap, a physical document you can link to. But perhaps more importantly, we will have the necessary processes and structure in place within The Foundation to develop and maintain that roadmap and required alignment so that our work continues to address the concerns of the businesses paying for it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Please join us in welcoming Joe back — and if you haven’t yet, check out what he’s been working on: <a href="https://github.com/krakjoe">github.com/krakjoe</a>.</p>

<p>💜🐘</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/09/25/joe-watkins/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2025/09/25/joe-watkins/</id><updated>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation: Impact and Transparency Report 2023]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="executive-summary">Executive Summary</h2>

<p>At the beginning of 2024, The PHP Foundation is a collective of <strong>9 volunteer board members</strong>, <strong>1 full-time operations manager</strong> sponsored by JetBrains, and <strong>10 developers</strong> paid part-time/full-time who make more than half of the contributions to the PHP language and its extensions.</p>

<p>In 2023, The PHP Foundation received <strong>$418,669 in financial contributions</strong> from organizations and individuals.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation’s main focus in 2023 was strengthening the maintenance of PHP core, the project that lives in the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> GitHub repository. This project is the home of the PHP language, where PHP’s interpreter is developed. Everyone who uses PHP benefits in one way or another from the work that is done in this repository.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation demonstrates its growing impact on the language through an increased volume and velocity of code contributions and reviews. The 6 part-time and full-time developers contracted by The PHP Foundation were responsible for nearly half of the commits and reviews made in the PHP language.</p>

<p>Moreover, the foundation's presence and activities have led to heightened interest and activity in the PHP project overall, with the total number of <strong>contributions to the language growing by 79% compared to 2022</strong>.</p>

<p>At the end of 2023, the German government’s <strong>Sovereign Tech Fund chose to invest in The PHP Foundation’s mission</strong> by providing funding for a security audit and other long outstanding projects critical for the PHP ecosystem.</p>

<p>The foundation is <strong>expanding its development efforts in 2024</strong> by contracting 4 additional developers and increasing the number of hours that current contracted developers are working.</p>

<p>The foundation plans to spend up to $1,045,000, including compensation and fees. We are looking for additional sponsor contributions to allow us to continue these efforts in the next years.</p>

<p>In 2024, we aim to achieve the following strategic goals:</p>

<ul>
<li>Ensure sustainable sponsorship for the foundation.</li>
<li>Ensure that foundation developers focus on valuable tasks.</li>
<li>Promote PHP within the web development ecosystem.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-mission">The PHP Foundation Mission</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation was initiated by JetBrains, Automattic, Laravel, Acquia, Zend, Private Packagist, Symfony, Craft CMS, and Tideways. It was publicly <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/2021/11/the-php-foundation/">launched</a> on November 22, 2021.</p>

<p>Since 2021, many companies and individuals have joined the initiative. To make the priorities of the foundation more clear and aligned, we’ve <strong>updated the mission statement</strong>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The PHP Foundation’s mission is to ensure the long-term prosperity of the PHP language. The PHP Foundation focuses on providing financial support and guidance to PHP language developers to support its goals of improving the language for its users, providing high-quality maintenance, and improving the PHP language project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors. The PHP Foundation aims to promote the public image of the PHP language in the interest of retaining existing and gaining new users and contributors.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><br>
So it defines 4 priorities of the foundation:</p>

<ol>
<li>Improve the language for users.</li>
<li>Provide high-quality maintenance.</li>
<li>Improve the project to retain current contributors and to integrate new contributors.</li>
<li>Promote the public image of PHP.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="organizational-growth">Organizational Growth</h2>

<p>Many companies with a vested interest in PHP’s prosperity made a major financial contribution during the year. These are the companies that contributed $10,000 or more in 2023:</p>

<p><strong>JetBrains, Automattic, Private Packagist, Craft CMS, Tideways, pixiv Inc., Mercari Inc., Symfony Corp, Aternos GmbH, Sentry, Ardennes-étape, Zend by Perforce, Les-Tilleuls.coop, Cybozu.</strong></p>

<p>Overall, 718 organizations and individuals sponsored the foundation in 2023 <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation">on Open Collective</a> and <a href="https://github.com/sponsors/ThePHPF">GitHub Sponsors</a>.</p>

<h3 id="quotes">Quotes</h3>

<p>Here is what some of the prominent folks say about the foundation.</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-brandon-kelly">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“We’re proud supporters of the PHP Foundation here at Craft CMS. PHP has played such a huge role in our careers, and it’s an honor to be a part of its story.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2024/report-2023/brandon_kelly.jpg" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Brandon Kelly, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">CEO at Craft CMS</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-ben-marks">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“So much of our world - the content we consume (blogs, ecommerce, social media) -  is delivered via PHP applications, enabled by the continuing efforts of the PHP Foundation and the ecosystem it enables. The PHP ecosystem's success has a significant impact on all of our lives, and we at Shopware are therefore proud supporters of the PHP Foundation.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2024/report-2023/ben_marks.jpg" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Ben Marks, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Director Global Market Development at shopware AG</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-kevin-dunglas">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“Les-Tilleuls.coop is proud to support the PHP Foundation. By maintaining the language, the foundation is ensuring the future of PHP and the web. By adding innovative new features, it simplifies knowledge sharing and, in the spirit of free software, makes it easier than ever for everyone to create independent sites and applications.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2024/report-2023/kevin_dunglas.png" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Kevin Dunglas, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Les-Tilleuls.coop, FrankenPHP</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-matthew-weier-o&#039;phinney">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“As longtime contributors to the PHP project, both financially as well as by employing developers on the project, Zend by Perforce is pleased to sponsor the PHP Foundation and support its mission. Expanding the pool of maintainers and developers capable of evolving the language will help keep PHP relevant, and expand its reach in the web development ecosystem.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2024/report-2023/mwop.jpg" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Matthew Weier O&#039;Phinney, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Senior Product Manager, Zend by Perforce</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><br></p>

<h2 id="the-sovereign-tech-fund-investment">The Sovereign Tech Fund Investment</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://sovereigntechfund.de/en/">Sovereign Tech Fund</a> (STF) supports the development, improvement, and maintenance of open digital infrastructure in the public interest. Its goal is to strengthen the open-source ecosystem sustainably, focusing on security, resilience, technological diversity, and the people behind the code. STF is funded by the German Federal Ministry for Economic Affairs and Climate Action (BMWK) and supported by the German Federal Agency for Disruptive Innovation GmbH (SPRIND).</p>

<p>We have collaborated with STF to create work plans for these specific projects:</p>

<h4 id="pecl-overhaul">PECL overhaul</h4>

<p>The current system for distributing PHP extensions, PECL/PEAR, is outdated and prone to supply-chain attacks, making it unreliable for average developers. This leads to the creation of redundant tools and new security issues.</p>

<p>We proposed to rewrite the PECL installer, replacing the messy pear code and the inefficient website.</p>

<p>Follow the progress of <strong>the new tool 🥧PIE</strong> here: <a href="https://github.com/ThePHPF/pie-design">https://github.com/ThePHPF/pie-design</a>.</p>

<h4 id="testing-tool-for-fpm">Testing tool for FPM</h4>

<p>Currently, the PHP project's testing framework lacks more specialized support for the automated testing of the FastCGI Process Manager (FPM), especially for issues that require higher load. We propose to develop an FPM/SAPI testing tool that can execute all applications and set expectations on the produced logs and server responses. This tool will be connected with a load testing tool (e.g., wrk) to simulate real-world usage and load.</p>

<p>The work has started in the <a href="https://github.com/bukka/wst">https://github.com/bukka/wst</a> repository with the plan to move it to the PHP GitHub organization when ready.</p>

<h4 id="security-audit">Security Audit</h4>

<p>PHP, like any other language, has its share of security issues. We are going to collaborate with a security research group for a comprehensive codebase audit and address the discovered issues. This will significantly improve the security of PHP and make it more reliable for developers and businesses.</p>

<p>The audit is being organized in partnership with <a href="https://ostif.org/">OSTIF</a>.</p>

<h4 id="documentation-improvements">Documentation improvements</h4>

<p>The current PHP documentation has several blind spots, with many functions and methods not covered at all. We propose to update and modernize the English PHP documentation, review and remove user comments, integrate 3v4l.org for interactive examples, and simplify the maintenance process. This will make PHP more accessible to new developers and serve as a reliable reference for experienced ones.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-governance">The PHP Foundation Governance</h2>

<p>In 2023, we renamed the Administration group to the <strong>Governing Board</strong> to avoid confusions and better align with industry standards.</p>

<p><a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/#admins">The lineup</a> of the group has not changed and consists of veteran PHP community leaders, representatives of the founding companies, and other key stakeholders.</p>

<p>One notable change compared to the previous year is a full-time operations manager sponsored by JetBrains in addition to the financial contribution.</p>

<p>We aim to establish a level of involvement for other key stakeholders from the PHP world through the Advisory Board and other initiatives.</p>

<h2 id="the-advisory-board">The Advisory Board</h2>

<p>To keep major sponsors of PHP abreast of the latest happenings in the foundation and allow them to see the direct impact of their support, we announced the advisory board initiative <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2023/03/31/php-foundation-update-march-2023/#a-new-benefit-for-major-sponsors-%E2%80%93-advisory-board-membership">in March</a>.</p>

<p>In addition to the <a href="https://thephp.foundation/structure/">Governing Board</a> representatives from Automattic, JetBrains, Private Packagist, Symfony, Tideways, and Zend by Perforce, the <strong>Advisory Board includes members from</strong> Moodle, Shopware, Laravel, Ardennes-étape, Les-Tilleuls.coop / API Platform, Aternos GmbH, PrestaShop, CraftCMS.</p>

<p>Your company can <strong><a href="https://thephp.foundation/join/">become a member</a></strong> by contributing a minimum of $12,000 to The PHP Foundation as at least a Silver Sponsor.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-staff">The PHP Foundation Staff</h2>

<h3 id="renewing-contracts">Renewing contracts</h3>

<p>In 2023, we had a team of 6 developers. All of them demonstrated a high quality of work and dedication to the mission of the foundation. We were happy to renew the contracts for 2024 as well as extend the total number of hours for developers requesting it.</p>

<p>We have also adjusted the compensation rates for developers to better reflect the market, as the rates had not changed since 2021.</p>

<p>We aim to review the rates every year based on the available funding and priorities.</p>

<h3 id="team-extension">Team extension</h3>

<p>As was mentioned in the previous transparency report, we aimed to extend the team. It did not happen in 2023 because one of the prospective developers could not join the team for personal reasons, and had to step down from PHP core development entirely. Again, this is <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/2021/11/the-php-foundation/#the_bus_factor">the Bus Factor at its worst</a>. However, we were able to extend the team starting with 2024.</p>

<p>We accepted applications for developer positions from September through October 2023. We received about 200 resumes, and we’ve chosen 4 developers with a proven track record of contributions to the PHP language and ecosystem.</p>

<p>We offered the new developers 6-month trial contracts so that the developers and the Governing Board can evaluate the results and then decide whether to continue the engagements.</p>

<h3 id="the-team-as-of-2024">The team as of 2024</h3>

<p>Starting from January, we now contract 10 developers to work on PHP:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Arnaud Le Blanc</strong> <a href="https://github.com/arnaud-lb">@arnaud-lb</a></li>
<li><strong>David Carlier</strong> <a href="https://github.com/devnexen">@devnexen</a></li>
<li><strong>Derick Rethans</strong> <a href="https://github.com/derickr">@derickr</a></li>
<li><strong>Gina Peter Banyard</strong> <a href="https://github.com/Girgias">@Girgias</a></li>
<li><strong>Ilija Tovilo</strong> <a href="https://github.com/iluuu1994">@iluuu1994</a></li>
<li><strong>Jakub Zelenka</strong> <a href="https://github.com/bukka">@bukka</a></li>
<li><strong>James Titcumb</strong> <a href="https://github.com/asgrim">@asgrim</a></li>
<li><strong>Máté Kocsis</strong> <a href="https://github.com/kocsismate">@kocsismate</a></li>
<li><strong>Saki Takamachi</strong> <a href="https://github.com/SakiTakamachi">@SakiTakamachi</a></li>
<li><strong>Shivam Mathur</strong> <a href="https://github.com/shivammathur">@shivammathur</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="team-timeline">Team timeline</h3>

<p>We established the following timeline for team review.</p>

<ul>
<li>January 2024: Developers start work according to the new contracts.</li>
<li>May 2024: Evaluate new developers, contracts are extended, expanded, or terminated after the first 6 months.</li>
<li>September 2024: Open applications for new developers, evaluate performance of the current group of developers.</li>
<li>October 2024: Evaluate applications, work out updates to compensation, decide on a budget.</li>
<li>November 2024: Renew contracts with existing developers, potentially sign contracts with new developers.</li>
</ul>

<p>And in 2025 we start the cycle again.</p>

<h2 id="retrospective%3A-goals-of-2023">Retrospective: Goals of 2023</h2>

<p>In the previous report, we outlined a few organizational and technical goals. Let’s look back and evaluate the results.</p>

<h3 id="organization-goals">Organization goals</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Extend the foundation developers team. ✅</strong><br/>
We did not grow in 2023 strictly speaking, but the work done in 2023 helped to build the ground for two contracted developers to go full-time, as well as to hire 4 new developers.<br/><br/></li>
<li><strong>Grow the community of the foundation. ✅</strong><br/>
The foundation’s Slack became a hub for the community and helped to move initiatives.<br/><br/></li>
<li><strong>Improve communication and provide clear benefits for sponsors. ✅</strong> <br/>
We created a <a href="https://thephp.foundation/join/#membership-deck">deck with benefits for sponsors</a> and started the advisory board initiative. <br/><br/></li>
<li><strong>Explore strategic partnerships and marketing opportunities. ✅ / ❌</strong><br/>
We received investment from the Sovereign Tech Fund and started collaboration with OSTIF.<br/>
We did not explore any marketing opportunities. And there is a room for many more strategic partnerships.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="technical-goals">Technical goals</h3>

<ul>
<li><strong>Ongoing maintenance and development of the PHP core.  ✅</strong> <br/><br/></li>
<li><strong>Improve the quality of the ideas and RFCs coming from the foundation. ✅</strong><br/>
One of the examples here could be <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/property-hooks">Property Hooks RFC</a>. Although it has not been voted on yet, we have put amazing work into it and consulted many different parties to make it as good as possible.<br/><br/></li>
<li><strong>Develop a high-level roadmap and vision for PHP changes sponsored by the foundation. ❌</strong><br/>
The roadmap and vision need further development and discussion. However, we conducted several pieces of research, both quantitative and qualitative. Some of these findings were shared at conferences where we participated, including PHPCon Poland, SymfonyCon, and Laracon EU. We plan to continue this work.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="php-language-impact">PHP Language Impact</h2>

<p>On a daily basis, the PHP Foundation staff team contributes to the open-source repositories of the <a href="https://github.com/php">PHP GitHub organization</a>. The foundation team contributes in many forms: filing issues, reviewing pull requests, participating in discussions on mailing lists, triaging issues, submitting RFC proposals.</p>

<p>In this document, four categories of contributions are presented in more detail: commits to php-src, reviews of pull requests on php-src, submitted RFC documents, and documentation work.</p>

<h3 id="commits-to-php">Commits to PHP</h3>

<p>The following chart summarizes the number of commits made to the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> repository in 2023.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th></th>
  <th>2022</th>
  <th>2023</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td>Total by The PHP Foundation</td>
  <td>683</td>
  <td>784</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Total other</td>
  <td>885</td>
  <td>1588</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2024/transparency-and-impact-report-2023/2024-02-26-transparency-and-impact-report-2023.md-1.svg" alt="Diagram 0" /></p>

<p>Note that the number of commits does not fairly represent the level of effort or the scope of the work. However, it can demonstrate the foundation's relative level of contribution to the PHP core through an objective metric.</p>

<h3 id="reviews">Reviews</h3>

<p>The diagram summarizes the number of pull request reviews made in the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> repository from January 1 to December 31, 2023.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th></th>
  <th>2022</th>
  <th>2023</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td>Total by The PHP Foundation</td>
  <td>283</td>
  <td>702</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Total other</td>
  <td>551</td>
  <td>416</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2024/transparency-and-impact-report-2023/2024-02-26-transparency-and-impact-report-2023.md-2.svg" alt="Diagram 1" /></p>

<h3 id="rfcs">RFCs</h3>

<p>Below are the RFC proposals authored or co-authored by The PHP Foundation developers in 2023 (random order).</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th>RFC</th>
  <th>Proposed</th>
  <th>Status</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/deprecate-implicitly-nullable-types">Deprecate implicitly nullable parameter types</a></td>
  <td>2023-12-20</td>
  <td>Under Discussion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/deprecate_functions_with_overloaded_signatures">Deprecate functions with overloaded signatures</a></td>
  <td>2023-01-31</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/datetime-exceptions">More Appropriate Date/Time Exceptions</a></td>
  <td>2023-02-08</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/proper-range-semantics">Define proper semantics for range() function</a></td>
  <td>2023-03-13</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/typed_class_constants">Typed class constants</a></td>
  <td>2020-07-06</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/assert-string-eval-cleanup">Deprecate remains of string evaluated code assertions</a></td>
  <td>2023-05-31</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/saner-array-sum-product">Saner array_(sum&#124;product)()</a></td>
  <td>2023-01-14</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/saner-inc-dec-operators">Path to Saner Increment/Decrement operators</a></td>
  <td>2022-11-21</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/rfc1867-non-post">RFC1867 for non-POST HTTP verbs</a></td>
  <td>2023-10-06</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/unbundle_imap_pspell_oci8">Unbundle ext/imap, ext/pspell, ext/oci8, and ext/PDO_OCI</a></td>
  <td>2023-10-03</td>
  <td>Accepted</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/policy-repository">Policy Repository</a></td>
  <td>2023-12-04</td>
  <td>Implemented</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/access_scope_from_magic_accessors">Access Scope from Magic Accessors</a></td>
  <td>2023-01-19</td>
  <td>Withdrawn</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/deprecations_php_8_4">Deprecations for PHP 8.4</a></td>
  <td>2023-07-25</td>
  <td>Draft</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/file-descriptor-function">Add file_descriptor() function</a></td>
  <td>2023-01-16</td>
  <td>Under Discussion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/core-autoloading">New core autoloading mechanism with support for function autoloading</a></td>
  <td>2023-04-03</td>
  <td>Under Discussion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/property-hooks">Property hooks</a></td>
  <td>2023-01-03</td>
  <td>Under discussion</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/release_cycle_update">Release cycle update</a></td>
  <td>2023-11-05</td>
  <td>Under Discussion</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="release-maintenance">Release Maintenance</h3>

<p>Jakub Zelenka, one of the foundation developers, also volunteered to be a release manager for PHP 8.3. The PHP Foundation supported such an initiative.</p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-brand-%26-public-channels">The PHP Foundation brand &amp; public channels</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation represents a community of core PHP developers and advocates for the PHP programming language. The channels listed below were used by the PHP Foundation for public communication:</p>

<ul>
<li>11,481 Twitter followers <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">https://twitter.com/thephpf</a></li>
<li>10,320 LinkedIn page followers <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation">https://www.linkedin.com/company/phpfoundation</a></li>
<li>684 Mastodon followers <a href="https://phpc.social/@thephpf">https://phpc.social/@thephpf</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The PHP Foundation members gave talks at multiple conferences throughout the year:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.phpconference.co.uk/">PHP UK Conference</a> – Derick Rethans</li>
<li><a href="https://phpconference.com/">International PHP Conference</a> – Nils Adermann, Benjamin Eberlei</li>
<li><a href="https://froscon.org/en/">FrOSCon</a> – Sebastian Bergmann</li>
<li><a href="https://tek.phparch.com/">php&#91;tek&#93;</a> – Derick Rethans</li>
<li><a href="https://events.drupal.org/lille2023/session/php-foundation-0">DrupalCon Lille</a> - Nils Adermann</li>
<li><a href="https://php.bettercode.eu/">betterCode(PHP)</a> – Jakub Zalenka</li>
<li><a href="https://event.afup.org/">ForumPHP</a> – Gina P. Banyard</li>
<li><a href="https://2023.phpcon.pl/en/">PHPCon Poland</a> – Roman Pronskiy</li>
<li><a href="https://live.symfony.com/2023-brussels-con/">SymfonyCon</a> – Nicolas Grekas</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="official-recognition-on-the-php-website">Official Recognition on the PHP website</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation is now officially endorsed on the php.net website. This was the result of a community vote on <a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/promote_php_foundation">RFC Promote the PHP Foundation</a>. Big thanks to Jim Winstead and the PHP community for this.</p>

<h2 id="financial-report">Financial report</h2>

<p>In 2023, The PHP Foundation was financially backed by organizations and individuals with the goal of paying a competitive salary to as many core developers as possible.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th></th>
  <th>2021 - 2022</th>
  <th>2023</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td>Total contributed to The PHP Foundation</td>
  <td>$ 712,484</td>
  <td>$ 478,767</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Fees *</td>
  <td>$ 90,273</td>
  <td>$ 60,098</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Total received</td>
  <td>$ 622,211</td>
  <td>$ 418,669</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>Paid to developers</td>
  <td>$ 133,285</td>
  <td>$ 275,181</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><br>
<em>* Fees include a 10%  Open Source Collective fiscal host fee (dealing with contracts, expense reviews and payments, bank account management, official registrations and dealing with government requirements, open collective platform development etc.), and 1-5% percent of payment processing fees, depending on the payment method used.</em></p>

<p>All incoming and outgoing <strong>transactions of The PHP Foundation are publicly available</strong> to view for anyone: <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation#category-BUDGET">https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation#category-BUDGET</a></p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2024/report-2023/budget.png" alt="Budget" /></p>

<h3 id="expenses">Expenses</h3>

<p><a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/expenses">https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/expenses</a></p>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2024/report-2023/expenses.png" alt="Expenses" /></p>

<h2 id="goals-for-2024">Goals for 2024</h2>

<p>Our foremost mission remains the same: <strong>maintain and develop the PHP language</strong>. We’d like PHP to be the best platform for users and for businesses creating web applications and APIs.</p>

<p>The main challenge for continuing the work of The PHP Foundation is to ensure sustainable sponsorship.</p>

<p>From a technical standpoint, the goal is to ensure that foundation developers work on valuable tasks.</p>

<h3 id="organization-goals">Organization goals</h3>

<ul>
<li>Onboard new major sponsors.</li>
<li>Explore strategic partnerships and marketing opportunities.</li>
<li>Further develop the Advisory Board initiative.</li>
<li>Grow the foundation's community.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="technical-goals">Technical goals</h3>

<ul>
<li>Ongoing maintenance and development of the PHP core.</li>
<li>Deliver the STF projects.</li>
<li>Improve the quality of the ideas and RFCs coming from the foundation.</li>
<li>Conduct research and surveys to define priorities.</li>
<li>Develop a high-level roadmap for PHP changes sponsored by the foundation.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="budget-plan-for-2024">Budget plan for 2024</h2>

<p>In 2024, two of our part-time developers extended commitment to go full-time, and we contracted 4 new developers.</p>

<p>We have also adjusted the compensation rates for developers to better reflect the market, as the rates had not changed since 2021. As a result, our budget significantly increased.</p>

<p>With this plan, we estimate our annual spending cap at approximately <strong>$840,000</strong> for developer compensation.</p>

<p>Additionally, we anticipate receiving <strong>€205,000</strong> from the STF investment. These funds will be allocated to developer reimbursements and our partnership with OSTIF.org for an external security audit.</p>

<p>Our collaboration with the OpenCollective platform has been positive, and we plan to continue operating under the umbrella of the Open Source Collective in 2024. This means that sponsorships we receive are reduced by 10% for Open Source Collective fees and 1–5% for payment processing fees.</p>

<h2 id="outro">Outro</h2>

<p>The PHP language is a living entity and, as such, requires continuous support to address developer issues, resolve security vulnerabilities, and has to evolve to meet the needs of the future.</p>

<p>Based on the strong second year of the foundation, we are excited to continue and multiply the efforts in the next years.</p>

<p>With your help, we continue the mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>

<section class="text-center mt-6">
    <div class="mb-14">
        <a href="/join" target="_blank" class="inline-block text-xl py-2 no-underline px-6 !text-white bg-[#7f52ff] rounded-3xl hover:bg-[rgba(127,82,255,.8)]">
            Join The PHP Foundation
        </a>
    </div>
</section>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/02/26/transparency-and-impact-report-2023/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/02/26/transparency-and-impact-report-2023/</id><updated>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation: Impact and Transparency Report 2022]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="executive-summary">Executive Summary</h2>

<p>At the end of 2022, The PHP Foundation is a collective of 10 volunteer administrators and 6&nbsp;part-time paid developers who make nearly half of the commits to PHP language core and extensions.</p>

<p>The collective received $580,000 in donations from organizations, and 1400 people backed or donated to The PHP Foundation individually.</p>

<p>The PHP Foundation’s main focus for 2022 has been the strengthening of maintenance for the PHP core, the project that lives in the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> GitHub repository. This project is the home of the PHP language, where PHP’s interpreter is developed. Everyone who uses PHP benefits in one way or another from the work that is done in this repository.</p>

<p>The 6 part-time developers employed by The PHP Foundation started in April 2022. From April through November (the time of this report), The PHP Foundation staff were responsible for nearly half of the commits and reviews made in the <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a> repository.</p>

<p>The foundation intends to expand its development efforts in 2023 by hiring an additional developer and increasing the number of hours that our current contracted developers are working. We plan to spend $678,000, including compensation and fees. Additional sponsor contributions will allow us to extend the developer team further.</p>

<p>Among other goals for 2023, we would like to address the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Extend the foundation developers team.</li>
<li>Establish processes for continuity beyond the current administration group.</li>
<li>Improve communication with sponsors and decide on the level of involvement for them.</li>
<li>Explore strategic partnerships and marketing opportunities.</li>
<li>Improve the quality of the ideas and RFCs coming from the foundation.</li>
<li>Develop a high-level roadmap and vision for PHP changes sponsored by the foundation.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="outset">Outset</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation was initiated by JetBrains, Automattic, Laravel, Acquia, Zend&nbsp;by&nbsp;Perforce, Private Packagist, Symfony, Craft CMS, and Tideways. It was publicly <a href="https://blog.jetbrains.com/phpstorm/2021/11/the-php-foundation/">launched</a> on November 22, 2021.</p>

<p>Intending to ensure the PHP language's success, a group of individuals and organizations have formed The PHP Foundation. Through part-time staff, community management, and a network of partner organizations, The PHP Foundation enables sustainable maintenance of the PHP interpreter.</p>

<h2 id="organizational-growth">Organizational Growth</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation's founding companies in 2021 included the following businesses, which took an active part in discussions about establishing and running the foundation:</p>

<p>Initial members:</p>

<ul>
<li>JetBrains</li>
<li>Automattic</li>
<li>Acquia</li>
<li>Private Packagist</li>
<li>Craft CMS</li>
<li>Tideways</li>
<li>Laravel</li>
<li>Zend by Perforce</li>
<li>Symfony</li>
<li>PrestaShop</li>
</ul>

<p>Representatives of these companies formed the initial administration group.</p>

<p>Many more companies with a vested interest in PHP’s prosperity, made a major financial contribution during the year. These are the companies that donated $10,000 or more:</p>

<ul>
<li>Livesport s.r.o.</li>
<li>OP.GG</li>
<li>EC-CUBE</li>
<li>Spryker</li>
<li>Polcode</li>
<li>Shopware AG</li>
<li>BASE, Inc.</li>
<li>Aternos GmbH</li>
<li>Digital Scholar</li>
<li>Ardennes-étape</li>
<li>RAKUS</li>
<li>Cambium Learning, Inc.</li>
<li>Paycom</li>
</ul>

<p>Overall, there are 145 organizations and 1220 individual sponsors <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation">on Open Collective</a>.</p>

<h4 id="taylor-otwell%2C-laravel%3A">Taylor Otwell, Laravel:</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Laravel is honored to support the PHP Foundation initiative as it continues to preserve, maintain, and mold the future of the PHP ecosystem.“</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="fabien-potencier%2C-symfony%3A">Fabien Potencier, Symfony:</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Symfony is very proud to support the PHP Foundation which helps build a bright and sustainable future for the PHP language, thanks to a large and diverse group of individuals and companies.“</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="jordi-boggiano%2C-private-packagist-%26-composer%3A">Jordi Boggiano, Private Packagist &amp; Composer:</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>“At Private Packagist we build and maintain the tools enabling a thriving PHP ecosystem. Our customers rely on the PHP language and runtime, so our contribution to the PHP Foundation helps ensure PHP receives a reliable amount of professional care.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="dries-buytaert%2C-acquia%2C-drupal%3A">Dries Buytaert, Acquia, Drupal:</h4>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Acquia and the Drupal community are proud to have helped with getting The PHP Foundation in place to provide broader and more resilient support to the mission of advancing and developing PHP. We are elated by the foundation's progress in a year and look forward to its future endeavors.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="events-timeline">Events Timeline</h2>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2022/report-2022/php-foundation-timeline-2022.svg" alt="Timeline" /></p>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-staff">The PHP Foundation Staff</h2>

<h3 id="application-process">Application Process</h3>

<p>We accepted applications for sponsorship from November through December 2021. We received about 100 resumes, and we’ve chosen 6 developers with a proven track record of contributions to the PHP language. We’ve created a shortlist of promising candidates for future expansion of the program or to replace participants, if necessary.</p>

<p>Up until March 2022, we were negotiating the text of contracts. The legal departments at JetBrains and OpenCollective both supported us in this.</p>

<h3 id="the-team-as-of-2022">The team as of 2022</h3>

<p>Starting in April, we contracted 6 developers to work on PHP:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Arnaud Le Blanc</strong> <a href="https://github.com/arnaud-lb">@arnaud-lb</a></li>
<li><strong>Derick Rethans</strong> <a href="https://github.com/derickr">@derickr</a></li>
<li><strong>Gina Peter Banyard</strong> <a href="https://github.com/Girgias">@Girgias</a></li>
<li><strong>Ilija Tovilo</strong> <a href="https://github.com/iluuu1994">@iluuu1994</a></li>
<li><strong>Jakub Zelenka</strong> <a href="https://github.com/bukka">@bukka</a></li>
<li><strong>Máté Kocsis</strong> <a href="https://github.com/kocsismate">@kocsismate</a></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="compensation-considerations">Compensation Considerations</h3>

<p>We have thought long and hard about what approach to use for remuneration. Given the different experiences of the chosen developers and the limited budget, we devised the following scheme.</p>

<p>We would take a conservative (safe) approach and accept 7 candidates with a proven record of work. We’d pay developers hourly, with a factor based on experience. This rate was chosen to meet developers' expectations, but to remain within the allocated budget.</p>

<p>In 2022, we offered all developers a 6-month contract to start. They all work as freelance contractors. In 2023, we offer yearly contracts.</p>

<p>With such an approach, we were planning to spend $329,000 per year, which was a safe number based on the funding at that time.</p>

<p>One of the candidates dropped out, and we eventually accepted only 6 candidates. That is one of the reasons we spent less money than expected. But sticking to our conservative approach made more sense to us in the initial year than spending everything at once, as it allowed us to build up savings to even out fluctuating income in the future.</p>

<h2 id="goals-for-2022">Goals for 2022</h2>

<p>The primary goal for the foundation in 2022 was to <strong>hire developers to maintain the PHP core</strong>.</p>

<p>We consider this goal accomplished. We'll look in depth at how much work has been done in the next section. The foundation demonstrated its reliability and effectiveness. We rolled out a sustainable process for supporting contributors. Now we are ready to scale and grow.</p>

<h2 id="contributions-to-php-core">Contributions to PHP Core</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation’s main focus has been contributions to <a href="https://github.com/php/php-src">php/php-src</a>, the primary repository for the PHP language.</p>

<h3 id="day-to-day-work">Day-to-day work</h3>

<p>On a daily basis, the PHP Foundation staff team contributes to the open-source repositories of the <a href="https://github.com/php">PHP GitHub organization</a>. The foundation team contributes in many forms: filing issues, reviewing pull requests, participating in discussions on mailing lists, triaging issues, submitting RFC proposals.</p>

<p>In this document, four categories of contributions are presented in more detail: commits to php/src, reviews of pull requests on php/src, submitted RFC documents, and documentation work.</p>

<h3 id="commits-to-php">Commits to PHP</h3>

<p>The following chart summarizes the number of commits made to the php/php-src repository from April to November, 2022.</p>

<ul>
<li>Total by The PHP Foundation: 683</li>
<li>Total other: 885</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2022/report-2022/commits_chart.svg" alt="Commits chart" /></p>

<h3 id="reviews">Reviews</h3>

<p>The diagram summarizes the number of pull request reviews made in the php/php-src repository from April to November, 2022.</p>

<ul>
<li>Total by The PHP Foundation: 283</li>
<li>Total other: 551</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/post-images/2022/report-2022/reviews_chart.svg" alt="Reviews chart" /></p>

<h3 id="rfcs">RFCs</h3>

<p>Below are the RFC proposals authored or co-authored by The PHP Foundation developers from April to November, 2022.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/readonly_classes">Readonly classes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/deprecate_dollar_brace_string_interpolation">Deprecate ${} string interpolation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/null-false-standalone-types">Allow null and false as stand-alone types</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/true-type">Add true type</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/dnf_types">Disjunctive Normal Form Types</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/fetch_property_in_const_expressions">Fetch properties of enums in const expressions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/dynamic_class_constant_fetch">Dynamic class constant fetch</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.php.net/rfc/auto-capture-closure">Short Closures 2.0</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-brand-%26-public-channels">The PHP Foundation brand &amp; public channels</h2>

<p>The PHP Foundation represents a community of core PHP developers and advocates for the PHP programming language.The channels listed below were used by the PHP Foundation for public communication:</p>

<ul>
<li>9,302 Twitter followers <a href="https://twitter.com/thephpf">https://twitter.com/thephpf</a></li>
<li>1,533 LinkedIn page followers <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/85931483/admin/">https://www.linkedin.com/company/85931483/admin/</a></li>
<li>1,441 Collective updates subscribers <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/updates">https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/updates</a></li>
<li>650 PHP Core Roundup subscribers <a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/roundup/">https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/roundup/</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/Ayeshlive">Ayesh Karunaratne</a> assisted us in publishing 7 iterations of the PHP Core Roundup blog posts, which provide a summary of the most recent PHP core updates, bug fixes, proposals, and other developments:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/roundup/">https://thephp.foundation/blog/tag/roundup/</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The PHP Foundation admins also participated in two conferences:</p>

<ul>
<li>Forum PHP, Paris [<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JBPtPy9iSP0">video</a>]</li>
<li>International PHP Conference, Munich [<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nmb-_66RArs">video</a>]</li>
</ul>

<p>Published a case study on the OpenCollective blog:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://blog.opencollective.com/php-foundation-alive-and-kicking/">https://blog.opencollective.com/php-foundation-alive-and-kicking/</a></li>
</ul>

<p>The PHP Foundation won the Next Generation Award at the Open Source Awards by All Things Open:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/MLHacks/status/1587805042282840073">https://twitter.com/MLHacks/status/1587805042282840073</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-php-foundation-governance">The PHP Foundation Governance</h2>

<p>The Administration group consists of veteran PHP core developers, PHP community leaders, representatives of the founding companies, and other key stakeholders.</p>

<p>We spent some time discussing how to organize management effectively. However, we concluded that it was worth focusing on our primary goal early on.</p>

<p>So for the first year, we decided to keep the group of administrators declared at the launch active. And make it invite-only for the first year.</p>

<p>This allowed us to move faster. However, the negative effect is definitely the lack of transparency in the process.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, this group will continue in 2023. And one of the goals will be to provide more transparency and establish a level of involvement for other key stakeholders from the PHP world.</p>

<p>We intend to make the ground rules more clear over the coming year, including the terms of participating in The PHP Foundation's governance and technical steering activities.</p>

<h2 id="financial-report">Financial report</h2>

<p>In 2022, PHP Foundation was financially backed by organizations and individuals with the goal of paying a competitive salary to as many core developers as possible.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
  <th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
  <td>• Total contributed by sponsors and individuals before fees: $712,484</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• Fees: $90,273</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• Total raised: $622,211</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• From organizations: 77%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• From individuals: 23%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• Recurring: 39.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• One-Time: 60.5%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• Paid to developers in 2022: $133,285</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• Current balance: $488,635</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>&nbsp;</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>• Planned expenses for 2023: $678,000</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p><br>
All incoming and outgoing transactions of The PHP Foundation are publicly available to view for anyone, not just sponsors of the foundation: <a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation#category-BUDGET">https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation#category-BUDGET</a></p>

<h3 id="all-financial-contributions-from-sponsors">All Financial Contributions From Sponsors</h3>

<p><a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/transactions?kind=ADDED_FUNDS%2CCONTRIBUTION"><img src="/assets/post-images/2022/report-2022/financial_contributions.png" alt="Financial Contributions chart" /></a></p>

<h3 id="expenses">Expenses</h3>

<p><a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/expenses">https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/expenses</a></p>

<p><a href="https://opencollective.com/phpfoundation/expenses"><img src="/assets/post-images/2022/report-2022/expenses.png" alt="Expenses chart" /></a></p>

<h2 id="why-did-we-not-spend-all-donated-funds%3F">Why did we not spend all donated funds?</h2>

<p>There were multiple reasons for this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Our projected budget was planned in December 2021, and the developers only started working in April.</li>
<li>One of the top-rated candidates to whom we had allocated a large budget dropped out for 2022 and this significantly reduced our spending.</li>
<li>Being a young organization, we felt that having a bigger buffer is a wiser choice for the first year.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="goals-for-2023">Goals for 2023</h2>

<p>Our foremost mission remains the same: <strong>maintain and develop the PHP language</strong>. In this regard, we have two groups of more specific goals for the next year.</p>

<p>From an organization perspective, the main challenge will be to grow in a way that ensures the long-term sustainability of the foundation and the PHP language.</p>

<p>From a technical standpoint, we'd like our work to be more meaningful, in the interest of PHP users, and oriented toward a common direction rather than uncoordinated, more or less random ideas.</p>

<h3 id="organization-goals">Organization goals</h3>

<ul>
<li>Extend the foundation developers team.</li>
<li>Grow the community of the foundation.</li>
<li>Improve communication and provide clear benefits for sponsors.</li>
<li>Explore strategic partnerships and marketing opportunities.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="technical-goals">Technical goals</h3>

<ul>
<li>Ongoing maintenance and development of  the PHP core.</li>
<li>Improve the quality of the ideas and RFCs coming from the foundation.</li>
<li>Develop a high-level roadmap and vision for PHP changes sponsored by the foundation.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="budget-plan-for-2023">Budget plan for 2023</h2>

<p>In 2022, all sponsored developers worked part-time, between 1 and 2 days per week.</p>

<p>In 2023, almost all developers indicated a desire to increase the amount of time they devote to PHP, ranging from working on PHP for 2 days a week to full-time.</p>

<p>As a result, we will pay for the equivalent time of nearly 4 full-time employees in 2023, which is close to double the 2022 commitment.</p>

<p>With this plan, we expect to spend about $600,000 per year on paying developers’ compensation.</p>

<p>Our collaboration with the OpenCollective platform has been positive, and we plan to continue operating under the umbrella of OpenSourceCollective in 2023. This means that in addition to the above-mentioned costs, we will also incur 10% in OpenCollective fees and about 3% in payment processing fees.</p>

<h3 id="what-if-the-foundation-has-extra-funds-in-2023%3F">What if the foundation has extra funds in 2023?</h3>

<p>We'd like to set aside at least 50% of an annual budget in reserves for unforeseen events.</p>

<p>If the PHP Foundation receives additional donations, we would be delighted to scale our efforts:</p>

<ul>
<li>Open the application form for new developers</li>
<li>Hire a technical writer to work on the documentation</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="thank-you%21">Thank you!</h2>

<p>The PHP language is a living entity and, as such, requires continuous support to address developer issues, resolve security vulnerabilities, and evolve to meet the needs of the future.</p>

<p>Based on the strong first year of the foundation, we are excited to continue and multiply the efforts in the next years.</p>

<p>With your help, we continue the mission to support, advance, and develop the PHP language.</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/11/22/transparency-and-impact-report-2022/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2022/11/22/transparency-and-impact-report-2022/</id><updated>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet team.blue: A PHP Foundation Sponsor supporting the language at the core of its ecosystem]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Starting January 2026, <strong>team.blue</strong> joined the PHP Foundation as a <strong>Gold Sponsor</strong>, reinforcing its long-term commitment to supporting the open-source technologies that power millions of businesses across Europe.</p>

<p><a href="https://team.blue/">team.blue</a> is a leading AI-powered digital enabler serving small and medium businesses (SMBs) and agencies across Europe. With more than 4,000 experts, 3.3 million customers, and operations in over 22 countries, team.blue provides businesses with the digital tools they need to build, grow, and scale online. Its ecosystem spans domains, hosting, cloud solutions, website and e-commerce tools, and a fast-growing portfolio of AI-driven SaaS products. For team.blue, PHP represents a foundational technology across its platforms and services.</p>

<h2 id="php%3A-the-engine-behind-team.blue%27s-platforms">PHP: the engine behind team.blue's platforms</h2>

<p>PHP's performance, stability, and extensive ecosystem also provide a scalable basis for delivering AI-powered capabilities and intelligent user journeys, enabling million SMBs to grow and succeed online. PHP underpins:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Shared hosting and managed WordPress products</strong> at brands like Combell, Register.it, and TransIP.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>PHP-based SaaS products</strong> (core app logic, integrations, and day-to-day feature work).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Internal tools and systems</strong> used across the group.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>PHP's mature ecosystem and proven scalability allow team.blue to build sophisticated digital tools that help SMBs and agencies grow online, demonstrating how the language powers modern high-traffic platforms across diverse use cases.</p>

<p>Discover more about the team.blue ecosystem: <a href="https://team.blue/our-ecosystem/">https://team.blue/our-ecosystem/</a></p>

<h2 id="giving-back-to-the-php-community">Giving back to the PHP community</h2>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-kirk-barlow">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“Open-source communities have always been essential to how we build and scale. PHP sits at the core of our hosting and WordPress ecosystem, so we are proud to give back and support the Foundation in ensuring its long-term growth. This sponsorship reinforces our belief that open-source thrives when everyone contributes.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/post-images/2026/team-blue/kirk-barlow.png" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Kirk Barlow, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Group Chief Technical Officer, team.blue</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p>As a Gold Sponsor, team.blue is putting tangible support behind PHP, helping accelerate progress, maintain strong security, and back the ecosystem globally, while directly supporting the essential work of maintenance, continuous improvement, and ensuring the language remains ready for what comes next.</p>

<p>Learn more about team.blue and its mission to make online business success simpler: <a href="https://team.blue/">https://team.blue/</a></p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2026/01/26/meet-team-blue-php-foundation-sponsor/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2026/01/26/meet-team-blue-php-foundation-sponsor/</id><updated>Mon, 26 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry><entry><author><name>Roman Pronskiy</name><uri>https://twitter.com/pronskiy</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Joining Forces for Open Source Cybersecurity Standards]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The PHP Foundation, alongside leading open source organizations including the <a href="https://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>, <a href="https://www.blender.org/about/foundation/">Blender Foundation</a>, <a href="https://www.openssl.org/">OpenSSL Software Foundation</a>, <a href="https://www.python.org/psf-landing/">Python Software Foundation</a>, <a href="https://foundation.rust-lang.org/">Rust Foundation</a>, and <a href="https://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse Foundation</a>, is excited to announce a collaborative initiative aimed at establishing common cybersecurity standards in alignment with the European Union’s <a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/library/cyber-resilience-act">Cyber Resilience Act (CRA)</a>.</p>

<p>This initiative, hosted by the Eclipse Foundation, will focus on creating specifications for secure software development rooted in open source best practices.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>We hope that our specifications could inform the formal standardisation processes of at least one of the European Standards Organisations. Given the tight time horizon for implementation of the CRA, we believe that this immediate start will provide a constructive environment to host the technical discussions necessary for the stewards, contributors, and adopters of open source to meet the requirements set forth in these new regulations.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At The PHP Foundation, we are committed to supporting the open source community, ensuring that the PHP language and its ecosystem are prepared for the upcoming regulatory changes.</p>

<p>For more information, see the <a href="https://eclipse-foundation.blog/2024/04/02/open-source-community-cra-compliance/">full announcement on the Eclipse Foundation website</a>.</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/04/02/open-source-community-cra-compliance-initiative/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2024/04/02/open-source-community-cra-compliance-initiative/</id><updated>Tue, 02 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry></feed>
