<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title><![CDATA[The PHP Foundation]]></title><description><![CDATA[Supporting, Advancing, and Developing the PHP Language]]></description><updated>2026-02-27T12:56:02+00:00</updated><entry><author><name>The PHP Foundation</name><uri>https://thephp.foundation</uri></author><title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcoming Elizabeth Barron as the New Executive Director of The PHP Foundation]]></title><content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're excited to welcome <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/elizabethn">Elizabeth Barron</a> as the next Executive Director of The PHP Foundation, following a thorough process led by our search committee of <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nilsadermann/">Nils Adermann</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sebastian-bergmann-phpunit">Sebastian Bergmann</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lornajane/">Lorna Mitchell</a>, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/benramsey/">Ben Ramsey</a>.</p>

<p>Elizabeth brings a rare combination of deep roots in the PHP community and proven leadership in open-source governance. She co-founded a volunteer-based nonprofit dedicated to supporting women and non-binary individuals in the PHP industry, served as Community Manager at GitHub where she led developer outreach programs including the Patchwork initiative, and has been active in CHAOSS – a project focused on open-source community health metrics.</p>

<p>Her experience spanning community building, fundraising, outreach operations, and open-source strategy makes her a natural fit to lead the foundation into its next chapter.</p>

<p>As previously announced, founding Executive Director <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/pronskiy/">Roman Pronskiy</a> is transitioning to focus on his growing role at <a href="https://www.jetbrains.com/">JetBrains</a>, while continuing to serve on the Board of Directors. Roman will work closely with Elizabeth to ensure a smooth handover.</p>

<p><figure class="max-w-screen-md mx-auto text-center mb-6" id="quote-elizabeth-barron">
    <svg class="w-10 h-10 mx-auto mb-3 text-gray-400" aria-hidden="true" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 18 14">
        <path d="M6 0H2a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3H2a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Zm10 0h-4a2 2 0 0 0-2 2v4a2 2 0 0 0 2 2h4v1a3 3 0 0 1-3 3h-1a1 1 0 0 0 0 2h1a5.006 5.006 0 0 0 5-5V2a2 2 0 0 0-2-2Z"/>
    </svg>
    <blockquote>
        <p class="italic text-gray-900">“In just a few years, The PHP Foundation has built something remarkable, and I'm honored to take on this role and continue that work. PHP powers a huge part of the web, and I'm excited to work with the Board, our core developers, and the broader PHP community to strengthen and expand the Foundation's impact so that together we can ensure PHP thrives for decades to come.”</p>
    </blockquote>
    <figcaption class="flex items-center justify-center mt-3 space-x-3 rtl:space-x-reverse">
        <img class="w-10 h-10 rounded-full" src="/assets/team/elizabeth_barron.jpeg" alt="profile picture">
        <div class="flex items-center">
            <cite class="pl-0.5 font-medium text-gray-900">Elizabeth Barron, </cite>
            <cite class="pl-1 text-gray-500">Executive Director, The PHP Foundation</cite>
        </div>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
</p>

<p><br>
Please join us in welcoming Elizabeth. We're looking forward to what's ahead.
🐘💜</p>
]]></content><link href="https://thephp.foundation/blog/2026/02/27/welcoming-elizabeth-barron-new-executive-director/"/><id>https://thephp.foundation/blog/2026/02/27/welcoming-elizabeth-barron-new-executive-director/</id><updated>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</updated></entry></feed>
